<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The cause use cure of feare. Or, strong consolations (the consolations of God) cordiall at all times, but most comfortable now in these uncomfortable times, to fixe, quiet, and stablish the heart, though the earth shake, and make it stand stil, to see the salvation of the Lord. Taken from Gods mouth, and penned by Hezekiah VVoodward, that all his servants may have assured confidence for ever.</title>
            <author>Woodward, Ezekias, 1590-1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 221 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96884</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3481</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E90_23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1487</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859753</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859753</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111850</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96884)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111850)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 16:E90[23])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The cause use cure of feare. Or, strong consolations (the consolations of God) cordiall at all times, but most comfortable now in these uncomfortable times, to fixe, quiet, and stablish the heart, though the earth shake, and make it stand stil, to see the salvation of the Lord. Taken from Gods mouth, and penned by Hezekiah VVoodward, that all his servants may have assured confidence for ever.</title>
                  <author>Woodward, Ezekias, 1590-1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 56, 59-66, 65-71, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Underhill, and are to be sold at the signe of the Bible in Woodstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Text continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: the 3 in the imprint date is crossed out; "feb: 25 1642".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fear --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fear --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111850:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Of</hi> FEARE.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The</hi> CAUSE</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The</hi> VSE</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The</hi> CURE</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>OR,</hi> Strong Conſolations <hi>(The Conſolations of</hi> God) Cordiall at all times, but moſt comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble now in theſe uncomfortable times, To fixe, quiet, and ſtabliſh the heart, though the earth ſhake, and make it ſtand ſtil, To ſee the ſalvation of The <hi>Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Taken from GODS mouth, And</hi> Penned by HEZEKIAH VVOODWARD, <hi>That all His Servants may have aſſured confidence for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSAL. 56. 3, 9.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>What time I am afraid I will truſt in Thee: When I cry unto Thee, Then ſhall mine enemies turne back: this I know, for</hi> God <hi>is for me, He will ſave me,</hi> becauſe <hi>I Truſt in Him.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. 40.</bibl>
               <p>Nil terribile, niſi ipſe timor.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Underhill,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Bible in <hi>Woodſtreet.</hi> 1643.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:111850:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:111850:2"/>
            <head>To the Right HONOVRABLE, Iſaac Pennington, LORD MAjOR <hi>Of the City of LONDON.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y the Bleſſing of <hi>God</hi> upon this treatiſe (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining His own directions there) it can heale the heart and the hand <hi>palſied</hi> with feare: It will be no diſhonour then to take it into your hand, and to lay theſe directions (if it can be) yet cloſer to your heart, whereby the City of God have been a <hi>quiet habitation,</hi> 
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Eſay 33. 20.</note> when, as now, The <hi>blaſt</hi> of the <hi>terrible ones</hi> have made the earth to ſhake and tremble under us: And you now, with ſuch as you, that <hi>love, feare, truſt</hi> GOD, <hi>doing</hi> your <hi>duty,</hi> and maintaining your <hi>watch,</hi> doe maintayne PEACE, <hi>and at ſuch a time.</hi> 
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Ezra. 4. 17.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Peace is good at all times, but ever beſt in the worſt times, <hi>perilous</hi> and <hi>feirce,</hi> as are the times of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, <hi>troublous</hi> evermore: when hands and <note n="*" place="margin">Dan. 9. 28. Jer. 20. 3.</note> Tongues are bent to make the <hi>City</hi> of GOD MAGOR MISSABIB, <hi>terrour on every ſide:</hi> Then peace is good; Then cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls
<pb facs="tcp:111850:3"/> are ſo indeed, ſtrong conſolations (they are the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations of GOD) <hi>at ſuch a time.</hi> Peace in and with the world is good, if it could be had upon good termes: But that it not poſſible. The world will love their own, And they ſhall have peace, ſuch as the world can give; They, who can comply with the world; can give out unto them the right hand of fellowſhip, to thruſt <hi>Chriſt</hi> from His Throne, and out of the world: theſe ſhall have peace, for they are the worlds <hi>firſt born,</hi> and right hands of the times, but you cannot do ſo. Such a peace, <hi>peace</hi> without <hi>truth</hi> is of vile eſteeme with you, you abhor it at ſuch a price, and upon ſuch termes as the world bids for it, and doth purchaſe the ſame. You <hi>follow peace with all men,</hi> and <hi>Holyneſſe</hi> (That is a point of the higheſt wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome) <hi>without which no man ſhall ſee the</hi> LORD: you <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue</hi> 
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">Heb. 11. 14. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> this <hi>peace,</hi> as others perſecute it: your zeale cannot boile higher then to their As, as they perſecute it. Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue it ſo ſtill, and if you overtake it not, (for it flees from you (elſe you ſhould not need to <hi>purſue</hi> it) if you cannot eſtabliſh peace in the <hi>City;</hi> yet, in that you have done your <hi>office,</hi> you have <hi>peace</hi> in your ſoul, a <hi>peace,</hi> which <hi>paſſeth all underſtanding;</hi> for whatſoever things are <hi>true</hi> 
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">Phil. 4. 7. 8.</note> are <hi>he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt;</hi> are <hi>juſt;</hi> are <hi>pure;</hi> are <hi>lovely;</hi> are of <hi>good report,</hi> theſe things you have done, and will doe, you have aſſured confidence now in this which follows, <hi>and the peace of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">ver. 9.</note> GOD <hi>ſhall be with you.</hi> What a good word is this, and at ſuch a time, when the Adverſary doth, as in all times he hath done (it is no new thing, when the <hi>breaches</hi> of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalems <hi>walls</hi> are making up) he ſends, and writes, and lies, and rayles, and blaſphemes, what doth he not, after his manner, <hi>to make the work to ceaſe</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Nehe. 4. and 6.</note>. You know your charge concerning him, <hi>Anſwer him</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">2 King. 18. 36.</note> 
               <hi>not;</hi> you look to the anſwer from a good conſcience, That, in zeale to you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:111850:3"/> LORD, The <hi>Cities</hi> peace and crown of rejoycing, you have done and ſpoken hitherto: And you are reſolved ſo to do ſtill, To ſtand up for <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſtill, To ſhoulder up His Throne ſtill; And you have made up your reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, you know what it will <hi>coſt</hi> you, poſſible as much as it hath coſt All His faithfull ſervants in all ages at <hi>ſuch a time;</hi> And having ſo wiſely counted your <hi>Coſt,</hi> you can <hi>mock</hi> at <hi>feare;</hi> and laugh at your Adverſaries, as the LORD doth, <hi>ſeeing their day is comming</hi> 
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">Pſal. 37.</note>: for their rage riſeth high, and their riſing by ſteps that way, are but ſteps and degrees to utter deſtruction, which ſhall riſe as their rage doth, unto <hi>heaven,</hi> and be <hi>lifted up, even to the skies.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Jer. 51. 9.</note> You cannot be deceived now, as, we thinke, good <hi>Jeremiah</hi> was; He <hi>heard the defaming of many, fear was on every ſide,</hi> and he heard a <hi>cry:</hi> nay he cryed out himſelfe, and ſaid, <hi>Violence and ſpoile!</hi> Then ſayes <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jer. 20. 8. 10. <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> O LORD, Thou <hi>haſt deceived me,</hi> and I was <hi>deceived.</hi> He was indeed, but GOD did not deceive him; He had ſet up <hi>Jeremtah,</hi> and made him ſo ſtrong for Himſelf, and for <hi>ſuch a time as that,</hi> when the adverſaries deeds and words would be as hard as iron againſt the Truth and him; but <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſhould be hard enough for them; The Adverſary might, to as good purpoſe, ſtrike his hand againſt a rock as ſtrike <hi>Jeremiah:</hi> ſhall iron <hi>breake</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jer. 15. 12.</note> 
               <hi>the Northern iron and ſteele?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No, no, the Adverſary was hard, and cruell, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent againſt <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> but <hi>God</hi> made <hi>Jeremiah</hi> too hard for them all, as He will all His faithfull ones, (ſtanding up for Him) a <hi>defenced City and a ſtrong brazen</hi> 
               <note place="margin">ver. 20.</note> 
               <hi>wall:</hi> That was the promiſe to <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> and in him to all faithfull ones, many thouſand yeeres agoe, and you have the comfort, and your faſt ſtanding from it at this day; <hi>The blaſt of the terrible ones, what can it doe?</hi> It was
<pb facs="tcp:111850:4"/> anſwered long agoe; As much as a blaſt of winde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a brazen wall, ſo the <hi>Spirit</hi> ſlights what fleſh can do againſt Him: <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſay 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 4.</note> They ſhall ſight againſt Thee (The Adverſary will make an experiment, what mettal you are made of, ſo you muſt expect) but <hi>they ſhall not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile</hi> 
               <note place="margin">ſer. 1. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>againſt Thee;</hi> There is the comfort, and it is yours, who wil ſtand up for God <hi>and at ſuch a time.</hi> As your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation from the World cannot deceive you (after the experiences of all the faithfull that have ſtood up for <hi>God)</hi> All hath been done againſt them, All ſhall be done againſt you, that <hi>Angry Nations</hi> can doe, <hi>Atheiſts</hi> and <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſwelled with wrath, and big with rage: So, nor wil The <hi>Lord,</hi> The <hi>Hope</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and Saviour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>in time of trouble,</hi> He will not deceive you. Then you ſhall ſee your ſtrength preſently, that you are better bottomed then are the <hi>perpetuall Hills,</hi> and <hi>everlaſting Mountains,</hi> a ſight worth the beholding and at ſuch a time. And becauſe your work is now to read the times, not book<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s; To get underſtanding in them, and what Iſrael ought to doe; and becauſe you feele ſo many ſhocks and thruſts made againſt you to make you fall, noman more; I will make bold to draw out this Epiſtle (againſt my diſpoſition and judgement) beyond its uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all proportion to perſons of your ranke; That I may make known not to you but to the world of ungodly men, where your ſtrength lyes. Then paſt all queſtion it will be ſaid, their <hi>rock</hi> is not as your <hi>Rock,</hi> the enemies themſelves being Judges.</p>
            <p>I have by the aſſiſtance of the great Phyſitian writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, I hope, from His Mouth, touching the <hi>Cure of Fear,</hi> your Lordſhip may have the marrow of it here.</p>
            <p>Firſt, You <hi>magnify your Office,</hi> contending for Chriſt againſt His enemies, who would ſhoulder Him out of
<pb facs="tcp:111850:4"/> His Throne and out of His Kingdome; Theſe enemies are in a rage, becauſe you are a friend to Chriſt; they fight againſt you, and have faire hopes too, they ſhall take <hi>revenge on you.</hi> Let them hope till their day comes, when their fleſh muſt conſume away, <hi>and their eyes in their holes,</hi> and their <hi>tongues in their mouth,</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Zech. 14. 12.</note> you have the anſwer of a good conſcience within: A GOD to go to, His promiſe to cleave to, which you find, in the place you were upon even now; <hi>They ſhall not prevaile againſt thee,</hi> for <hi>I am with thee, ſaith the</hi> LORD, <hi>to deliver thee:</hi> And not barely ſo, but a <hi>Mighty</hi> TERRIBLE <hi>one:</hi> There <note place="margin">Jer. 20. 11.</note> you may reade what follows, to your everlaſting com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and confuſion of your Adverſaries. This anſwers all that can be ſaid or done againſt you, all <hi>hard words and ungodly deeds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>GOD <hi>is with you;</hi> All His attributes, power, wiſdom, goodneſſe ſhall be laid out for you, and for all like you, who lay out themſelves, all they are and have for Him.</p>
            <p>You have now, as All His faithfull ſervants have, written this downe in the Table of your heart. Now you may write what you will, for a <hi>Legion,</hi> now marching on againſt the <hi>City of God,</hi> you can <hi>ſet down quickly</hi> (before feare ſurpriſeth the heart, for it hath ſudden and violent motions) and write, <hi>fifty:</hi> what? <hi>froggs, lice, flies.</hi> So The Church deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her proud adverſary, that terrible one, laughing him to ſcorne, regarding his huge Hoſt, not ſo much as <note place="margin">2 Kings 91. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> a legion of froggs, an armie of lice, or ſwarme of flies. Theſe Egyptian, theſe Northerne Troops (the Armies of The <hi>Lord</hi> of Hoſts have been a plague to the Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, and other Nations, as idolatrous as they, never ſo to a people with whom <hi>God is, a mighty terrible One.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:111850:5"/> Certain it is That he, who wil ſearch into the records of time, ſhall never read, that an Army of Papiſts, a People of <hi>Gods curſe,</hi> ever did the Church hurt: They have annoyed it, that is granted: For frogs, and lice, and flies in aboundance, can doe ſo, (&amp; yet not ſo much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe God pleaſeth, but if ſo, then) for the <hi>Churches good.</hi> Idolatrous Iſraell have pillaged Judah, and have taken away much ſpoile (ſometime the Lord made the Adverſary vomit it up again:) their rage has reached yet higher, but then their day haſteneth as now it doth, and they come down mightily, this alſo was forthe Churches good. Indeed, and to contract; every thing, which we commonly call evill, nay, what properly is ſo, (ſinne it ſelfe) is for the good of thoſe with whom the LORD is, a God in covenant, our God. You ſee your ſtability now, your ſecurity, your exceeding comfort. It is good to looke upon it with all your eyes, well to conſider on it at ſuch a time as this, leſt you fainte in your minde, as a faithfull ſervant of the <hi>Lord</hi> did, <hi>eying</hi> his Adverſaries, and not obſerving his ſtanding, nor his ſtrength where it was, and then he ſpeakes unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſedly with his lips. <note n="c" place="margin">Jer. 22. 14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Truly I thinke it my Duty, being upon ſuch a Subject, and at ſuch a time, to make ſome enlargement to my <hi>Epiſtle</hi> here, now that tongues and hands are ſo buſied to cauſe feare, which is ſo encroaching, you cannot keep it out with all your power, unleſſe you hold faſt ſtill-faſt to this <hi>ſtrong hold, I will be with thee a mighty terrible One,</hi> bleſſed be His name for that promiſe.</p>
            <p>You ſhall heare your ſelfe charged as <hi>Job,</hi> perhaps by <hi>Eliphas</hi> a friend, and that, if you will obſerve it <hi>(a)</hi> you will think very ſtrange, and nothing <hi>now</hi> that is <hi>new.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob. 22. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 6, &amp;c.</note> Your enemies, and they are many, all that are ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb facs="tcp:111850:5"/> to Chriſt, they will for His ſake defame you, ſpeak all manner of evill againſt you, for they call you <hi>by their</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exulem me de ſuo nomine vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat. Cic. parad.</note> 
               <hi>owne names.</hi> While they reproach <hi>God</hi> in you, you feele a <hi>ſword</hi> in your bones: <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal 42. 10</note> But in reference to your ſelfe, and that good thing within you, <hi>the ſouls pillow,</hi> you goe away rejoycing, bearing the reproach; and, being at <hi>peace</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Recta conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia culcitra animae.</note> with <hi>God,</hi> no more moved then the Moone is at the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of dogs. Behold her courſe, ſaith one, <note n="*" place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> the courſe of the Sun too, they run on like mighty Giants: ſuch is the courſe of a <hi>godly</hi> man, he is for <hi>God, God</hi> is with him, he breaks through all difficulties in this way, as through <hi>ſpiders webs:</hi> he is above all, <hi>hard words,</hi> and <hi>ungodly deeds,</hi> riding upon the high places of the earth. <note n="a" place="margin">Eſay. 58. 14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, you ſhall ſee the earth ſmitten <hi>terribly,</hi> that her bloud may be diſcovered, and her Idols there given up to the <hi>Moles</hi> and to the <hi>Bats;</hi> you ſhall feele it ſhake under you, and the Kingdomes totter like a drunken man. All the while you ſhall <hi>ſtand ſtill,</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 14. 13.</note> calme in your mind, beholding the <hi>ſalvation of GOD,</hi> for you ſtand up for Him, and He is <hi>with you</hi> as a <hi>Mighty Terrible One.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, you ſhall heare of War, and the deſolations that it cauſeth; Whether you ſhall live to heare that GODS <hi>peace</hi> is concluded on, and eſtabliſhed in the land, I cannot tell, nor, perhaps, the beſt <hi>Seer</hi> in your City: But this I can tell you, becauſe you have the Anſwer of a good conſcience, and can tell your ſelfe, you <hi>fear GOD,</hi> and you ſtand for <hi>Him,</hi> and <hi>He</hi> is with you, a <hi>God</hi> in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and a <hi>Mighty Terrible One,</hi> That you, and all ſuch as you, who follow <hi>peace,</hi> and <hi>holineſſe,</hi> ſhall have <hi>peace,</hi> not as the world gives, but peace in <hi>God.</hi> Oh how ſweet it is! and as ſure, as it is ſweet, in <hi>God;</hi> and yet ſweeter yet at ſuch a time, when the Kingdomes totter, the <hi>gods</hi> there are all ſtarved, nay when the heart-ſtrings and eye-
<pb facs="tcp:111850:6"/> ſtrings muſt break: O how ſweet is Peace then! ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then honey was to <hi>Jonathan,</hi> when his ſoule fainted. This <hi>peace</hi> is yours, for you are <hi>Chriſts,</hi> and Chriſt is GODS, <hi>Whoſe you are, and Whom you ſerve.</hi> This <hi>peace</hi> is yours, and now it paſſeth all <hi>underſtanding</hi> indeed, when you ſhall heare the moſt comfortable word that ever was ſpoken, <hi>Well done good and faithfull ſervant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the heritage of them that <hi>feare</hi> the LORD; hard words and ungodly deeds cannot diſcourage you now, for <hi>God</hi> is with you, there is your <hi>ſecurity</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chriſtum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe cum Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> ſumma ſecu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas: Paulum aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe cum Chriſto ſumma foelici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas.</hi> 1 Theſ. 4. 17, 18.</note>; you ſhal be with Him anon, there is your <hi>happineſſe; for ever with the Lord,</hi> you can comfort your ſelfe in theſe words.</p>
            <p>Heare me with patience one word more, touching the ſucceſſe of the <hi>great work</hi> in hand, and the <hi>ſecurity</hi> of this great <hi>City,</hi> where the <hi>Lord</hi> hath made you a <hi>Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and hath found you faithfull, which is your glory, but in The <hi>Lord.</hi> Surely, ſurely, the work ſhal proſper, for it is wrought by <hi>God;</hi> your <hi>City</hi> ſhall not be deſtroyed, for it is GODS <hi>City.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely a work carryed on with ſo many hands and hearts; ſo much life, and ſpirit, love, faith, patience, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be diſappointed of its end. And for the <hi>City</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Where are many thouſands that cannot ſpeak, yet is their language very moving with their <hi>Lord.</hi> Jonah 4. 11.</note>, her fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe is in her <hi>skirts</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Lam. 1 9.</note>; Ai and upon her forehead too: But yet a righteous people are there, and <hi>Gaius mine Hoſt</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 16. 23.</note>, and many ſuch as he: She is a refuge to the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, a great Sanctuarie at this <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>The day of Jacobs trouble.</hi> Jer. 30. 7.</note> time; and much good is found there: We doe not boaſt of her goodneſſe, but we boaſt in The <hi>Lord,</hi> Who hath inſtructed her to diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, To ſtand up for Him and His Cauſe above all the Cities, that are or ever were in the world, <hi>and at ſuch a time.</hi> Surely the <hi>Lord</hi> will watch over her; &amp; her Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men think ſo too, &amp; pray for her night and day. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they be ſuch, as never ſought <hi>God in vaine,</hi> they are
<pb facs="tcp:111850:6"/> bold and confident, That The <hi>Lord</hi> will watch over this City for good, it ſhal ſtil be ſaid, The LORD <hi>helpeth them;</hi> The <hi>North</hi> ſhall give in unto them, the <hi>ſouth</hi> ſhal not keep back: the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt</hi> ſhall confer unto them the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of the Land and of the Sea. But this is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement of all, <hi>Salvations will God appoint for walls and Bulwarks.</hi> I will conclude with the cloſe of a Pſalm, <hi>Let</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 48. 11, 12, 13</note> 
               <hi>mount Sion rejoyce, let the daughters of Judah be glad, becauſe of Thy judgements: walk about Sion, and go round about her, tell the towers thereof</hi> (A goodly proſpect, and <hi>at ſuch a time) Mark ye well her Bulwarks, conſider her palaces, that you may tell it to the generation following.</hi> What ſhall they tell? or what is this ſtrength? wherein doth it conſiſt? or where is it? for it is not viſible. It follows, <hi>For This</hi> GOD <hi>is our</hi> GOD <hi>for ever and ever: He will be our guide even</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 41. 13.</note> 
               <hi>unto death. Bleſſed be the Lord God of Iſrael from everlaſting and to everlaſting.</hi> AMEN <hi>and</hi> AMEN.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:111850:7"/>
            <head>By way of <hi>Preface</hi> to the <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Need not tell thee what the times are, how <hi>hard, fierce,</hi> and <hi>perillous;</hi> nor how we are diſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in them; ſo much thy very looks can tell me: The news, now a-dayes, is ſo legible, that he who runs may read it, and in moſt mens faces.</p>
            <p>There is a <hi>paſſion</hi> now, quick and ſtirring within us, which may ſtand us in great ſtead at this time, as it may be ordered and pointed; if in a right way, and to the right object, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can doe us better ſervice to ſtay and ſtabliſh us: but if out of the way, and from that object, nothing works us more miſchiefe: nothing more unſettles us. It will betray all our ſuccour; it will ſhake us, as a leafe with the wind, and make us flee as a Roe before the hunter.</p>
            <p>It were ſeaſonable now to reade a Lecture upon this paſsion of <hi>feare,</hi> not as a Philoſopher, but as a Chriſtian; I cannot ſay, ſo I have done; but I have beſtowed many ſad (yet quiet) thoughts upon its uncomfortable and unquiet motions; and here I have made them legible, That, though the adverſary doth all he can to make us afraid, yet he may not have his will <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 6.</note> ſo farre, as to make us afraid with <hi>any amazement,</hi> for we have made three Concluſions, are fixed thereupon, and reſolved to take the <hi>Product</hi> or <hi>Reſult</hi> therefrom, <hi>That we will doe our Duty,</hi> not diſquieting our ſelves about what The LORD will doe hereafter, or what our foes are doing now. The firſt Concluſion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That things ſtand at as great a diſtance from an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 9. 22.</note> 
               <hi>Peace,</hi> as Iſrael ſtood when the <hi>WITCHCRAFTS</hi> of their <hi>mother Jezebel,</hi> and her whoredomes were ſo many.
<pb facs="tcp:111850:7"/> If one man ſin againſt another, a third may take up the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and make an agreement betwixt them: <note n="d" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 25.</note> The caſe is not ſo here; Man hath ſinned againſt The <hi>Lord,</hi> and we have provoked Him to His face by our Idolatries and bloud-ſhed: Man ſhall not determine this caſe, a caſe of bloud, and betwixt <hi>GOD</hi> and <hi>Man.</hi> There may be eſſayes and overtures that way, to <hi>ſcab-over</hi> the <hi>matter,</hi> but it cannot be; the wound is deep, much venome in the hottome, it hath layne feſtring there theſe by paſt yeeres, three or foure, and now The <hi>Lord</hi> is ſearching into it, making <hi>inquiſition for bloud:</hi> and before He hath done (for that is His manner) He will find it out, and His <hi>ſword</hi> ſhall not reſt, till He hath <hi>required</hi> and avenged it. That is the firſt Concluſion. The adverſary makes a ſecond, That as</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. He hath done all he can by <hi>fraud,</hi> ſo he doth and will doe all he can by <hi>force,</hi> not to waſte and deſtroy onely, not to out <hi>Iſrael ſhort,</hi> but cleane off from being a Nation: So the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74.</note> Adverſary hath concluded now. And now the Church makes a third Concluſion, and thereon ſhe will fixe, and be eſtabliſhed for ever.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. That <hi>God</hi> will make His Church a <hi>cup</hi> of <hi>trembling</hi> in the adverſaries hand, as a <hi>burdenſome ſtone</hi> upon his <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 12. 2.</note> ſhoulders, as a <hi>torch of fire</hi> in a ſheafe, or amidſt ſtubble. The <note place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>Lord</hi> doth open <hi>His eyes upon His people;</hi> He doth plead His owne cauſe. So the Church hath concluded.</p>
            <p>I could ſet downe ſome Premiſes whence ſhe draws her Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, but it is her LORDS promiſe ſo; and that is enough, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven long ſince, but written <hi>for the generations to come.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74. 22, 23.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Reſult</hi> from hence is, <hi>That we do our duty,</hi> as the Church doth, &amp; not trouble our ſelves with unneceſſary quaeres, <hi>what, how,</hi> or <hi>when GOD</hi> will work: He works wonders e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day, and let Him work as He pleaſeth, He will work all for good, and all in the fitteſt ſeaſon. Let us <hi>doeour duty,</hi> that is
<pb facs="tcp:111850:8"/> our work; <hi>work out our ſalvation;</hi> &amp; for the <hi>ſalvation</hi> of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> by all ſuch means, wherein <hi>GOD, Nature, Grace,</hi> have given us a capacity, and power of working. We muſt lye on our face in deep humiliation, while the <hi>Joſhuahs</hi> are ſearching the tents, that the accurſed thing may be caſt out, for ſo they have commanded us. We muſt doe for the cauſe of Chriſt, <hi>as</hi> the <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall</hi> Lords, Devils, and men doe againſt Chriſt, to ſhoulder Him out of His throne: This is to doe our duty, to doe <hi>As,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo doing, we doe our duty heartily, and <hi>ſhall rejoyce in time to come;</hi> that is very comfortable, as we read it; but there is more comfort in it then ſo, we ſhall <hi>laugh at the time to come</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 21. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Ridet ad tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pera ſeq<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ontra.</note>: Not care ſo much for the Army in the north, as their fore-fathers did for an Army of <hi>frogs, lice,</hi> &amp; ſwarms of <hi>flies;</hi> nor for any other <hi>mountain</hi> in the way, for he ſhall be made a <hi>plaine:</hi> Wee have and will do our Duty; They that do ſo may laugh and ſing too.</p>
            <p>But theſe are but words, the <hi>Lord</hi> knows not the <hi>ſpeech,</hi> but the <hi>power</hi> of our <hi>doing our duty.</hi> And He put it into our hearts, and keep it there for ever. We can hardly ſet upon it, though we are ſet upon by the hand of violence, our gods are taken away from us, I mean that we dote upon, which quickned a man as dead in his body, as we in our ſpirits; For thus it was <q>The Phiſitians knew no way to quicken him out of his <hi>lethar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy</hi> but by gingling his baggs before him upon the table; then he awakened and ſtirred himſelfe up, for he would hold <note place="margin">Hor. li. 2. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Satyr. 3.</note> his bags, as long as he could hold his breath.</q> This <hi>god</hi> is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from us, our liberty too, and that is our <hi>god</hi> alſo; Nay our <hi>LORD Chriſt</hi> is taking fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> us, Who gives all to us, He is <hi>GOD</hi> indeed. Now or never we will bethink our ſelves, and lay out all we have &amp; are to keepe Him, the <hi>LIFE</hi> of our <hi>lives,</hi> and <hi>SOUL</hi> of our <hi>ſouls,</hi> we wil keepe Him. There is but this that can diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage us (and it is the greateſt encouragement in the world, if we can contend for Him) we may loſe our eſtates and lives too.
<pb facs="tcp:111850:8"/> That is true; All may be loſt, &amp; moſt happily loſt in ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention; Nay it is not <hi>loſt,</hi> it is <hi>gained,</hi> and the greateſt gain, for <hi>He is worthy,</hi> for Whoſe cauſe we do expend all this, if it be our deareſt blood, and all: He became <hi>poor</hi> for us, to make us <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8 9.</note> rich<hi rend="sup">e</hi>; nay, a <hi>Curſe</hi> for us, to make us a <hi>Bleſſing.</hi> If we think of this, goods ſhal go and life too, and bleſſe God with all our hearts, that He put ſuch a <hi>price</hi> into our hand, to lay out our ſelves for Chriſt, to ſuffer for Him: Indeed it is as glorious a work as to <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve</hi> in Him; we cannot do the one without the other, but ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hath the preheminence, that no man may be diſmayed at his ſufferings, if called thereunto, and for Chriſt, for <hi>unto you it</hi> is given in the behalfe of Chriſt, not onely to beleeve on Him, but <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip.</hi> 1. 29.</note> alſo to ſuffer for His ſake.</p>
            <p>I have done prefacing, The <hi>Lord</hi> give us underſtanding in the times, and what Iſrael ought to do.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV.</hi> 29. 25.</bibl>
               <p>The feare of man bringeth a ſnare: but who ſo putteth his truſt in The <hi>Lord,</hi> ſhall be ſafe.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:111850:9"/>
            <p> IT is ordered by the Committee of the Houſe of Commons in Parliament con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Printing, this 22. day of Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber 1642. that this booke Intituled <hi>(The uſefulneſſe of Feare, &amp;c.)</hi> be printed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John White.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111850:9"/>
            <head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>
                           <hi>Of</hi> FEARE.</head>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Just Cause</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The True Use</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Soveraign Cure</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The ſumme and ſcope of this Treatiſe; The kinds of Feare; The ſtrange effects there from; What the worſt effect; What the great deſigne of the Adverſary; How he proſecutes it; His advantage if he can effect it; His power and malice that way gives us juſt cauſe of feare.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. I.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Introduction to, and purpoſe of this Treatiſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ur <hi>Affections</hi> doe us the greateſt ſervice, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervice, that well can be imagined: and this they doe, as wee maſter them; or as they maſter us. If we maſter them, they are the <hi>winds</hi> of the ſoule, carrying it ſo as it is neither becalmed, that it moves not when it ſhould; nor yet toſſed, that it moves diſorderly: If they maſter us, they raiſe ſtorms there, and we are ſtorm-like, ſudden and violent, carryed as a ſhip in a tempeſt. If we maſter them, they are the very <hi>wings</hi> of the ſoule; A <hi>Prayer without them,</hi> (ſo we may ſay of any other performance) is like <hi>a bird without wings:</hi> 
                     <note n="(a)" place="margin">Oratio ſine malis, avis ſine alis.</note> If I <hi>cared for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> (ſaid <hi>Melancthon)</hi> I ſhould <hi>pray for nothing:</hi> 
                     <note n="(b)" place="margin">Si nihil cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarem, nihil Orarem.</note> If they maſter us, they are the <hi>clogs</hi> of the ſoule; or if they be as <hi>wings,</hi> it is to make us flee away from <hi>God,</hi> and goodneſſe; from our ſelves and Duty. Our Affections are the <hi>ſprings</hi> of all our ſervices to GOD: we are dry, and cold, and dead without them; with them (well ordered) the ſoule is ſet on work, and then the work
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111850:10"/> will be done, when the heart is upon it: <hi>David</hi> had prepared much for the houſe of GOD, himſelfe gives the reaſon, <hi>Becauſe I have ſet my</hi> AFFECTION <hi>to the houſe of my</hi> GOD. <note n="(c)" place="margin">1 Chr. 29. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Feare</hi> puts on the ſoule almoſt as faſt as <hi>Love</hi> doth, that great Centuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or puts it farther back: I cannot doe this and ſin; I muſt doe this, and why? <hi>Becauſe I have ſet my</hi> FEARE upon GOD; and <hi>knowing the</hi> TERROR <hi>of the</hi> LORD, <note n="(d)" place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 11.</note> I <hi>muſt perſwade men.</hi> In a word, weare as a dead ſea without our affections; and as a raging ſea if they exceed the bounds: And no affection beats more ſtrongly upon the ſoule, (and more like waves againſt the banks) to exceed its juſt bounds, and get over, then <hi>feare</hi> doth: and when it hath got over, no affection ſooner drowns the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, ſinks Reaſon, and ſo becomes a <hi>Paſſion</hi> indeed, vexatious and troubleſome: for where <hi>feare</hi> is (in exceſſe) there is <hi>tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> 
                     <note n="(e)" place="margin">1 John. 4. 18.</note> This tormenting <hi>Paſſion,</hi> the ſtilling its unreaſonable motions, is the ſubject of my Diſcourſe now; but GODS work, To calme the Spirit, to make it <hi>ſtand ſtill,</hi> when the earth ſhakes, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>(f)</hi> Exod. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Ne con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>un.</note> and the kingdomes <hi>are moved;</hi> I ſay, His work, Who <hi>chid</hi> the winds, and commanded the ſeas, and they obeyed <hi>Him, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently there followed a great calme.</hi> Feare, let alone to work its owne effects, (for like water it hath no bounds of its owne) is <note place="margin">
                        <hi>(g) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> Math. 8. 20.</note> in the heart, as the tongue in the body, <hi>kindleth a great fire</hi> 
                     <note n="(h)" place="margin">Jam. 3. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>there</hi> from every little matter, quickly raiſeth that little to a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging flame, which no man can quench, onely GOD can. And what way He commands and preſcribes us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (for we muſt keep to His preſcriptions, the ſame, which the <hi>whole City</hi> of GOD, All His People, have taken in all <hi>troublous times</hi> upward to this day) To reaſon with this unreaſonable Paſſion, To keep it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in bounds of juſt moderation, is the maine intendment of this Treatiſe, wherein, but in paſſage only, I muſt make cleare proofe to them, who will be as are many now adayes, <hi>willingly ignorant</hi> That the Citties <hi>feare</hi> is <hi>juſt</hi> and Reaſonable; That all the Cauſes and reaſons both, which can be imagined, from within, and from without, commands the wiſeſt men to <hi>feare,</hi> yea commends them ſo fearing, for they are wiſe men, they can not be <hi>afraid with any amazement.</hi> But that I may begin in order, I muſt diſtinguiſh firſt,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:111850:10"/>
                  <head>CHAP. II.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Kindes of feare, The diſquietings therefrom, and ſharp effects; The worſt effect of all, is,</hi> It maketh a man chooſe ſinne rather then affliction.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <p n="1">1. THere is a <hi>feare,</hi> which ſinks Reaſon, then raiſeth up unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable motions, ſuch which make a man <hi>feare where no feare is;</hi> heare a noiſe meerly fancyed; flee, when none purſueth; ſo betrayeth the ſuccors <hi>which reaſon offers.</hi> 
                     <note n="(a)" place="margin">Wiſdom. 17. 12.</note> This <hi>feare</hi> made the <hi>Syrians,</hi> and others, infamous in the ſacred Writ, to fly, <note n="(b)" place="margin">2 Kings 7</note> &amp;c. And the Papiſts, in their houre of Darkneſſe, and Saint <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> Church in <note n="*" place="margin">Act. and M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pa 1102.</note> 
                     <hi>Oxford,</hi> To ſhelter their heads againſt the ſcalding lead, melted in the fornace of their own conceits, and guilty conſciences: for they heard a noiſe of fire onely, could ſee none, and yet they thought they ſhould be ſcalded to death with the droppings of lead melted in a fancyed fire of their owne imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary. This is a <hi>Panick</hi> feare, a feare where there is no cauſe of fear; a <hi>noiſe,</hi> which GOD cauſeth the wicked to heare, His enemies and adverſaries to feele: the effects thereof, as we heard.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. There is a naturall <hi>feare,</hi> which all partake of, that partake of the ſame common nature: Nay all creatures that have ſenſe, have ſenſe of <hi>feare,</hi> feare of ſuffering, It is naturall; The Beares will roare; Ravens Crye; Doves Chatter; Lambs Bleat; The Swine are troubled in a windy night, though I read of <hi>Pyrrhos Hogge,</hi> that eate his meate quietly in the ſhip almoſt covered with waves, while the Paſſengers there were almoſt dead with feare: And I have knowne ſome men, who ſeemed to have no other ſenſe, but that ſenſe of feeling, fearleſſe men; They feared nothing: But this <hi>fearleſneſſe</hi> was not from any cleanneſſe and ſerenity of mind; not from a true ſecurity and peace from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: but from a <hi>dead palſie</hi> rather, a <hi>ſtupor,</hi> a blockiſh ſtupidity upon their ſpirits.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. There is a <hi>feare,</hi> which hath a ſtrong foundation in nature: ſo alſo muſt it needs have the ſame foundation in ſin: A corrupt, a ſinfull feare: And the more or leſſe ſin is maſtered and ſubdued
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111850:11"/> in us, ſo will this <hi>feare</hi> be; ſo quieted, or ſo diſquieting: And this all men partake of, and in meaſure, according to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion before mentioned. If <hi>ſin</hi> beare rule in us, <hi>feare,</hi> when it comes, will command in chiefe too, and be exceeding: <hi>Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> and <hi>wickedneſſe</hi> are the very <hi>eſſentialls,</hi> whereof it doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, the ſupporters of it; and when it exceeds its bounds, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a <hi>paſſion</hi> indeed: We ſuffer much by it, and act or practiſe in it, I know not how, but as men forſaken of all, wit and reaſon both. It cauſeth ſtrange and ſtrong motions within, no paſſion ſtronger or ſtranger then <hi>feare</hi> doth. It is within us like foule weather upon the ſea; It no ſooner riſeth and getreth maſtery, but it cloudeth our <hi>Heaven,</hi> and ſils the ſoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with thick miſts and ſmoak. The Apoſtle ſpeaks all in one word, <hi>Where feare is, there is torment.</hi> 
                     <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> 22. 2.</note> It is the very <hi>Rack</hi> of the ſoule; it ſlayeth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſword: <hi>Thy ſlaine men are not ſlaine with the ſword nor dead</hi> (c) <hi>in Battell.</hi> How then were they ſlayn? with <hi>feare,</hi> that ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> eye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> cove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> his death, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> covered a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gain tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> hee might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ead his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> dead upon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Scaf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>old. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> them before the Battell, and did the part of an executioner before the ſword came.</p>
                  <p>But that is not the worſt; <hi>feare</hi> can doe a worſe office to a man then ſlay him; It can put us cleane off from GOD and from <hi>Duty,</hi> and that is worſt of all. What baſe ſhifts will the ſoule uſe when feare poſſeſſeth her? Feare of mans wrath, feare of loſſe of goods, of good name, of liberty, of life, will put a man upon the loſſe of all we properly call <hi>good;</hi> upon ſtrange adventures, upon deviliſh projects; It will daſh his ſoule upon this rock and the other, till He hath ſplit himſelfe, and made <hi>ſhipwrack</hi> of <hi>thoſe</hi> ineſtimable treaſures, (which render a man rich in the loweſt eſtate, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure in the greateſt danger) FAITH and a good CONSCI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ENCE: It will make a man ſeek for ſecurity from every thing, but where it ſhould: it will make him look to all means but one; in his diſtracting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eare, he will not look to God, and an upright converſation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:111850:11"/>
                  <head>CHAP. III.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The deſigne of the wicked ever was and now is To make the Godly afraid: The advantage if they can effect it: Tongue and hand im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed about it: Their judgement from the Lord: Their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and ſcarce that, for their works are manifeſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>THis the wicked know very well, they have learnt it of their Fathers: therefore heare what they have deviſed anciently, to make the righteous <hi>afraid.</hi> When the breaches of <hi>Ieruſalems</hi> walls were making up, what was the great deſigne of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary then? To <hi>make the builders</hi> AFRAID. We reade often <note place="margin">N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he. 6.</note> The adverſaries ſent and wrote Letters, raiſed falſe reports, hired light fellows; All this they did, <hi>That they might make the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">ver. 13.</note> 
                     <hi>afraid.</hi> Could they have effected it according to their minds, then the hands of the builders had been <hi>weakned from the worke: it had not beene done.</hi> 
                     <note n="(d)" place="margin">ver. 9.</note> If you will do any thing for The LORD, keepe up your ſpirits, and keepe out <hi>feare,</hi> that infeebling Paſſion, which cuts a Mans ſinewes, renders him unfit for action. When the heart ſinks, then the hands hang downe, and the <hi>work ceaſeth.</hi> If <hi>Nehemiah</hi> had given way to baſe and cowardly feare, he had done ſo and ſo, and <hi>ſinned.</hi> Beſides, he had given matter for an evill <note place="margin">ver. 13.</note> report, <hi>That the adverſary might reproach him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus The Adverſary did anciently, So hee doth now, Hee takes the ſame way; his deſigne and end is the very ſame with theirs; ſtill Hee ſends, hee writes, hee raiſeth falſe reports, hee <hi>hires</hi> light fellowes (if there bee any lighter then himſelfe:) what tongue or hand can doe hee doth, <hi>to cauſe terrour on every ſide;</hi> Their <hi>tongue walketh about the City,</hi> and <hi>all to diſquiet the inhabitants</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 42. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>thereof.</hi> What ſhall bee done unto thee thou deceitfull and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheivous tongue? for thou loveſt all devouring words: I cannot make full anſwer to that, but I read; The <hi>Lord ſhall deſtroy thee for ever, and pluck thee out of thy dwelling place,</hi> and roote thee out <note place="margin">ver. 5.</note> of the land of the living: here is alſo a prayer put up againſt theſe tongues, theſe fiery flying ſerpents; <hi>Let the miſcheife of their own</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 140. 9. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>lips cover them; let burning coals fall upon them,</hi> The Church
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111850:12"/> ſeekes not her <hi>God</hi> in vain, ſhee makes account it is done.</p>
                  <p>The hand is more rough and violent, and put forth as farre as it could bee, to make both Citty and Country MAGOR-MIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SABIB <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> 3.</note> 
                     <hi>feare on every ſide.</hi> What ſhall bee done unto thee thou violent and bloody man? Man cannot anſwer that; blood purſues him; the Deſtroyer ſhall bee deſtroyed; God hath ſworne by His Holineſſe, <hi>utter deſtruction ſhall come unto them;</hi> Hee will UNDOE <hi>all that aſſlict his people</hi> 
                     <note n="(a)" place="margin">Zeph. 3. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>Their fleſh ſhall conſume a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way while they ſtand upon their feete; and their eyes ſhall conſume a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in their holes, and their tongues ſhall conſume away in their mouth;</hi> 
                     <note n="(b)" place="margin">Zeph. 14. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>This is the portion of them that hate His Church; they ſhall be utterly deſtroyed,</hi> in the cloſe of this <hi>work</hi> (for there is a great work to be done upon mount Sion) and about the cloſe of the day they ſhall be utterly <hi>undon.</hi> But firſt they ſhall bee made a <hi>terrour</hi> to themſelves, and round about: As they thought to do to the Righteous, ſo it ſhall bee done to them: As they have determined, ſo it ſhall bee unto them, that ſhall bee their lot and portion of their cup from the Lord in his appointed Time.</p>
                  <p>But do wee not wrong theſe harmeleſſe people, theſe innocent Lambs (ſome of them were in <hi>ſheepes clothing,</hi> and they would <note place="margin">Mal. 8. 15.</note> bee accounted <hi>ſheepe</hi> till their cloak fell off, and the wolfe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared) what have they done, or ſpoken to make the City af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid? They will tell us, Nothing at all. <q>We doe but fancie our feares; we heare a rumour, we ſcarce know of what, or from whom, and we are afraid, we know not wherefore. We conceit danger onely, as they, who took ſhadows for men: or <note place="margin">Judges 19. 36.</note> as thoſe, who, beholding at a diſtance, a field over-grown with tall thiſtles, thought verily they had been ſo many ſpearmen.</q> So the adverſary ſaith, and ſo ſay they too, who ſhould ſpeakas the <hi>Oracles of</hi> GOD, for they ſpeak from the Pulpit. And what ſaid they? As the Adverſary before them, <q>That there was no cauſe of feare formerly, nor any cauſe now; A Phantaſme, a conceited thing, a <hi>Panick</hi> feare the City is poſſeſſed with, whereof they can give neither cauſe nor reaſon for, neither is reall nor viſible.</q> They have ſaid; and ſo they have <hi>forced</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as <hi>unjuſt</hi> men doe. Now we wil take leave to conſider the matter, and their words, and give no more credit to them then we doe to ſuch men, who <hi>know no ſhame.</hi> 
                     <note n="(a)" place="margin">Zeph. 3. 5.</note>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:111850:12"/>
                  <p> Catholique men, bloody Papiſts, (univerſally, all the world over) brawned in villanies, theſe fellowes, that hate the Lord, make Tumults, lift up the head, and yet <hi>no ground of feare,</hi> not any. The neighbours houſe is on fire, there the fire rageth, and the wind blows the flame directly hitherward; it began there, to end here; yet <hi>no cauſe of feare,</hi> That our common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe may ſmell of the ſmoak, or that it is time for every common man to look to his owne: No reaſon for that, none at all, ſpeaks the adverſary, but he is not ſo mad as to think any wiſe man beleeves him. The vile Prieſts and the Treacherous Prophets, that have polluted <hi>the Sanctuary,</hi> have <hi>done violence to the Law;</hi> 
                     <note n="(c)" place="margin">Zeph. 3. 4.</note> Theſe doe rage, and are ſwelled with malice: The brutiſh people, almoſt as much, make tumults; and they that ſung forth their requeſts, roare like Beares, and are as fierce as the <hi>ſhe-beares,</hi> fearing their ſweet morſels may be taken from them, and their <hi>ſervice ordered</hi> according to <hi>Rule,</hi> and <hi>yet no ground of feare.</hi> The tumult of thoſe, that riſe up againſt The LORD, that would dethrone Him, encreaſeth continually, and <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>et no cauſe of feare.</hi> Indeed there is not; no cauſe we ſhould be afraid, when we look up to GOD, for it is the Tumult of thoſe that riſe up againſt <hi>Him,</hi> and <hi>He</hi> will look to <hi>His</hi> owne Cauſe and <hi>Glory,</hi> That ſhall receive no loſſe, no diminution at all, but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage a great deale: But looking down to the Adverſary, there is cauſe we ſhould <hi>feare,</hi> after <hi>a godly ſort:</hi> ſo as to make provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion againſt him, and then ſecure our ſelves and the cauſe in GOD. This <hi>feare</hi> is a <hi>Godly feare:</hi> The Godly mans <hi>feare</hi> is his humility, and caſting away of Pride; his reverent care to walk in the wayes of God: A <hi>feare</hi> which drives out ſecurity, not a feare which takes away the boldneſſe of faith. More of this anon. This here, that there is juſt cauſe of <hi>feare,</hi> but of ſuch a <hi>feare</hi> that hath been deſcribed unto us, which ſecureth the ſoule, the godly man, and his cauſe in <hi>God;</hi> And great need of ſuch a feare, for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Adverſary ſaith, no man that hath his eyes in his head will beleeve him; though his words were as ſoft as butter: and his deeds as ſmooth as oyle: much leſſe now, when his words are as drawn ſwords, violence is in his hands, &amp; war in his heart. The Adverſary is ſo mad with rage now, That he caſteth fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands, arrows and death, and cannot deceive his neighbour <note place="margin">Pro. 26. 18.</note>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:111850:13"/> now, ſaying, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> not I in ſport?</hi> No ſure, no man is ſo ſenſleſſe as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> beleeve that; for when he ſeemed to ſpeak faire, we beleeved <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> not, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>wing there were ſeven abominations in his heart:</hi> Hee that hateth, may diſſemble for a time, and lay up deceit within him; for words, which are wounds, and lying lips and a wicked heart may be like a <hi>pot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ard covered with ſilver droſſe</hi> for a time. But now his hatred (as active as fire) cannot be covered by <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ceit,</hi> his wickedneſſe is ſhewne <hi>before the whole congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe are Generalls; That I may be more particular, I will quarter out this <hi>Legion,</hi> the Adverſary I meane, for <hi>he is many,</hi> and behold him as a man of War, in his <hi>Ranks</hi> and <hi>Poſtures:</hi> doubtleſſe, if we ſo behold him, and can look no higher, he will ſeem terrible, as an Army with banners; or rather, as <hi>Goliah</hi> before the <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> I ſaid not, <hi>before David,</hi> for <hi>he laughed him to ſcorne,</hi> and <hi>deſpiſed him:</hi> but this I may ſay truly, juſt cauſe we have to be <hi>afraid,</hi> for conſider the Churches enemies, <hi>how many they are.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Without number for multitude.</hi> 2. <hi>Without reaſon for rags and cruelty.</hi> 3. <hi>Boundleſſe in malice, miſchievous in projecting, and watchfull in executing thereof.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p n="1">1. HOW many adverſaries hath the Church? It were well with the Church if ſhe could number her enemies, tell how many adverſaries ſhe hath: We ſay, They are but a few, that can be numbred. The Shepherd can tell his ſheep, but hee cannot tell how many Wolves, nor Foxes there be: nor how many dogs, which doe their office the contrary way, hurrying the ſheep, and are as bloody as the wolſe or foxe, every whit. The Church can ſay, They are, as in former dayes, <hi>encreaſed that</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 3. 1. Pſal. 22. 12. 13.</note> 
                     <hi>trouble me; Many Bulls have compaſſed me, ſtrong Bulls of Baſhan have beſet me round. They gaped upon me with their mouthes, as a ravening and roaring lyon.</hi> 
                     <note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſal. 31. 1.</note> She hath heard <hi>the ſlander of many, feare was on every ſicle. While they took, counſell together againſt</hi>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:111850:13"/> 
                     <hi>me, they deviſed to take away my life.</hi> The Church can onely an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, MANY, <hi>Many are my Adverſaries,</hi> many my perſecutors; <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 15<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> Many, that ſight <hi>againſt my ſoule, becauſe I ſeek the thing that good is.</hi> All the luke-warm Proteſtants, theſe are not a few; and they are againſt the Church, for they are not with her: All the <hi>light</hi> Prophets, and <hi>Treacherous</hi> Prieſts, Theſe are exceeding ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and their rage is exceeding, as is their zeale to their eaſe, and filthy lucre, to their pleaſure alſo boyled up to the height: All the Devils in hell, and both their hands on earth, right and left, Pope and Popelings, with the Atheiſts too, theſe ſwarm every where, ſuch multitudes there are. But thanks be to God, wee know where they ſettle, and fixe, though a gadding company, yet we know where they are <hi>ſolden together as thornes;</hi> and if their bodies <note place="margin">Nah. 1. 10.</note> are not there, yet their hearts are, joyned all together from all the quarters of the world. And now we can give a gueſſe how many they be, that band themſelves againſt the Church, as <hi>the</hi> ſands by the <hi>Sea-ſhore for multitude:</hi> and then it follows, That we may have juſt cauſe of feare, In the ſecond place conſider we their</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Cruelty. The dark places of the earth are full of it, where the light of the Goſpel comes not, is thruſt out, or deſpiſed. Their <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> their Laws, the beſt things with them are as the bloud of a dead man. What are their manners then? Bloody ſure. Theſe ſons and daughters of men, ſtand upon ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting record, To be the moſt bloody enemies that ever the Church met withall in this world: They are free of the Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Malignant Church, and have purchaſed their free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome there: How? and at what rate? By Maſſacres, outrages and villauies of all ſorts and ſizes. If any of the company are not ſo cruell by nature, yet they muſt be ſo by command, and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted to be ſo, by Law. They may and <hi>muſt purſue their brother with the ſword, and caſt off all pity: Their rage muſt teare perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Amos 1. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>they muſt keep their wrath for ever.</hi> Keep wrath for ever? Yes, for ever; for though they are but Mortall enemies, yet doth their enmity mannage an immortall hatred againſt the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; for they purſued <hi>him to death;</hi> and when he had got into his ſtrong-hold, the <hi>grave,</hi> there they troubled him, that they did.</p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:111850:14"/>
                  <p> They have executed their rage and malice againſt the <hi>Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aries of the dead,</hi> the <hi>Graves,</hi> the place where <hi>Iob</hi> was confident he <hi>ſhould lye at reſt:</hi> even thither, to their <hi>Sanctuaries,</hi> the hand of <note place="margin">Job 3. 17.</note> the <hi>oppreſſour reached;</hi> There the wicked did not ceaſe to trouble the bones, and ſacred aſhes of the Martyrs; there, at that <hi>Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary,</hi> the dead were not free from the oppreſſours, <hi>his anger did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>are perpetually, he did keepe his wrath for ever.</hi> They have been cruell to the living and to the dead, and ſo are they to this day. Hiſtories Ancient and Modern, a cloud of witneſſes would croud in here to give evidence to what was laſt ſaid; but it needs not, all the world is fully ſatisfied in that point, for in alluſion to that which the learned Knight ſaith touching <hi>Henry the eight of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> I may ſay touching the Papiſts; If all their Hiſtories were loſt; if all the maſſacres, outrages, villanies of theſe mercileſſe men were forgot and quite out of mind, they might be renewed and deſcribed forth to their life, out of theſe three yeares ſtory concerning their practice in <hi>Ireland,</hi> where they have ſlaine their brethren with a rage that <hi>reacheth up to heaven.</hi> They have made <note place="margin">2 Chron. 28. 9.</note> that Countrey a Land of wrath, a field of bloud at this day. So they would make this Land alſo, that is their <hi>deſigne,</hi> we ſhall come to that preſently, for I will ſpend no more time, nor blot any more paper in making knowne how cruell they are, how they breathe forth threatnings, and how exceeding mad with rage: Papiſts are the executioners of wrath, we need not then adde, <hi>They are grievous as wolves, and fierce as ſhe-beares:</hi> their Natures ſuch, their Laws ſuch: their words and deeds, how hard and ungodly they are, all the Chriſtian world, the heathen people alſo, all know and ſeele. Obſerve we then,</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Adverſaries Deſigne; how miſchievous and Diveliſh; the ſame which wee read of, <note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſal. 83.</note> or as <hi>Hamans</hi> was, not <hi>to cut Iſrael ſhort,</hi> but cleane off from being a Nation: <note n="(b)" place="margin">Eſther 3. 6</note> And his heart is bent upon this Deſigne, now, Now he moves every ſtone, as the Proverbe is; now they put ſhoulder to ſhoulder, <hi>heaving</hi> at the Church, to remoove and ſhoulder her downe. Why now? Becauſe hee had brought the Church once and againe to the <hi>brow</hi> of the <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ill,</hi> but, as her Lord before her, ſhe paſſed through the midſt of <note place="margin">Luke 4. 20.</note> them ſhee knowes not how, and went her way; This admirable Reſcue enrageth the adverſary; Now hee hath them in the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111850:14"/> open feild, hee ſayes, as their fore fathers, <hi>I will purſue, I will over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, I will devide the ſpoile, my luſt ſhall bee ſatis ſied upon them, I will draw my ſword, mine hand ſhall deſtroy them</hi> 
                     <note n="(c)" place="margin">Exod. 15. 9.</note> But ſee the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries COLOURS, under which hee marcheth, I meane his <hi>pretences,</hi> for though hee purſues the enemy with open face, yet <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> hee puts a vizor over it, and that makes the <hi>face</hi> more ugly: it putts an <hi>accent</hi> upon the deſigne, making it above meaſure horrid, ſinfull and abominable. The Adverſary fights (I take him ſingle though hee bee <hi>many)</hi> againſt <hi>God,</hi> under a pretence of being for <hi>Him:</hi> he fights againſt the life and ſoul of our lives; he ſheds in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent <hi>blood to his Power;</hi> hee treads the Righteous as mire in the ſtreets: doth what hee can to lay the <hi>Glory</hi> in the duſt, and all this he doth under a <hi>colour</hi> (but blood hath quite waſhed off the varniſh) of Advancing Religion and the glory: he hath engaged himſelf to ſubject our conſciences, our laws, our liberties, our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, to a perpetuall ſlavery: but obſerve the <hi>manner</hi> how he proſecutes all this, for there is the abomination, pretending <hi>liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> to conſcience; eſtabliſhment to lawes; property in our goods; &amp; a free enjoyment of all unto us, as to free men. Never was there ſuch a thing as this heard of ſince man was upon the earth: nor was there ever an Hypocriſie ſo pellucide, ſo tranſparent, that every child laughs at it, ſees through it, as through the cleareſt glaſſe. But The LORD ſees it, Hee beholds iniquity and wrong, and hath taken it into His owne hand to <hi>Require</hi> it: which ſpeaks comfort to the Righteous, as it ſhould terrors to the ungodly.</p>
                  <p>Now we will look over the <hi>Premiſes,</hi> and conclude, The Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary is a Legion, and more, without number for multitudes; without Reaſon for rage and cruelty: Boundleſſe in their malice, bloody deſigns, and miſchievous Projects: reſtleſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, watching thereunto (that I ſhould have added) for their ſleepe is <hi>taken away unleſſe</hi> they cauſe <hi>ſome to fall.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 4. 16.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>We conclude: There is juſt cauſe of a juſt feare, which makes the city ſtand upon their Watch-Tower, gird on their Armour, and, when they have done all, ſtand faſt in the <hi>faith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> To main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it, and a good <hi>conſcience,</hi> To do this with all their ſtrength, and To do it continually, praying and watching thereunto: As Rome ſaid once touching her Adverſary <hi>Carthage; ſhee</hi>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:111850:15"/> 
                     <hi>would never forbeare to watch againſt Carthage, till they ſaw that City quite demoliſhed and laid even with the ground:</hi> So this City will never forbeare to keepe <hi>watch</hi> and <hi>ward</hi> and her ſelf in a Poſture of Defence againſt <hi>Rome</hi> now, and her <hi>vaſſals,</hi> till ſhe ſees them, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſaw the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> dead before her upon the ſands.</p>
                  <p>This City ſtands as much engaged to <hi>Watch</hi> and <hi>Pray</hi> too, (ſo they gird up their loynes) as <hi>David</hi> did, when <hi>Saul</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued him, for The City may ſay as David did at that time, <hi>my</hi> ſoul <hi>is among Lions; I lye even among</hi> them, <hi>that are ſet on fire,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 57. 4.</note> even the <hi>Sonnes of men, whoſe Teeth are ſpeares and arrowes and their tongue a ſharpe Sword:</hi> fiery Adverſaries, <hi>who ſent</hi> and <hi>watched the houſe to kill him.</hi> It was even ſo with the City as wee read in the title of the <note n="(d)" place="margin">Pſal. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> Pſalme: Oh! great Reaſon of <hi>feare!</hi> I mean ſuch a <hi>feare,</hi> as puts a man upon Duty, To pray and watch too. Why? The Adverſary, as wee may remember, did, when time was, watch and guard his <hi>Croſſe,</hi> that Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable <hi>pile of images,</hi> ſtocks and ſtones, ſuch deſpicable things: much more will the wiſe in heart, in tender compaſſion to their lives, and juſt liberties, keepe watch night and day over them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and this great City, where are ſo many thouſand perſons, that cannot diſcerne between their Right hand and <hi>their</hi> Left, <hi>and alſo</hi> much <hi>Cattel.</hi> And ſo (Bleſſed bee God) they can ſanctify The <hi>Lord God in their hearts,</hi> and are <hi>ready alwayes to give an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to every man, that asketh them a Reaſon of their feare,</hi> and <hi>hope</hi> alſo, that is in <hi>them, with meekneſſe.</hi> So wee have ſeen a juſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count given of our <hi>feare,</hi> how juſt it is, no Phancied thing, but Reall and viſible: wee will ſee now what uſe GOD makes of this affection, in the hearts of the Righteous. And indeed it is very notable to obſerve the wiſdom of <hi>God</hi> in planting His People there, where they muſt look for diſquietings; And in Implanting in them ſuch an affection as <hi>feare</hi> is; When wee have obſerved this, then I ſhall ſet downe the meanes how the Righteous have had power, and been able to command over their feares, deporting themſelves calmly in ſuch ſhaking times: And this will make much for the ſetling our minds in our diſquietments, and ſo I ſhall bring it downe and make it uſefull for the preſent time.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:111850:15"/>
               <head>SECT. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The wiſdome of God in planting His Church in the world, not the place of their reſt: And in implanting in them, This Affection of Feare; The True uſe thereof; The advantage His people get by it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. I.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>This world no paradiſe: The Church expects her heaven above, her Purgatory here: It is her Lords pleaſure ſo, and ſhe is content, and thankefull.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>EE What a place the Church lives in! where ſhe hath no <hi>reſt,</hi> nor muſt look for any. They who were diſquieted yeſterday, muſt look to be diſquieted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: They that ſuffered, muſt ſuffer, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps unto bloud. Laſt yeeres were vexatious and troublous; ſo are theſe: the next following may be worſe: If better, The Church will be very thankfull: if much more trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blous, The Church hath counted the coſt, ſhe cannot be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but ſhe can be very thankfull too. We ſee the Changes and Turnings in the world: They, who ſate at reſt as we doe, two yeares agoe, They ſit as a widow now: at five a clock all was peace, (for ſo I heard a Miniſter of their owne ſay) and before ſixe, behold War, and the terrours thereof on every ſide. This world now anſwers to the Iſraelites Wilderneſſe once, variety of feares and troubles here. Our life is as a Checquer work, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwoven with black and white, here <hi>Good,</hi> there <hi>Evill,</hi> but the Evill takes up the greateſt part: Bleſſed be <hi>God,</hi> that it is ſo, elſe even His owne People would be much in love with the place, where their Reſt is not; They would build Tabernacles here, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver think of removing hence. If the cloud of feare and diſcontent did not ſometimes overſhadow them; if there were not unſetled times, we would ſettle on our lees; if there were not <hi>a want,</hi>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:111850:16"/> when we are at the fulleſt, we would be ſo full of earth, that there would be no roome for heaven; If we had no feare, we ſhould have no Care; But we are ſtill in feare, for ſomething is ſtill wanting, and we feare and are troubled leſt that <hi>want</hi> ſhould not be ſupplyed: That want is ſupplyed, and then wee are in more feare then before, leſt we come to be at a loſſe again. To explaine this: We have a full eſtate, and health is wanting; we have plenty of all things, and health withall, but now the feare is, That the ſpoiler may come, <hi>men skilfull to deſtroy,</hi> and take away all, <hi>goods, life,</hi> and all. But ſuppoſe now we could be ſecure, That none of this could happen to us; our eſtates could be ſecured to us, and our health too, ſuppoſe it ſo, for we may ſuppoſe impoſſible things: then <hi>Abrahams</hi> 
                     <note n="(a)" place="margin">Gen. 15. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>feare</hi> troubles us, we <hi>have not a child to inherit:</hi> and then, WHAT <hi>is all our ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe unto us?</hi> We make but a <hi>[What]</hi> of all the reſt of our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments, becauſe a child is wanting, for ſo that good man did, though <hi>God</hi> be there as a <hi>portion:</hi> Then A child is given us, but what a feare there is leſt the child be taken away againe? why then, if we would keep him, we muſt ſacrifice him. That is true, but that is a <hi>death</hi> too; we cannot think of the withering of that <hi>Gourd,</hi> (ſuch a thing as that was, a child, is quickly withered) and ſo the <hi>goord</hi> withers, and we dye: That we <hi>feare</hi> is come upon us; It grows up as a flower, and is cut downe like the graſſe. And all this That <hi>Gods</hi> people may not fixe and faſten upon ſuch reeds, which, if you leane and beare upon, they break and pierce too: And yet we will leane upon them, we will be <hi>very glad</hi> of our <hi>gourds;</hi> then The LORD knaps them aſunder, <note place="margin">Jonah 4. 6.</note> withers them, and then we are troubled exceedingly.</p>
                  <p>In the laſt place, ſuppoſe we have health, and wealth, and peace withall, and children round about our table, yet there is a <hi>feare</hi> That we may be taken away in the midſt of all our fulneſſe. What is our life? We know what the Apoſtle anſwers, and every day <note place="margin">James 4. 14.</note> ſaith as much, <hi>It appeareth for a little time, &amp; then vaniſheth away.</hi> A man is well to day, and dead to morrow, and this feare (if there be not a hand over it to ſubdue it) <hi>holds us in bondage all our life time.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 2. 15.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>But Bleſſed be God, ſo He unbottomes His People, drawing the heart to Himſelfe. If it were not for theſe feares, Faith
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111850:16"/> would have no maſtery: but ſo it is, we are in ſuch feares often, and that is almoſt to be in <hi>death</hi> as often: ſo in this our wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and <hi>God</hi> beareth with our <hi>manners here;</hi> weaneth His peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <note place="margin">Acts 13. 18. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> from drawing ſo hard at the breaſts of the world: Aſſureth them, This is not the place of their reſt, but there remaineth a Reſt to his people, which ſhall laſt as long as Eternity is long, for ever. Therefore they may beare patiently their diſquietings, their changes here below, for a moment, a little, a ſmall <note n="(c)" place="margin">Eſay 26. 20. 54. 7.</note> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, quickly over, and then they ſhall <hi>ſee evill no more.</hi> 
                     <note n="(d)" place="margin">Zeph. 3. 15.</note> Shortly they ſhall be above in the heaven of Heavens, where all is peace for evermore. And their diſquietments and fears make them work more ſtrongly after this place now: ſo <hi>God</hi> makes all work for their good, whereof in the cloſe This here muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, even</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. II.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The wiſdom of God in planting this affection of feare in His People.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>BLeſſed be God, wee are in feares, often it is beſt for us ſo to be; wee ſhould ſurfeit every day of our ſweets, if the feare of looſing them did not allay the luſſiouſneſſe of the ſame: wee ſhould bottome our ſelves too ſtrongly upon our mountaine, if wee were Confident (wee are too conſident) it cannot be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved. Dayly experience tells us ſo much therein, That wee cannot ſtand feareleſſe upon the ſtrongeſt and beſt bottomed comfort, that hath its bottome upon the earth. And Bleſſed bee God for all this, even for this affection of feare: So alſo, and that The Lord hath put a vanity and vexation into the Creature, and feares many; feare make us all pull up our feet, and walke more warily; feare feeds us with food Convenient: So it clothes us: feare is our watch keeper: It is the moſt wakeing affection, moſt ſerviceable of any, if it doth Its office. It is the houſe-porter, the bodies <hi>Spiall:</hi> and the ſoules too, ſtill keeping watch: It is, next to <hi>love,</hi> the moſt Commanding affection: our keeper, and Truths keeper alſo; It is the beſt King in the world, (the great or little) for it keeps both <hi>tables.</hi> I ſhould ſpeake more of it, but I
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111850:17"/> find my ſelf prevented here in a Booke called <hi>The Childs portion,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>2, 163.</note> whereto I would referr the Reader, if pleaſe him, I would rather ſpeake ſomewhat more touching the uſefulneſſe of this affection, God ſanctifying the ſame.</p>
                  <p>It makes the people of God to put no confidence at all in the fleſh: I meane by <hi>[Fleſh]</hi> All things under the moone: They cannot <hi>feare</hi> now the changes of things here below, and vexation from them, for they have been ſo uſed to it, That, which they feared from the creature ſo often came upon them, That now they expect no ſtability in the creature at all, but changes, and troubles, and vexations from it evermore. They <hi>can now ſuffer the ſpoiling of their goods with joy.</hi> They did indeed put ſome confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in ſuch things, They thought ſuch things to be a HIGH WALL, <hi>(a)</hi> but it was (and they ſee it now to be) a meere con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit <note place="margin">Prov. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> onely, and no more. They know now, and they are <hi>fearleſſe</hi> about it, That the theefe and the robber breaks in upon theſe treaſures every day; therefore it is nor their <hi>treaſure,</hi> they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count not of it ſo: they have laid up their <hi>treaſure</hi> in a ſafe place, where they <hi>feare</hi> not the thiefe nor the moath, and it is well they are ſo well inſtructed to diſcretion.</p>
                  <p>I remember a Story worth the noting, of <hi>Paulinus, Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Nola:</hi> he had abundance of wealth, but no affection to it; bags <note place="margin">Aug. deciv. De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> lib. 1. c. 10. <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>ate pauper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>imu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>me ſanct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </note> full, and coffers full, but his heart was not ſet upon that <hi>fulneſſe,</hi> but on a better <hi>treaſure,</hi> and full of the ſame. It was well for him that he had a <hi>Treaſure,</hi> which Man could not give, nor take away: For, though he was a very rich man but as yeſterday, yet was he ſtript of all preſently, and as poore as <hi>Iob.</hi> The <hi>Goths,</hi> a barbarous people, almoſt as any we can ſee or heare of, brake in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that City <hi>Nola,</hi> like ſo many Devils, and did <hi>flee upon the prey,</hi> flee preſently upon all the Biſhop had in this world, and took it <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cum ab cis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neretur, ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> corde ſuo, ut ab co poſtea cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>imus, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabatur: Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, non excru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cier propter au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; argen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum: ubi e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>m ſunt omnia mea tu ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>is.</hi> ibid. &amp;c.</note> into their poſſeſſion, and the Biſhop priſoner alſo. Now mark his Prayer, for that was all the refuge he had now, being in the hands of Robbers: LORD GOD, <hi>Let me not be greatly troubled for my ſilver and gold: Thou knoweſt,</hi> Lord, <hi>it is not my</hi> Treaſure, <hi>That is laid up according to Thy Commands, Who didſt tell us long before, That this would happen, Theſe barbarous people would break in upon us for our ſinnes: therefore,</hi> Lord, <hi>I was warned, and laid up my Treaſure, as Thou haſt charged me, and as Thou knoweſt.</hi> What a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111850:17"/> wiſe man was this! Truly all his neighbours counted him ſo; for though they were not ſo wiſe before-hand, yet now they had learnt by ſad experience, <note n="(c)" place="margin">Si non prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente ſapientia certe conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te experientia didicerunt.</note> (an after-wiſdome, that comes too late) That ſo they ſhould have done too; They ſhould have laid up their Treaſure where their Teacher did, and charged his people ſo to doe. For mark how it hapned to thoſe after-wits, They counted the wedge of gold their <hi>Treaſure,</hi> and all their care and feare was To ſecure that, ſo they hid it in the ground. The Robbers came, they knew there was ſilver and gold both, and they would have it, and by torments the enemy forced the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed Captives, To tell where they had hid their treaſure. Nay the Adverſaries cruelty was ſuch, That they tormented ſome poore wretches, that had neither ſilver nor gold, upon ſuppoſition that they had both, and diſſembled the having of it. Other ſome, the richeſt men amongſt them, were ſo hardy, That they would die upon the rack rather then diſcover where their gold was; and ſo they were admoniſhed (ſaith the Author) <hi>by ſuffering ſuch</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Si autem to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queri quam au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum prodere maluerunt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monendi crant, qui tanta pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ebantur pro au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro, quanta eſſent ſuſtinenda pro Chriſto.</hi> ibid. &amp;c.</note> 
                     <hi>things, rather then betray their gold,</hi> WHAT THEY SHOULD HAVE SUFFERED FOR CHRIST. Other ſome againe, the feweſt of them, could not be forced to betray their Treaſure, or forgoe the ſame, for, indeed, they had not laid it upon earth, but in heaven, where Robbers could not break-in, and ſteale: So well they had profited by their <hi>feare</hi> about ſuch uncertaine things, that now they were not carefull about them at all. They could take <hi>joyfully the ſpoiling of ſuch goods,</hi> knowing in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, That <hi>they had in heaven a better and enduring ſubſtance.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 10. 34.</note> And ſo the <hi>Father</hi> concluſes, <hi>No man kept his gold but by denying</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">In e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> tormenta nemo Chriſtum confitendo ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit: nemo aurum niſi negando ſervavit.</note> 
                     <hi>it:</hi> that is, by taking off his <hi>love</hi> and <hi>feare</hi> from it: and no man kept <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but by <hi>confeſſing him,</hi> (that is) by giving up his <hi>love</hi> and <hi>feare</hi> unto him.</p>
                  <p>2. It is ſo with and about their children too; Their diſcreet <hi>feare</hi> hath taught them, not to be carefull about children neither: The <hi>Lord</hi> gave them, He may take them; They can bleſſe His <hi>Name</hi> in all: They did not ſet their <hi>hope,</hi> nor their <hi>hearts</hi> on ſuch periſhing things, and then, when <hi>God</hi> takes them away, their <hi>hope</hi> is where it was, and <hi>heart</hi> alſo, even in heaven, where their <hi>Love,</hi> and JOY, and TREASUREIS: And they can ſubmit to their FATHER in heaven; It is <hi>Hee,</hi> The LORD, He hath done
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111850:18"/> it, and they are ſilent; It is His will ſo, thereto they reſolve all, and there they reſt, ſaying, <hi>The will of the</hi> LORD <hi>be done.</hi> So their feare (the Lord ſanctifying it) hath taught them touching their Children.</p>
                  <p>3. They have brought their hearts to the ſame point touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their <hi>life</hi> alſo; that is a precious thing: skin after skin, a man will part withall to ſave his life: And yet, they are not now <hi>fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> about it; it is of ſmall continuance here below: and, while it doth continue here, it is full of changes and ſorrows. They are the leſſe carefull about it. They that have been moſt afraid, and ſo would ſave their life, have ſooner loſt it, and upon the greateſt diſadvantage. They, who have <hi>loved their life more then Chriſt,</hi> Who is the life of their life, have loſt their life, and Him too: and They that have <hi>hated</hi> their <hi>life</hi> in this world for <hi>His</hi> ſake, have made no account of it in reference to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and their love to Him, have <hi>kept it unto eternall life.</hi> 
                     <note n="(c)" place="margin">John 12. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> That is the <hi>life</hi> they think upon, of being BLESSED FOR EVER; That is a <hi>life</hi> indeed. This here, in compariſon, abides but a moment, a ſmall, a little moment, not worth the ſetting our <hi>feare</hi> upon, ever ſince we could look through it, what a life it is. They make no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of any thing, but what ſets them backward or forward toward eternity, where they ſhall live <hi>bleſſed for ever</hi> in eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> nitas fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit bonum infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite melius; malum infinite pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us.</note> The thought wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of makes that which is good, infinitely better; and that which is evill, <hi>infinitely worſe.</hi> Thereon, upon Eternitie, they place their <hi>feare</hi> now, and concerning this life they are fearleſſe. We have ſeene what uſe the righteous make of <hi>feare,</hi> they work good out of it: and by theſe unquiet motions here below, they get an eſtabliſhment in God. I come now in the third place to the meanes whereby the righteous Nation can and doe maſter their feares, keeps them under ſo, as they are a <hi>quiet habitation,</hi> when all about them are full of ſtirs, a tumultuous people.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:111850:18"/>
               <head>SECT. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The meanes of the righteous mans eſtabliſhment, and how his</hi> feare, <hi>the diſeaſe of it is cured.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E ſee the righteous are a people that are not afraid with any amazement. They feare, but with a <hi>godly feare;</hi> They <hi>feare,</hi> but nothing ſo much as ſin, and the frown of their God; They <hi>fear,</hi> but ſo, as they can look up with confidence, and down to the means of their ſafety with comfort; They <hi>feare,</hi> and yet they can gird up their loines, and put on their armour; They <hi>feare,</hi> and yet doe <hi>truſt perfectly;</hi> They <hi>feare,</hi> and are diſquieted, but not <hi>greatly.</hi> Their hearts may ſhake, and their heads ake with <hi>feare,</hi> and yet then they can calme their hearts, and reſt their heads in the lap and boſome of their <hi>everlaſting Father,</hi> there laying their ſelves downe quietly, aſſured they may reſt in ſafety, and the end will be peace. How comes this to be ſo? The Anſwer is, They expect troubles in the world, afflictions there; and they expect, nay they know <hi>God</hi> will deliver them out of them all: For they LOVE God heartily, ſo they FEARE HIM, ſo they TRUST IN HIM, ſo they OBEY HIM, even from the heart, walking in His way, doing His work; They <hi>keep continuall watch</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Adverſary, and over themſelves. All this muſt be conſidered on diſtinctly and apart, and ſo we ſhall learne the way how to ſettle the heart in the moſt unſetled times: The chiefe ſcope and mark we would carry all levell unto.</p>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:111850:19"/>
                  <head>CHAP. I.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The righteous mans expectation from the</hi> world, <hi>and from his</hi> GOD, <hi>ſhall not be deceived: He expects all the evill the world and their</hi> god <hi>there, can doe againſt them; And from His</hi> GOD <hi>all that is truly called</hi> Good, <hi>or is made ſo: All this he is ſure of, therefore he waits patiently for</hi> God. <hi>He will come ſurely and in ſeaſon, Bleſſed are all they that wait for Him.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>THe righteous are in continuall expectation: Of what? Of troubles in the fleſh, of afflictions in the world: Ever ſince they underſtood themſelves, they ſate downe to conſider what it would <hi>coſt</hi> them, To doe their Maſters work; To ſerve Him in ſinceritie and truth; and Their brethren, in love to their ſoules, and faith of the Goſpel: In this great work now, (whereunto evermore Chriſtians ſtand ſo engaged) the building themſelves up, and <hi>Ieruſalems wall</hi> in faith and love, They have <hi>counted</hi> their <hi>coſt,</hi> and they know what they muſt find at the bottome of their reckoning, <hi>troubles</hi> from within, <hi>diſquietings, perſecutions</hi> from without, of all ſorts and ſizes: And it was well, and they bleſſe God with all their hearts, Who hath inſtructed them to diſcretion, To <hi>count</hi> their <hi>coſt</hi> ſo ſoone as they thought of <hi>Temple-work,</hi> The <hi>edifying</hi> (the building up) themſelves and others in their moſt holy faith. This was the uſe they made of their <hi>Reſt</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> GOD was graciouſly pleaſed to afford unto them: They knew this <hi>Temple-work</hi> would coſt them deare, Labour and Trouble both: They expected all this, and whatever it be it is but anſwerable to their expectation: they looked for it, and now it is come, it is welcome: They are fit to entertaine it, they are fitted for it, as the burden is fitted for the ſhoulder, and the yoak for the neck.</p>
                  <p>I will tell a knowne and ſad ſtory of a man that lived in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity all his life long, God ſpake to him once and againe, and every day by every mercy he gave unto him; but he would not hearken, and that was his manner <note n="*" place="margin">Jer. 22. 21.</note> from his youth, he would not obey Gods voice, what cared he what God ſaid, he was inpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:111850:19"/> had no changes, and expected none; Towards the end, as the manner is, The <hi>Lord</hi> made a breach upon him, ſorrows o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verwhelmed him like a mighty flood. O, ſaid he, <hi>I never looked for this:</hi> Ai, that was true enough; and therefore his ſorrowes preſſed his ſoule we know not how low. <hi>We looked for peace,</hi> ſaid they. <note n="(a)" place="margin">Jer. 8. 15. ver. 19.</note> Why did they ſo? For firſt, They had provoked GOD <hi>to anger with their Images, and ſtrange vanities:</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, (for I haſten here) The word is gone forth of His mouth, Who cannot lye, <hi>In the world affliction:</hi> Yet ſay they, <hi>We looked for Peace,</hi> what followes? <hi>No good came; we looked for a time of health, and behold trouble.</hi> A miſerable caſe to be ſo deceived, and in point of Peace.</p>
                  <p>The righteous not ſo, They are not deceived; They expect trouble, what the gates of hell can doe againſt them. All this is done againſt them, they are not troubled at it; They had their maſters word, it would be ſo, and ſo it is. Where is their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort now? <hi>In</hi> ME PEACE; Trouble round about, and War at the doores, making breaches upon them; That which upholds them is, and fully to their expectation, IN ME PEACE.</p>
                  <p>I will aske a Queſtion, and reſolve it in two Anſwers; when I have cleared them, then I will conclude this point.</p>
                  <p>Is the Church never deceived in her expectation? <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                     </label>
                  </p>
                  <p>No, never deceived in the world, in her expectation therein; <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> ſhe expects no favour from it, but all the evill that can be done againſt her; and ſhe is ſure to have it from the world: And</p>
                  <p>2. Nor ſhall their expectation in GOD be fruſtrate; and there is the comfort.</p>
                  <p>I will cleare theſe premiſſes, and then conclude.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Churches expectation from the world is never decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. What doth ſhe expect? As aforeſaid, <hi>Affliction</hi> and <hi>Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution</hi> thence; Her <hi>Lord</hi> hath bid her expect it, for the world love their owne, not His people, as they love not <hi>Him;</hi> and they muſt not look to fare better then their <hi>Lord:</hi> Affliction in the world, Perſecution from the world, is a part of the Churches Dowry. See what a <hi>Ioynter</hi> her Good <hi>Lord</hi> hath made His <hi>Church</hi> and People! He hath given to her All, Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and All, the world and All, ALL THINGS <note n="(b)" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 21</note> ARE YOURS, you ſhall profit and receive benefit from all, even from
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:111850:20"/> all that is called evill in the world: <hi>All is yours.</hi> There we reade the particulars of her Dowry, and amongſt them, DEATH, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, perſecutions, pains, ſorrows, troubles in the fleſh, (that is <hi>Death)</hi> and all this is in the <hi>Churches</hi> Dowry: no Part or Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of it is ſo large as this, for it containes <hi>neceſſities, diſtreſſes, ſtripes, impriſonments, tumults, labours, watchings, faſtings;</hi> all this a very DEATH to a mans ſenſe, and preſent feeling. Is it not think you <hi>Death</hi> to be as the Church is in ſome of her people al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes? <note place="margin">2 Cor 6. 4, 5.</note> In <hi>journyings, in perils of waters, in perils of robbers, in perils by her owne Countreymen, in perils by the heathen, in perils in the City, in perils in the wilderneſſe, in perils amongst falſe brethren,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11. 26.</note> 
                     <hi>in wearineſſe, and painfulneſſe.</hi> That was <hi>Pauls</hi> caſe you wil ſay. Nay it is the <hi>Churches</hi> caſe with ſome of her ſons and daughters, and it will be their caſe unto the worlds end. And certainly all this is a very <hi>death:</hi> To ſojourne in <hi>Meſech,</hi> to dwell in the tents of <hi>Kedar,</hi> amongſt them <hi>that hate peace,</hi> a very <hi>Death</hi> all this, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <note place="margin">Pſal. 120.</note> indeed graciouſly and gloriouſly, through GOD, that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders all for Good; but a very death to ſenſe, to fleſh and bloud. But it is her portion in this life (and no longer, but <hi>durante vitâ,</hi> a ſpan, a little <hi>moment,</hi> in compariſon to eternity, in the heavens, where <hi>God</hi> hath time enough to doe them good, and refreſh their hearts after their hard labours here, with joyes there unſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and long-laſting pleaſures, laſting as long as eternity is long, <hi>for ever:</hi> but I ſay their ſorrowes laſt no longer but <hi>durante vitâ)</hi> and diſpoſed to her as a <hi>Legacie</hi> by her EVERLASTING FATHER, and ſhe is content. Content! A poore and beggerly expreſſion; ſhe rejoyceth in her portion: for all that, which went before comes in at laſt with advantage, adding very much to the weight of her crowne: ſo ſhe bleſſeth <hi>God</hi> for all, but for nothing ſo much as for <hi>death,</hi> for it makes the world nothing to her while ſhe lives, and when ſhe dies, ſets her cleare of all, that we call <hi>Evill;</hi> makes her compleat throughout, FITTED and <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>Meet</hi> for after<hi>-Glory.</hi> Death in ſome ſort is like the <hi>Whale,</hi> which ſwallowed <hi>Ionah,</hi> a terrible thing; but it waſteth the man to Land, ſetteth him cleare from all winds and ſtormes.</p>
                  <p>But <hi>Death</hi> is Part of the Churches Dowry; her lot To bee made the <hi>portion of foxes;</hi> To bee perſecuted in this world: ſhee hath ſo much of Heaven in her, that ſhee muſt fare the worſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:111850:20"/> in the world, which knowes none, favours none heartily but <hi>its owne;</hi> Without controverſy, perſecution is the note of a True Church, There is <hi>God</hi> or ſomething of <hi>God,</hi> ſome plaine cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of His Image, againſt whom the Aſſemblies of violent men, The <hi>Nimrods,</hi> The <hi>Eſaus,</hi> The <hi>Neroes</hi> of the world do bend themſelves.</p>
                  <p>But can this People endure all this hardſhip? are they able to <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                     </label> beare up againſt all this perſecution from the tongues and hands of violent men?</p>
                  <p>Yes, no doubt of that, for <hi>God</hi> hath fitted them for ſhocks, and <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                     </label> brunts, and violent blaſts; Hee hath made their faces like flints, their ſhoulders like braſſe, their Hands and Armes like Iron. What <note place="margin">Eſay 1. 5, 7. Jer. 1. 18.</note> can the Adverſary doe now? The blaſt of the terrible ones, what can it availe? It is anſwered; As much as a ſtorme againſt <hi>a bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zin</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Eſay 25. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>wall:</hi> ſo the SPIRIT ſcornes what <hi>fleſh</hi> can doe againſt <hi>Him. Greater is He That is in you, Then hee that is in the world.</hi> 
                     <note n="(k)" place="margin">1 Joh. 4. 4.</note> Theſe people are reſolved upon that, and they have <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the world;</hi> ſhould then ſuch men as they <hi>feare,</hi> when they heare the <hi>Defaming of many,</hi> (which they looke to heare) and crying out <hi>violence and ſpoile?</hi> Should ſuch men as theſe feare? <note place="margin">Jer. 20. 8, 10.</note> No, They cannot bee affraid with any amazement, for <hi>I am with them ſaith The</hi> 
                     <note n="(a)" place="margin">Jer. 1. 19.</note> LORD, they are aſſured of that. What then? Then what They will follows, for They will ask nothing, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to His will. If they have written down that, as one ſaith, then they may write what they wil, for GOD is <hi>with them,</hi> then all is with them, That can make for their proviſion and protection; <hi>They ſhall dwell on high, their place of Defence ſhall be the munitions of Rocks;</hi> BREAD <hi>ſhall be given them;</hi> their WATERS <hi>ſhall bee ſure</hi> 
                     <note n="(b)" place="margin">Eſay 33. 16 <hi>Ac ſi dice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>et p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ris &amp; inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>is Dei culto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ibus nihil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futurum panis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nim &amp; a quae nomine ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat omnia, &amp;c.</hi> Cal. Jer. 20. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>God</hi> is with them, Then All That is in <hi>God,</hi> His <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, wiſdome, Power,</hi> All ſhall be laid out for them, to make all that is needfull for them, ſure unto them. And then touching their Adverſary, though hee bee a <hi>Legion,</hi> this followes; <hi>hee ſhall fight againſt them, but hee ſhall not prevaile againſt them: The</hi> LORD IS WITH ME <hi>as a</hi> MIGHTY TERRIBLE ONE, <hi>therfore my perſecuters ſhall ſtumble &amp; be greatly aſhamed; his ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting confuſion ſhall never bee forgotten.</hi> Nay, the adverſary ſhall bee ſo far from hurting them, that hee ſhall do them good, and they ſhall hurt him; for now that <hi>God</hi> is with them, they have
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:111850:21"/> Armes of ſteele, and feete of braſſe, and they ſhall <hi>threſh the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines like ſtraw, and the hills like Chaffe, and come upon Princes as</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Eſai. 41. 15. 25.</note> 
                     <hi>upon morter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Are the Righteous people aſſured of all this?</p>
                  <p>Yes, for the Lord hath ſaid it, as wee have read, Hee hath given His word for their ſecurity, they take it, are ſecure, fixed and Reſt thereon. As their expectation from the world never deceived them ſince the world was, and they were in the world; So, nor ſhall their expectation from <hi>God</hi> faile them, they have an aſſured confidence of That. Shall the expectation of the Righteous faile? No, the <hi>Lord</hi> forbid, nay the <hi>Lord</hi> forgive u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to them any ſuch miſgiving thoughts within them. The <hi>hope of the Righteous ſhall bee gladneſſe: but the expectation of the wicked ſhall periſh.</hi> 
                     <note n="(b)" place="margin">2 Pro. 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 10. 18.</note> Can the Righteous feare this, That their hope ſhal fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le them? No; It cannot bee, for they have <hi>ſet their hope in God.</hi> The hope of the wicked ſhal be <hi>cut off: they ſhall be afraid and aſhamed</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> (the word) <hi>their expectation; and of</hi> (the Content<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ents there) <hi>their Glory,</hi> 
                     <note n="(c)" place="margin">Eſai. 20. 5.</note> And now, LORD, <hi>what</hi> 
                     <note n="(d)" place="margin">Pſal. 39. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>wait I for? ſayes</hi> DAVID. As if the ſervant of The LORD had ſaid; doe I waite, doe I expect, doe I looke for Peace, Comfort, eſtabliſhment and ſatisfaction from the world? do I ſeeke <hi>great things</hi> for my ſelfe therein? Thou knoweſt, LORD, what I wait for, none of all this from the world; But, as it followes, <hi>my hope</hi> is in <hi>Thee.</hi> What an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable thing were it, how unworthy of GOD, The <hi>God</hi> not of ſome but of all conſolations, how unworthy a thought of Him, To thinke, That a poore creature, who hath ſet his <hi>hope</hi> in GOD, expects all from <hi>Him,</hi> from The world nothing at all; how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy a thought, That This GOD will deceive this poore crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that waites for Him; though Hee <hi>hideth His face,</hi> yet lookes for Him: He frownes upon him, anſwers him Roughly, yet this ſoul expects from <hi>Him;</hi> notwithſtanding what is ſaid or done, the poore ſoule will not returne <hi>to vanity,</hi> hee will not looke to the world, hee will wait, hee hath <hi>ſet</hi> his <hi>hope</hi> in GOD, hee will looke for <hi>Him;</hi> Will the LORD deceive this Man, that expects all from Him, hath ſet his hope upon Him? It is ſure enough, <hi>Hee</hi> will not; <hi>The needy ſhall not bee alway forgotten; the hopes of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſhall not periſh for ever:</hi> 
                     <note n="(e)" place="margin">Pſal. 9. 18.</note> The poore and needy mans ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation (ſet upon God) is not delayed, but deferred, and ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:111850:21"/> Why? To open the mouth and heart wider, that the more comfort may come in at laſt; and that their heart and JOY there may be <note n="(g)" place="margin">Joh. 16. 24. Pſal. 40. 1. Eſay 8. 17.</note> FULL. <hi>They have waited patiently</hi> for The LORD, they waited upon <hi>Him.</hi> They, When He <hi>hid His face, then they looked for Him:</hi> They waited the time, when He would be graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Now hearken, <hi>Therefore will The</hi> LORD <hi>wait that He may be gracious unto you: and therefore He will be exalted, That he may have mercie upon you: for The Lord is a God of judgement, Bleſſed</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Eſay 30. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>are all they that wait for Him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ai, but <hi>hope deferred maketh the heart ſick.</hi> That is true, but <note place="margin">Pro. 13. 12.</note> there is a time comming, when the heart ſhall recover, be made every whit whole, and perfectly well againe: and it ſhall be the more haile and comforted, the ſicker it was: for <hi>When the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire commeth it is a tree of life.</hi> Therefore though The <hi>Lord</hi> tarry, the ſoule will patiently wait for Him, becauſe He will <hi>ſurely</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Hab. 2. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>come,</hi> and <hi>will not tarry.</hi> And when He, That was ſo long expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, waited-looked-for, when He commeth (and then He comes, and Tarries not, when the Churches ſeaſon is come) then He makes amends for His long tarrying (as the world thought, and ſometimes the Church alſo, and in her haſte counted it <hi>ſlackneſſe)</hi> He tarryed ſo long, that He might come in ſeaſon, that His peoples joy might be brim-full: when their hearts, wearyed with long <hi>waiting,</hi> ſhall the more rejoyce, and their wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered bones <note n="(o)" place="margin">Eſay 66. 14</note> ſhall flouriſh like an herbe: For it ſhall be ſaid in that day, (after their long waltings) <hi>Loe This is our</hi> GOD, <hi>we have waited for Him; This is The</hi> LORD, <hi>we have waited for</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Eſay 25. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>Him:</hi> and we are glad He is come; with all our hearts doe we rejoyce in His ſalvation, for it is His, a marvailous, great, excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſalvation, the greater, the longer it ſtayed: And now theſe waiting people ſhall <hi>renew their ſtrength, they ſhall mount up with</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Eſay 40. 31.</note> 
                     <hi>wings as Eagles, they ſhall run and not be weary, and they ſhall walk and not faint.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We are concluded now upon theſe Points,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That the righteous mans expectation from the world will not deceive him; what the world and the god therein can doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, ſhall be done, he expects it, therefore they ſhall not be able to doe him hurt.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. His expectation from <hi>God</hi> cannot deceive him; for GOD
<pb facs="tcp:111850:22"/> is faithfull: They that wait for Him, (doe expect all from Him, and from the world nothing but affliction thence) ſhall not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of their waiting, for GOD will come in ſeaſon, and not tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, when they ſhall be moſt glad of His comming, and ſay, It is beſt of all that He came not ſooner: for now their hearts are brim-full of joy: So they have concluded: In aſſured confidence hereof, theſ people are not afraid now with any amazement: As their <hi>hope</hi> is in GOD, ſo is their <hi>heart</hi> and <hi>love</hi> ſet upon Him alſo. This followes,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. II.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Righteous love</hi> God: <hi>That Love caſteth forth Feare: Sad ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections cleared to the hearts of the righteous: God comes-in to ſuccour and reſcue thoſe, whom He loveth, not always when they call, but alwaies in ſeaſon, and fitteſt time: Seldome to their</hi> wil, <hi>but ever to their</hi> weal, <hi>when they ſhall ſee leaſt in themſelves, and moſt in God: The perſons, whom</hi> God <hi>loveth, ſhall be afflicted, but</hi> for their good.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>THe Righteous <hi>love</hi> GOD: And <hi>Love</hi> to the ſoule is like the <hi>Rudder</hi> to the Ship, it turnes about all the powers and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of the ſoule, and all to <hi>God;</hi> It lades and unlades all the goods there, all for GODS <hi>glory;</hi> it receives all in, and gives all forth for that ſame great end: ſo <hi>Love</hi> doth. I have ſaid all, when <hi>I</hi> have ſaid, The Righteous <hi>love</hi> GOD. It <hi>formes</hi> every work they doe; and nothing forms a man or his work ſo dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly as <hi>Love</hi> doth, Love to God, Love to His Truth, Love to His People, Love to their peace; This inflames mens mindes, works them ſuddenly to great perfection, facilitates the work, makes it ſlide on. Nay farther, as one obſerves truly, <q>That all other Affections, though they raiſe the minde, yet they doe it by diſtorting, and uncomelineſſe of extaſies, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes; but onely <hi>Love</hi> doth exalt the mind, and nevert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eleſſe, at the ſame inſtant, doth ſettle and compoſe it:</q> So in all other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies, though they advance Nature, yet they are ſubject to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:111850:22"/> exceſſe: onely Charity admitteth no exceſſe. The righteous love God. I have ſaid all.</p>
                  <p>Why, but all will ſay as much: No man in the world, but wil <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                     </label> ſay, <hi>I love</hi> GOD: he dares not, nay he is aſhamed to ſay other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
                  <p>True, I will reply ſhortly to this, and once for all, for all will <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> ſay as much touching their <hi>feare</hi> too, and their <hi>truſt</hi> alſo, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>As the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> ſo the <hi>love</hi> of <hi>God</hi> is not in <hi>word,</hi> but in <hi>power:</hi> GOD <hi>doth know</hi> (that is, approves) <hi>not the ſpeech of them, that ſay</hi> 
                     <note n="(a)" place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 19, 20.</note> 
                     <hi>ſo, but the power of them, that doe ſo:</hi> That love The Lord, not in <hi>word,</hi> but in <hi>deed.</hi> We have all, I verily beleeve it, a kind of faint, weak, wateriſh <hi>love,</hi> which indeed the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture calls an hatred, when the creature hath the ſtrength, and as I may ſay, the firſt-borne of our love: and <hi>God</hi> the after-birth, which is of no account with <hi>Him,</hi> but counted as aforeſaid. The righteous people <hi>love God;</hi> They ſee an excellencie in <hi>God,</hi> a tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeendent goodneſſe. As it was ſaid of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> when they ſaw their boldneſſe, They <hi>tooke knowledge of them that they had</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Acts 4. 13.</note> 
                     <hi>been with Ieſus:</hi> So, doe we obſerve the Saints love to Chriſt! We muſt take knowledge, That the City of God doe <hi>know</hi> The <hi>Lord Chriſt,</hi> they have and doe ſee His Goodneſſe; They are with Him by their graces of <hi>love,</hi> and <hi>faith;</hi> they <hi>converſe</hi> with Him day and night. Therefore they <hi>ſo love God,</hi> even <hi>as</hi> they <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie Him,</hi> As <note n="(b)" place="margin">Rom. 1. 21. Exod. 15. 11. 1 Tim. 6. 15.</note> GOD, <hi>glorious in holineſſe, fearfull in praiſes, doing wonders: The onely Potentate, The King of Kings and Lord of Lords.</hi> They <hi>Love</hi> GOD <hi>as</hi> they are <hi>thankefull</hi> to <hi>Him, as</hi> To GOD, in Whom they live, move, and have their Being: in Whoſe hands is their <hi>Time,</hi> their Breath, and all their wayes: from Whom they have all things richly to enjoy, to whom He communicates Himſelf: ſo they glorifie Him, ſo they are thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and ſo they <hi>love</hi> HIM with an exceeding love, a love that commands in chiefe; the great <hi>Centurion,</hi> it commands all within and without, to ſpeak, to doe, to ſtrive for <hi>God,</hi> for ſo they love HIM with a predominate <hi>love,</hi> which carryeth the ſoul on high. And where this love of God rules, there <hi>peace</hi> rules, be the earth never ſo unquiet. Get we this <hi>love</hi> rooted in our hearts; it is the fitteſt of any thing to expell <hi>feare,</hi> to keep downe the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings of it, for it maintains and guards Reaſon, and raiſeth the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:111850:23"/> ſoule above the world, ſo as it can bid defiance to <hi>death,</hi> and then to unreaſonable men, and devils too. If I beare a true <hi>love</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> ſtronger then death, if ſo, then I can beare any thing; I can goe through fire, and water, all along before the face and noſe of the adverſaries, (if I am called to do it) and feare nothing. The <hi>love</hi> of GOD conſtraines me, yea commands me, and, as the <hi>peace of</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Phil. 4. 7. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>God, keeps</hi> and <hi>ſafeguards</hi> me alſo; It <hi>keeps</hi> my <hi>heart</hi> and <hi>mind,</hi> my <hi>ſoul</hi> and my <hi>ſpirit, through Chriſt Ieſus:</hi> It keeps my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that there be no defilement there through the errors of wicked men. It keeps my <hi>will,</hi> that there be no perverſeneſſe there, not ſubdued and brought under: It keeps my <hi>affections,</hi> that they be cleane and holy; that my hatred be to all <hi>iniquity,</hi> and my love to <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> for I <hi>love God,</hi> how then ſhould I think or doe thus and thus, and ſo ſin againſt him? The <hi>love</hi> of God keeps me in perfect peace, ſo far as that <hi>love</hi> is perfect in me. If a man can reſolve himſelf (by the Spirit) <hi>That God loves him,</hi> That he is in Chriſt reconciled unto Him, This is enough To diſſolve the thickeſt cloud of feare, overcaſting the ſoule; enough to take off the edge, and blunt that eager and keene paſſion, which ſo cuts, and lanceth the ſpirits: for then, he can ſay alſo, <hi>He loves GOD with a CHILD-like love,</hi> as a child loves the father; ſo as he can repoſe himſelfe in his fathers lap or boſome, in aſſured confidence <hi>He careth for him;</hi> and then he can be as bold as <hi>Paul</hi> was, and as well perſwaded, <hi>That neither death, nor life, nor An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, nor Principalities, nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature, ſhall be able to ſeparate us from the love of God,</hi> 
                     <note n="(a)" place="margin">Rom. 8. 38, 39.</note> 
                     <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The work then of a Chriſtian is to cleare this point; for when that is done, all is done; he lives as a man in the upper Region of the world, <hi>riding upon the high places of the earth,</hi> above the winds <note place="margin">Eſav 58. 14.</note> and ſtormes, which infeſt and trouble us here below. I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber I have read of one, who being upon a tempeſtuous ſea, and his ſhip almoſt covered with waves, and the paſſengers there al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt dead with feare, was, not withſtanding, very cheerfull and comfortable, calme and quiet in his mind, rather inclined to ſing then to mourne: Being asked the reaſon of his ſettlement, and ſo quiet repoſe of ſpirit, anſwered thus: <hi>My Father is the Pilot of the ſhip; He is at the ſterne, holds the helme: He loves me, I love</hi>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:111850:23"/> 
                     <hi>Him,</hi> The winds and ſtormes fulfilling his word, <note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſal. 148. 8</note> 
                     <hi>He bids them riſe, and they are up, and ſo bluſtering: then (He chideth) He rebuketh them, then they fall and are ſtill. I know and am well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 8. 26.</note> 
                     <hi>whether ſtormes or calmes, I ſhall get to my Heaven, and in paſſage thither nothing ſhall doe me hurt, every thing ſhall doe me good from His hand that loves</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Chryſoſt. <hi>Faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le impetratur ſemper quod filius poſtulat.</hi> Ter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ul. de po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n. c. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>me. And this makes me fearleſſe, this calmes me within, what unquiet motions ſoever are without.</hi> Oh of what mighty concernment is this, in theſe times! when <hi>the commandement is gone forth to reſtore and to build Ieruſalems wall,</hi> (evermore TROUBLOUS TIMES) <note n="(c)" place="margin">Dan. 9. 25.</note> That every man ſhould labour to cleare his ſpirit (by the Spirit) at this great point, <hi>The love of</hi> GOD <hi>towards him, his love to</hi> GOD; for this makes faire weather within, however tempeſtuous it is abroad. Here comes in an Objection, I will reſolve it at the firſt, and once for all.</p>
                  <p>A man may love GOD, and feare Him too, (which followes <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                     </label> next) and obey Him alſo, and all this from the heart, and yet he may be afraid: he may have a great deale of <hi>love,</hi> and <hi>faith</hi> too, and yet have a great deale of feare; he may love, and feare God above many, and yet feare the creature more then is meet.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Iacob,</hi> a very good man, he loved <hi>God</hi> with all his heart, yet <hi>Iacob was</hi> GREATLY <note n="(a)" place="margin">Gen. 32. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>afraid.</hi> [GREATLY,] Marke that.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>David,</hi> a man after <hi>Gods</hi> owne heart, yet heare him what he ſaith, <hi>Fearfulneſſe and trembling are come upon me, and terror hath overwhelmed me.</hi> 
                     <note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſal. 52. 5.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Iehoſhaphat,</hi> a very good King, yet <hi>he feared.</hi> 
                     <note n="(c)" place="margin">2 Chr. 20. 3.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. The Diſciples, choiſe men all, ſuch as loved their Maſter with all their heart, and with their whole ſoule, yet <hi>fearfull.</hi> 
                     <note n="(d)" place="margin">Mat. 8. 26.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Before the Anſwer, note this: A man may love God much, and yet feare much hurt from the creature. And a man may have no <hi>love</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> and yet no feare of the creature: ſo ſtupified his ſpirit may be. Now I anſwer, indeed the Context anſwers it for me.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iacob</hi> was greatly afraid and diſtreſſed; how then? his feare <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> did not put him off from duty, but engaged him thereunto. Now ſee how wiſely he diſpoſeth of things, then rouls himſelfe and <note place="margin">Gen. 32. 7, 8, 9, &amp;c.</note> all his upon GOD, wraps up his ſoule, and all his concernments
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:111850:24"/> in a promiſe, and there is an end of the matter, and enough for <hi>Iacob.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>2. <hi>Davids</hi> caſe was extraordinary, a thick cloud was over his ſpirit, and the face of God was clouded towards him too. He <note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>et Deus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la eſt tenta ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>tudo quae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>beſcat.</hi> Cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. in Pſal. 55.</note> had troubles within, and ſtorms without; whether <hi>Saul</hi> purſued him, or his owne ſon, it is not reſolved, but he was in the ſtraits, and <hi>God</hi> was not ſo preſent to ſenſe, and then we muſt <hi>give the ſtouteſt heart leave to quaile,</hi> ſaith Maſter <hi>Calvin.</hi> The Concluſion is ſure and certaine; Cleare your evidence, That <hi>God</hi> loves you, and you ſhall cleare your ſpirits of theſe thick fogs which <hi>feare</hi> raiſeth. Nay, if you cannot cleare your evidence, but God will keep you humble all your dayes, in a hanging, and doubtful eſtate, yet caſt your ſelfe upon Him; though He kill, yet truſt in Him. But more of this a little after.</p>
                  <p>3. <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> feared alſo, for hee heard that which would quicken any man that had life in him: <hi>There commeth a great multitude againſt thee.</hi> 
                     <note n="(e)" place="margin">2 Chron. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> Then <hi>he</hi> FEARED. <note n="(f)" place="margin">ver. 3.</note> But take the following words, <hi>And ſet himſelfe to ſeek the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> His Feare put him upon Duty. Then be remembred <hi>God,</hi> in Whoſe hand is power and might, <hi>Art not Thou God in heaven?</hi> 
                     <note n="(g)" place="margin">ver. 6.</note> Then he pleads his intereſt in his God, <hi>Art not Thou</hi> OUR GOD? <note n="(h)" place="margin">ver. 7.</note> Then he cals to mind the right hand of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, what He had done of old. O bleſſed be God for that feare, (as was ſaid before) you cannot have too much of that feare, which renders you much in ſeeking, which makes you love much, feare much, obey much.</p>
                  <p>4. The Diſciples were fearfull, but they were prayerfull; They would not let GOD <hi>alone;</hi> they would <hi>give Him no reſt.</hi> GOD ſeemes to be (for he ſpeaketh to our capacity) as <hi>Ionah,</hi> aſleep, when the Ship of the Church is covered with waves. Nay The <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> was, at that time, as clothed with our fleſh, ſo ſubject to our infirmities, and was aſleep: And then the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples are fearfull, All will be caſt away, Chriſt and all. Indeed they that feare the Church will be drowned, doe feare that Chriſt will be drowned too: for if the Body drowne, the Head muſt drowne; and if the Head drowne not, the Body cannot drown: it may be overwhelmed with great waters of affliction. While the Head is above, the Body is ſafe enough. But ſuch was the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:111850:24"/> Diſciples infirmity at this time, and ſuch was our Lords infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty at that time, that then He was aſleep. What then? They a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woke <hi>God</hi> with their prayers, as we know the manner is. A bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed feare then (as was ſaid) which makes a man a wake Chriſt by his importunity; which puts a man upon duty, makes him more prayerfull, makes him love more, and cling to his Father the faſter, ſo <hi>Iacob,</hi> ſo <hi>David,</hi> ſo <hi>Iehoſhaphat,</hi> ſo the <hi>Diſciples</hi> feared, ſo as they did their Duty the better.</p>
                  <p>But much may be ſaid touching this <hi>love</hi> of GOD: It is not <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                     </label> ſuch a <hi>Cure</hi> of <hi>feare,</hi> not ſuch a buckler to a perſon; we ſee here how the fore-mentioned were <hi>terrified,</hi> yet they <hi>loved</hi> GOD. Look I pray you and it is a ſad ſight, <hi>Thou art become cruel to me, with Thy ſtrong hand Thou oppoſeſt Thy ſelfe againſt me. Thou lifteſt me up to the wind, Thou cauſeſt me to ride upon it, and diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt my ſubſtance.</hi> 
                     <note n="(a)" place="margin">Job 30. 21, 22.</note> I will defer the Anſwer to this till anon. The Objection now runs thus: Not how the <hi>Lord</hi> hath dealt with particular perſons, whom He loves dearly: nor what thoſe perſons have ſaid, when they walked in darkneſſe, and ſaw no light, [We muſt take it for granted, That there are ſad expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons breaking forth of the lips, when there are grievous apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions within the ſoule] But How he hath dealt with a whole Nation, and that the <hi>dearly beloved of Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſoul;</hi> He hath delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſuch a Nation into <hi>His enemies hands:</hi> 
                     <note n="(c)" place="margin">Jer. 12. 7.</note> So that they who hated them, have Lorded it over them, have dealt <hi>hatefully</hi> and deſpitefully with them. <note n="(d)" place="margin">Ezek. 23. 28, 29.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>This cannot be denied, and ſince His <hi>Iudgements are manifeſt,</hi> and the Reaſons of them alſo are written and made legible for <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> our inſtruction, we ſtand charged to take good notice of them here, I meane The Reaſons, which moved The <hi>Lord</hi> to proceed in wrath againſt His <hi>dearly beloved,</hi> and to caſt them out of their owne Land, and into the hands of them, from whom <hi>their mind</hi> was <hi>alienated</hi> firſt.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. When GODS <hi>People</hi> doe not walke As His People; when He takes them neere unto Himſelfe, and they walk looſe with him; not as a ſeparated and peculiar people to Him, whom He hath ſeparated, and beſtowed upon them ſpeciall and peculiar mercies. When His people walke ſo <hi>contrary</hi> to Him, and their owne Proteſtation, Then His manner is to walke <hi>contrary</hi> to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:111850:25"/> them. He may goe out of that path when He liſteth, and exempt a Nation from the generall rule: But this is His <hi>manner;</hi> He may d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with us according to His <hi>Prerogative Royall,</hi> which is ever in ſhewing mercy: He may doe ſo, but it is extraordinary, as we have cauſe to obſerve above all the Nations in the world.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. When His People do not do according to the CHARGE, <note n="(l)" place="margin">Deut. 25 19</note> 
                     <hi>utterly to root out the name of Amalek,</hi> that old and ancient enemy to His Church, and the very ſame to this day: when this charge is neglected or ſlighted, and the contrary is done; <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lek</hi> is countenanced, encouraged, foſtered, ſuffered to get head; Then it ſhall come to paſſe, That theſe Adverſaries and enemies ſhall be <hi>pricks</hi> in your eyes, and <hi>thornes in your ſides,</hi> and ſhall <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>xe you in the Land wherein you dwell,</hi> 
                     <note n="(m)" place="margin">Num 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 35.</note> 
                     <hi>ſaith the Lord.</hi> They ſhall be ſnares and traps unto you, untill ye periſh from off the good Land, which The Lord your God hath given you. <note n="(n)" place="margin">Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 23. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> It is the good word of The Lord, which is the ſame for ever.</p>
                  <p>3. When the Rulers, the Princes and Judges of the earth are like the evening wolves, ravening the prey: <note n="(o)" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 22.</note> What then? Then, for their ſakes, <hi>Zion muſt be plowed as a field.</hi> 
                     <note n="(p)" place="margin">Mich 3. 11 Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ph. 3. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>zech. 22.</note> When the Prieſts violate the Law, profane the holy things, devoure ſoules, hide their eyes <hi>from the Sabbath,</hi> put no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the holy and profane: What then? Then <hi>peace is taken from the earth:</hi> When the Sabbaths are gone, when the people <note place="margin">Mic. 5. 12, 13.</note> oppreſſe, exerciſe tyrannie, and vexe the poore and needy: When the Prieſts are become brutiſh, the people no better: when they that are good, and have power, ſit ſtill, and contend not againſt the ſtreame: Then we reade this, <hi>All ye beaſts of the field, come to</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Eſay 56. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>devoure, yea all the beaſts of the forreſt.</hi> 
                     <note n="(q)" place="margin">Jer. 12. 9.</note> His Watchmen are blind, and the Paſtors are become brutiſh: <note n="(r)" place="margin">Jer. 10. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> what then? Then <hi>all their flocks ſhall be ſcattered.</hi> Behold the noiſe of the <hi>bruit is come,</hi> and a great commotion to make <hi>Cities deſolate,</hi> and <hi>a den of dragons.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In theſe caſes, The Lord is provoked very much, even til there be <hi>no remedy.</hi> 
                     <note n="(ſ)" place="margin">2 Chr. 36. 16. Jer. 12. 7.</note> And then He forſakes His houſe, leaves His heritage, gives up the <hi>dearly beloved of His ſoule into the hands of her enemies,</hi> lets in judgements like a floud, and it carryeth down all, good and bad, with the impetuouſneſſe of its ſtreame. What, good and bad together? Will the LORD deſtroy the righteous
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:111850:25"/> with the wicked? Yes, No man knoweth either <hi>love,</hi> or <hi>hatred</hi> by <hi>all that is before the eye.</hi> 
                     <note n="(p)" place="margin">Eccleſ. 9. 1.</note> All things come ali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e to all; The ſame Common deſtruction takes away all together, makes no difference: And there is a great reaſon for that, which we muſt take in, in paſſage, for,</p>
                  <p>The Righteous did comply too much with the time, went along with the ſtreame, ſided with the ſtrongeſt in ſight, or looked on heareing Blaſphemies, beholding iniquity and wrong, In the mean time, ſaid and did nothing; <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Jure iſtam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>am quando di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> initus affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guntu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, cum eis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>maram ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, cupus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mando dul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>em peccan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> eis amari eſſe nolue unt.</hi> Aug. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> civ. l. 1. c. 9.</note> ſtood not up <hi>in the gap;</hi> And therefore now he is thruſt down alſo, hurried along with the T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rrent and breaking in of mighty Waters: he is over-whelmed in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lood, even theſe good Men for the reaſon aforeſaid: No difference at all in the ſuffering, for the manner and time thereof; but in the fruit, iſſue and end, an infinite diſtance, and inequality. <q>Where we note, That this difference between the good &amp; bad, in a Common Calamity, is not viſible, not diſcernable by the Eye, &amp; yet a great, wide, and an ever-laſting difference; the good are delivered in it; The bad utterly deſtroyed by it; The good <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Manet diſſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>tud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> paſſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>um etiam in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                                 <desc>•••</desc>
                              </gap>il<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>aſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, &amp; licet in eodem tormento non eſt idem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>tus &amp; viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. Nam ſicut ſub uno igne aurum ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>lat, pal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap> fumat, &amp;c.</hi> Aug. de ci. l. 1. c. 8. Am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s 9. 9.</note> pur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ed; The bad conſumed. Good and bad are in the ſame ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity, But as the Gold and Chaffe are in the ſame fire, The one ſhines there, the other ſmokes, As the ſtubble, and the wheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corne are under the ſame flaile, the one is bruiſed there, the other cleanſed; freed of its Chaffe, and fitted for the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ive, not a Corne <hi>ſhall be loſt.</hi> So alſo one and the ſame violence carryes away all the good and the bad all together; deſtroyeth, waſteth the one with an utter deſtruction: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ut trieth, purgeth, purifieth the good.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is good to note this with all obſervation; for heere we have a Cleere difference betwixt the <hi>good</hi> and the <hi>bad,</hi> betwixt the perſecuted now, and the perſecutors afterwards, The good may fall, but they ſhall bee holpen <hi>with a little help:</hi> And their fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the ſword <hi>and by ſpoyle many dayes,</hi> ſhall be to them as of old it was, <hi>To trie them, and to purge and make them white.</hi> 
                     <note n="(ſ)" place="margin">Dan. 11. 33</note> But for the wicked it is not ſo with them, but as we heard. It is a comfortable ſpeech; <hi>Rejoyce</hi> 
                     <note n="(t)" place="margin">Micah 7. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>not againſt me O mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my:</hi> When <hi>I fall I ſhall ariſe;</hi> But when thou falleſt, Thou ſhalt fall; Thy caſting down ſhall bee like <hi>the fall</hi> of <hi>a millſtone</hi> 
                     <note n="(u)" place="margin">Rev. 18. 21</note> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to great waters, Thou ſhalt riſe no more: <hi>When I fall, I ſhall ariſe;</hi> This is the heritage of them that love The <hi>Lord:</hi> when their
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:111850:26"/> Adverſarie falls he ſhall <hi>riſe no more,</hi> This is the portion of his meaſures for ever.</p>
                  <p>The concluſion is, It ſhall be well with them that love The <hi>Lord.</hi> Nay it is well with them now, though not to <hi>ſenſe,</hi> yet to <hi>faith.</hi> The caſe of <hi>David</hi> was not ordinary; <hi>Iobs</hi> caſe extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary: That which follows will give ſome light and ſome ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to both.</p>
                  <p>It is a moſt prevailing argument, which the ſiſter uſed in behalfe of her brother <hi>Lazarus;</hi> LORD, <hi>behold he whom Thou lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">John 11. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>is ſick.</hi> This will prevaile ſure; It is the mightieſt argument in the world, LORD, The <hi>Perſon, whom Thou loveſt;</hi> The <hi>Cauſe, the Faith, the Truth, the Religion,</hi> WHICH THOU LOVEST is <hi>now in jeopardie;</hi> The Malignants oppoſe it, oppreſſe it, they would thruſt it out of the world, and the profeſſors of it; That which THOU LOVEST, <hi>theſe ſons of the earth doe hate; Thoſe whom Thou loveſt, theſe men would cut off from being a Nation.</hi> Certainly GOD will come in for reſcue now, and worke a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Deliverance. And yet perhaps not at the juſt and ſet time of our over-haſty expectation: Before Deliverance comes, this perſon, whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> loveth, may be ſurpriſed with fearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; <hi>trembling</hi> may <hi>come upon him,</hi> and <hi>horror</hi> may over-whelme him, that it may. The <hi>Cauſe,</hi> the <hi>Truth,</hi> which GOD loveth, may ſeem to be delivered up into the enemies hands, ſo as they may lay the <hi>Glory</hi> of it (for a time, and in the eye of man) in the duſt. Let us conſult with the context once more, and with good conſideration. There we read; <hi>Lord, he whom Thou loveſt, is ſick; when Ieſus heard that He abode two dayes ſtill in the place where He was.</hi> 
                     <note n="(a)" place="margin">John 11. 3.</note> That is a ſtrange matter; we ſhould thinke, and ſo the ſiſters thought too, That when <hi>Ieſus</hi> heard, That The man, whom He loved was ſick, He would have made haſte away, and come with all ſpeede to His ſick friend; But it was not ſo, when He heard THAT, <hi>He abode two dayes ſtill in the ſame place.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">ver. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> Was this His kindneſſe to His friend? <hi>Ieſus loved Martha and her ſiſter and Lazarus:</hi> But His abode two dayes longer, and when He heard that <hi>Lazarus</hi> was ſick, made no cleare proofe of it unto them at that time. Jeſus came indeede, but when <hi>Martha,</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> and the <hi>Iewes</hi> alſo thought it was too late, when the breath was departed, the body laid in a cave, and <hi>a ſtone</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">ver 38.</note>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:111850:26"/> 
                     <hi>laid</hi> upon it foure dayes before <hi>Ieſus</hi> came. Then, and then when the caſe was ſo helpleſſe, and hopeleſſe, then Jeſus came. Truly, that is His manner now, but ſee mighty reaſon for His ſo long tarrying then. Had He come quickly, as ſoone as He was ſent unto, and called for, poſſible it was, That He, who opened the eyes of <hi>the blinde,</hi> might have cauſed <hi>even</hi> this man <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſhould <hi>not have dyed:</hi> 
                     <note n="(b)" place="margin">ver. 37.</note> ſo ſome there reaſoned at that time, and ſo we have reaſoned (in ſuch caſes) ever ſince. The Perſons, or the Cauſe, which Jeſus loveth, have beene in jeopardy; to the eyes of man, in an helpleſſe and hopeleſſe condition; If God had come in to his ſervants and their cauſe ſo ſoone as they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for Him, then their hopes had flouriſhed, but ſtaying till the caſe is deſperate to ſenſe &amp; reaſon, their hope is periſhed. Surely, ſo the ſervants of God have reaſoned many a time. But let the ſervants of The <hi>Lord</hi> well obſerve The <hi>Lords</hi> comming in to theſe two ſiſters, at that time, and they can never diſtruſt The <hi>Lord</hi> at any time. Had their <hi>Lord</hi> come in unto them, when they called for Him, He might have cauſed that even <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſhould not <hi>have dyed.</hi> But then what ſingular thing had Hee done? A Phyſitian, an ordinary man, had done many a time as much as that before Him. But when as He abode two dayes longer in the ſame place, where He was, when He heard of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> ſickneſſe; and ſtayed yet two dayes longer by the way (of ſet purpoſe to let the laſt enemy alone to compleat its conqueſt, to cloſe the pits mouth upon <hi>Lazarus,</hi> and to role a ſtone over him) and now comming in for reſcue, and taking the <hi>prey</hi> out of the hands of the <hi>terrible one;</hi> This made Chriſt admired in all, <hi>that did beleeve:</hi> for now, they muſt needes ſee, The <hi>Glory</hi> of GOD, whereas, had <hi>Ieſus</hi> came at their call, before <hi>Death</hi> had made its conqueſt, they had ſeene no more but the meere exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of power, and skill, which might be put forth by a meere man. Jeſus ſaid plainly (without a figure, for he called death a <note place="margin">John 14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> ſleepe before) <hi>Lazarus is dead, and I am glad for your ſakes.</hi> Why glad that His friend <hi>Lazarus</hi> was dead? and glad for their ſakes? They were all very ſorry that <hi>Lazarus</hi> was dead; and it grieved them to the heart, that Jeſus came not ſooner, for if Jeſus had beene there, their <hi>Brother had not dyed,</hi> ſaid the ſiſter: Then why was Jeſus glad that he was not there? Becauſe, that they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:111850:27"/> beholding His glorious worke in raiſing a putrified car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſſe, they would then <hi>beleeve,</hi> and <hi>rejoice</hi> with <hi>an exceeding joy,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">If any thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> to the advantage of His people <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>peaking to our capaci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty) is glad, and there is joy in Heaven even new.</note> which they had not done, had Jeſus beene there before, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that <hi>Lazarus</hi> had not dyes. We may conclude now; That the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ill come in for the ſafegard and reſcue of His people, <hi>whom He loveth,</hi> of His <hi>Cauſe,</hi> which He ſo favoureth, in ſeaſon, the fitteſt time, when His beloved people ſhall <hi>moſt admire His comming,</hi> beholding the exceeding glory thereof. When is this time? Then, when the Righteous mans hopes are dead to the world, ſenſe and reaſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and when the malignants hopes flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, Then The <hi>Lord</hi> comes in, That is His Time, when the wicked thinke they have their hope in their hands, and when the Righteous are emptied of all creature-confidence, they ſet no hope there, but all in God: Then The Lord comes in, when they are to ſenſe, as <hi>dead bones,</hi> then they ſhall flouriſh like <hi>an herbe,</hi> for <hi>then the hand of the Lord ſhall bee knowne towards His</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">ſay 66. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>ſervants,</hi> when they are <hi>Orphanes,</hi> poore, peeled, helpleſſe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe people, then the <hi>Lord</hi> comes with His comforts, and how doth he comfort? <hi>As one whom His mother comforteth.</hi> Then they ſhall be comforted indeed, <hi>For as a mother comforteth her</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">ver. 13.</note> 
                     <hi>childe, ſo will I comfort you, and you ſhall be comforted:</hi> From theſe premiſes the concluſion is worth the repeating, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calling again and again. <q>The Lord comes in ever to His be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved people moſt ſeaſonably, in the fitteſt and beſt time, when they can ſee the <hi>moſt</hi> of <hi>God</hi> that can be ſeene, and the <hi>leaſt</hi> of the creature.</q> He will come in them, when His people ſhall ſay, if He had come ſooner, it had not beene ſo well, we had not loved Him ſo much, admired Him ſo much, we had not ſeene ſo much of His Glory, we had not ſo <hi>rejoyced in His ſalvation.</hi> So they love God, and ſo they are beloved of Him, therefore they are not afraid, at no time <hi>greatly</hi> troubled. If there be a cloud of feare, there is an eclipſe of <hi>Gods Love,</hi> onely we muſt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber we make an allowance to the beſt man, when wee weigh him upon the ballance, for hee is ſuppoſed ever in a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. <note place="margin">Homo ſupponi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Before we cloſe, let us note this from the premiſſes, That The <hi>Lords</hi> manner is, To exerciſe the perſons whom Hee loveth, with the ſoreſt afflictions; <hi>Ieſus loved Martha and her</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">John. 11. 3.</note>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:111850:27"/> 
                     <hi>ſiſter</hi> and <hi>Lazarus:</hi> therefore Hee would try their patience; He would not come to them at their call, till the caſe was deſperate; till, that they feared, had taken hold of them, and overwhelmed them; <hi>whom the Lord loveth Hee chaſteneth, and ſcourgeth every</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>on whom Hee receiveth. It is</hi> the manner of Parents ſo to doe, not ſcourage ſtrange children, but him, whom they love they will ſcourge. The <hi>Lord</hi> hath delivered up The dearly beloved of His Soule; whither? As we have read, <hi>Into the enemies hands.</hi> It was ever ſo, it is ſo at this Day; hee, whom GOD <hi>loveth,</hi> is ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, robbed, pillaged; the enemies bend all their malice againſt him, whom GOD <hi>loveth;</hi> And <hi>God</hi> ſuffers them ſo to do, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ends ſpoken of before, for theſe here To hide pride from their eyes by hiding the creature from them, To try their pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; To raiſe up their hope after an enduring ſubſtance; To try them, I ſaid, and to pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ge them to make them <hi>white even</hi> 
                     <note n="(c)" place="margin">Dan. 11. 35.</note> 
                     <hi>to the time of the end.</hi> To make them <hi>Meet</hi> for the <hi>inheritance of the Saints in light.</hi> 
                     <note n="(d)" place="margin">Coloſ. 1. 12.</note> It is notable, The <hi>Lord</hi> uſeth theſe vile wretches, as ſcullions, To <hi>purge</hi> and <hi>whiten</hi> His veſſells, oppoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for honour. Indeed the rod of the wicked may bee ſo heavy upon the back of The Righteous, and may raiſe within them ſuch a thick cloud, that hee can hardly diſcerne a <hi>Fatherly love</hi> and <hi>Hand</hi> through it (for there are ſtrange apprehenſions and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blings within the heart, when there is a cup of trembling in the hand:) But it will be faire weather anon; The thick cloud ſhall bee diſſolved, and The <hi>FATHERS love</hi> will ſhine forth the clearer, the thicker the cloud hath been, The FATHERS <hi>love</hi> over-rules the Adverſary, binds him, <hi>meaſureth out</hi> the effects of their fury and mallice, orders all as Hee did that long captivity, FOR THY <note n="(c)" place="margin">Jer. 24. 5.</note> GOOD, whom Hee loveth; That is the comfort and the concluſion of this point, <hi>for their Good, whom Hee loveth,</hi> And who make Him their feare.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:111850:28"/>
                  <head>CHAP. III.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Righteous feare God,</hi> as <hi>God; they that doe ſo, cannot feare the creature.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>THe <hi>Righteous feare</hi> GOD; what then? I have ſaid all. They <hi>feare</hi> GOD, then they feare neither men, nor Divells. If wee obſerve, wee meete with this expreſſion often, I FEARED. what? The Creature, what hee could doe againſt me; I was afraid of a Man, and then hee deſerted his Duty, ran away from GOD and from himſelfe. Wee read againe, I know not how of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>I feare</hi> GOD; And then hee feares nothing, hee goes on, as bold as a lion, the enemy is behind him, a mountain of <hi>ſtraits</hi> on each hand, a ſea of troubles before him, yet he goes on with the more courage: hee ſets GOD before his eyes, Whom hee ſerves, Whom hee feares, His <hi>Cauſe,</hi> His <hi>Glory,</hi> and goes on, breaks through the <hi>ſtraits,</hi> as you will doe through a ſpiders web. Hee feares <hi>God,</hi> of whom ſhould he be afraid? He fears <hi>God,</hi> he keeps himſelfe from every evill work, though he might commit it in ſecret, <note n="(d)" place="margin">Levit. 19. 14</note> no eye upon him, His Lords eye, Which <hi>runs through the world,</hi> 
                     <note n="(e)" place="margin">2 Chron. 26. 9.</note> That is upon him, That awes him, even to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving his thoughts, and bringing them into ſubjection, and them moſt of all. So he <hi>feares</hi> GOD, And the Armies of men, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, not ſo much as the wicked have feared an Army of flies. Let <note n="(f)" place="margin">Eſai. 33. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>ſinners in</hi> ZION, who ſeeme to maintain the eſtabliſhed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion with their mouth, and perſecute it with their hand, let them be afraid, <hi>fearfulneſſe muſt ſurpriſe the Hypocrites,</hi> thoſe that profeſſe one thing, and doe another: But this man feares <hi>God,</hi> that is, <hi>He walks righteouſly, ſpeaketh uprightly, deſpiſeth the</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">ver. 15.</note> 
                     <hi>gaine of oppreſſions, ſhaketh his hands from holding of bribes, ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth his eare from hearing of bloud,</hi> (Oh how far is he from ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of it) <hi>ſhutteth his eye from ſeeing evill.</hi> Reade on. <hi>He ſhall dwell on high, his defence ſhall be the munitions of rocks, bread ſhall be</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">ver. 16.</note> 
                     <hi>given him, and his waters ſhall be ſure.</hi> And he is ſure of all this, for he <hi>fears</hi> GOD, and all we reade before is but the reſult of that <hi>feare.</hi> Why then, Lions, and Beares, and Wolves, and Foxes, I meane (for ſo the Scripture doth) by theſe, bloody and treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:111850:28"/> men, theſe may be hungry and ſtarved too, they may feare famine. The righteous, who feare God, they feare it not; In fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Fides famem non metuit.</hi> Hieron.</note> that is, in every extremity, they ſhall be provided for, they ſhall have <hi>enough,</hi> for they have <hi>God,</hi> and he is <hi>All.</hi> I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract. Indeed, and in truth, the <hi>feare of</hi> GOD (for it contains the whole Duty of man) is <hi>excellent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now I know what All will ſay; for I know their hearts and their language there by my owne. I and every man will ſay for himſelf, <hi>I feare</hi> GOD too, that I do: hee that feares not an oath, (that is too paticular) he that feares not to ſin before The Lord; nay, he, that doth violence to the law, and ſheds blood to his power, the Man that neither feareth God nor reverenceth man, wil ſay, I <hi>feare</hi> GOD too. It is as commonly ſaid as any thing in the world, for every man ſayes it, as was ſaid, and anſwered before. It is not conſiderable then what men <hi>ſay,</hi> but what men <hi>doe;</hi> not what they profeſſe with the tongue, but what they act with the hand. They profeſſe, ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> that they <hi>feare</hi> GOD, (for they that <hi>know</hi> GOD, <hi>feare Him)</hi> but <hi>in works they deny Him, being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Titus 1. 16.</note> 
                     <hi>and diſobedient, and unto every good worke, reprobate.</hi> They walk cleane contrary to that man, that <hi>feares God,</hi> (wee heard how he walketh, and how he ſpeaketh) and yet they <hi>feare</hi> GOD. It is but a bare profeſſion ſo, with the mouth onely. But obſerve what their caſe will be when their <note n="(b)" place="margin">Jer. 2. 24.</note> 
                     <hi>month</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, and they muſt caſt-out their ſorrows, they will be <hi>afraid;</hi> then <hi>fear fulneſſe will ſurpriſe them,</hi> and heare them what they <note place="margin">Eſai. 33. 14.</note> ſay; <hi>Who among us ſhall dwell with the devouring fire? Who among us ſhall dwell with the everlaſting burnings?</hi> And ſo much be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to my owne heart, and to theirs, who profeſſe to <hi>feare</hi> GOD, yet walk ſo notoriouſly contrary to what they doe profeſſe.</p>
                  <p>We alſo, who, not perhaps ſo notoriouſly wicked, yet are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to this <hi>HOLY AFFECTION,</hi> (profeſſing wee <hi>feare</hi> GOD, when indeed it is not ſo) we doe not feare Him in <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer,</hi> which appeares thus: When danger preſents its ſelfe, where are we then? Almoſt dead with feare, which could not be, if we feared GOD in <hi>Power.</hi> When trouble ſhews it ſelfe, we ſhake at it as at ſome new and ſtrange thing, never looked for, nor feared till it come: And theſe ſhaking fits declare, That we, whatſoever we ſay and pretend, do not <hi>feare</hi> GOD: <hi>feare</hi> will
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:111850:29"/> not be concealed no more then folly can; when <hi>he that is affraid,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 10. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>walketh by the way, his wiſdom faileth him, and he ſaith to every one he is affraid:</hi> And he can give a Reaſon for his feare, which is this, That hell is let looſe now, and Divels are broke-in amongſt us, in the ſhape and likeneſſe of men. Grant it to be ſo, as ſo it is, yet the Righteous he that feareth God in Power) feareth not, (that is) he is notvoid of feare, but he is above his feare, he is as bold as a Lion, for he <hi>feareth</hi> GOD; how? <hi>As God:</hi> That cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es and quieteth his ſpirit: we do not as the Righteous do, maintaine the feare of <hi>God;</hi> Set up <hi>God</hi> ruling as chiefe over all. Certaine it is They that feare <hi>God</hi> indeed <hi>as</hi> GOD do ſo: do ſet Him up in their hearts, and ſo ruling in the world. They that feare the Creature, do ſet the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture above <hi>God:</hi> they make <hi>God</hi> the Vial, and Man the pourer forth of the wrath: whereas it is cleane contrary. And, Oh! the torment they feele within (if their hearts be not as <hi>Nabals</hi> was, like a ſtone) when terrours is round about! They ſhewed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>gods</hi> againſt GOD: and row they ſhew themſelves ſlaves towards men, whoſe bodies and conſciences are alike rotten. <hi>Who art thou that thou art afraid of a man?</hi> 
                     <note n="(g)" place="margin">Eſai. 51. 12.</note> Reade and reſolve that Queſtion. He that forgetteth The LORD his Maker, makes no more account of <hi>Him,</hi> then of a meer man, nor ſo much neither, though He ſtretched forth the Heavens, and laid the foundations of the Earth: and makes a meere man a <hi>God,</hi> heightens that low and <hi>diminutive</hi> thing (for, in Compariſon, he is a very ſmall thing, very little more then nothing, not ſo big as a drop of water, or the ſmall duſt of the Ballance) <note n="(h)" place="margin">Eſay. 40. 15.</note> 
                     <hi>that ſhall dye, and be made as graſſe;</hi> A goodly thing, if we obſerve it well, to make our object, to ſet our feare upon. O wonderfull Ignorance of our ſelves, and of <hi>God!</hi> Ai, It is want of knowledge, therefore we ſet our feare upon periſhing things, and we periſh with them. Truely upon due conſideration, <hi>who</hi> would not <hi>feare Thee</hi> O Lord? He hath ſaid ten times, <hi>feare not;</hi> 
                     <note n="(i)" place="margin">Eſai. 41. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>I am thy God: I am with thee, I will up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thee, &amp;c. I am God,</hi> and <hi>Thy God,</hi> It is enough. He created the <hi>Smith</hi> 
                     <note n="(k)" place="margin">Eſai. 54. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> that blowes the coale. He is The <hi>Lord Generall</hi> of all the forces of Heaven, Earth, and Sea; Maſter of the <hi>Armoryes:</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Jer. 50. 25.</note> There is not a Sword, not an inſtrument there, but it is for His Work, He gives it forth, ſtamps His Commiſſion upon it, <hi>Go ſo far, do this, and no more; not an inch farther, not to the loſſe of a haire</hi>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:111850:29"/> 
                     <hi>more;</hi> no marvaile, The Righteous are as bold as a Lion, they fear nothing, for they feare GOD: They <hi>Sanctify the Lord of</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Eſay 8. 13.</note> 
                     <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>s Himſelfe.</hi> What then? Then He will <hi>be a Sanctuary,</hi> The Righteous know it, they are aſſured of it, and it is enough to qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tand calme the ſpirit, when the Earth is moved, and the <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ry.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This will ſeeme ſtrange, which follows, THE RIGHTE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OUS ARE NEVER SO SAFE AND SECURE AS IN AN EARTHQUAKE. And yet, why ſhould it ſeeme ſtrange? It is demonſtrated and made evident to ſenſe and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. In a ſhaking Time, when the Kingdoms are moved; Nay in that time, which is not yet come, but haſting and coming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pace, when there will be <hi>a great earth-quake, ſuch as was not</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Revel. 16. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n were upon the earth, ſo mighty an earthquake and ſo great,</hi> The Righteous then will cling the faſter to The Arme of The Almighty, (there is ſecurity you will ſay) And then, at ſuch a time as that, The Arme of the Almighty holds them the faſter: We parents doe ſo; If my childe be in danger, If my childe ſhake, I will hold it faſt, if I can, perhaps I cannot, It is not f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r want of love, but for want of ſtrength: GOD can hold them faſt, for none can take His children out of His Hands, There is no want in Him, neither of <hi>Love</hi> nor <hi>Power,</hi> Therefore it follows, clee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſenſe and reaſon both, <hi>That when the Kingdome is moved, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>en it totters like a drunken man,</hi> nay, when that <hi>Earth-quake</hi> ſhallbe, then the Righteous ſhall ſtand moſt ſtedfaſt, ſecure, and ſteady, even then when that Earth-quake ſhall be, ſo mighty an Earth-quake and ſo great, never ſo ſecure as then, then they ſhall lift up the head, for then they hold faſt by Gods Arme, and they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inde by good experience, that he holds them faſt.</p>
                  <p>I <hi>feare</hi> GOD, ſaid <hi>Ioſeph</hi> 
                     <note n="(a)" place="margin">Gen. 42. 28.</note> I am an Hebrew ſaid <hi>Ionah</hi> 
                     <note n="(b)" place="margin">Jonah. 1. 8.</note> and <hi>I feare The Lord God of Heaven, Who hath made the Sea and the dry land.</hi> This put in ſecurity for them both, That, though they might be overcome through infirmities, yet willingly they would doe no wrong. But that is not the point we are now upon, This is it, which is cleere from hence, That the true feare of <hi>God</hi> ſecureth the ſervants of The <hi>Lord,</hi> againſt the wrong and injurious dealing from man. Man (for his mercies are cruell)
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:111850:30"/> will doe the faithfull what wrong he can, but he cannot hurt them, nor are they carefull concerning that.</p>
                  <p>I remember a ſhort Anſwer from a true ſervant of GOD to an over-hearing and tyrannicall <hi>Lord, Am not I your head and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander?</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> The need hath an Head; All things ſhal be don<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l have it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>u n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand as God will have it. <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſt.</hi>
                     </note> Yes ſaid the faithfull ſervant, but your <hi>headſhip</hi> hath an <hi>Hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> That is over you and me both, I FEARE HIM. Cannot I thruſt thee into priſon? Yes, if <hi>God</hi> will give you leave, and I FEARE HIM: And if He permits you ſo to doe, yet His <hi>Word</hi> is not bound, nor can His influence be reſtrained any more then can the influence from the Sunne. <hi>I feare</hi> GOD, ſaid he: and this was all the anſwer this domineering Lord could get from this good man: For he profeſſed, That no <hi>mans terrour</hi> could make him afraid: The terrour of The LORD, that could doe it; none could daunt his ſpirit, but He, Who could caſt bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoule both into hell. Him indeed he feared with all his heart, his CREATOR, therefore he could not feare his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. We have here our leſſon, if we do thereafter, we may reade our comfort, <hi>Be not afraid of their terrour, neither be troubled,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 3. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>but ſanctifie, &amp;c.</hi> We have proceeded in our <hi>Cure</hi> thus farre; Expectation of evill from the world, and of good from a Good <hi>God,</hi> works a great <hi>Cure</hi> of <hi>Feare:</hi> Love to Him, feare of Him, is very ſoveraigne alſo. We proceed now to <hi>Truſt</hi> in <hi>God,</hi> and that is ſoveraigne indeed: it eſtabliſheth, it fortifies a man migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, it makes a man ſtand like Mount Sion, he cannot be moved, for he ſtands better bottomed then are The everlaſting hills or <note place="margin">Hab. 3. 6.</note> perpetuall mountains.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:111850:30"/>
                  <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Righteous are faithfull, they truſt God: He never deceives them, that truſt in Him: They commit all to Him, ſecured in His faithfulneſſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>THe Righteous, they <hi>Truſt</hi> GOD, and They know Whom they have truſted, To whom they have committed their lives, liberties, and eſtates, their children, all they have; and they know He is faithfull and true, and now they are feareleſſe, now they heare of robbing, and ſpoiling, and pillaging; nay, though it come home to their own houſes, they can ſuffer the ſpoiling of their goods with joy: They <hi>Truſt God,</hi> He is their Guardian, they are not carefull, they are, as was ſaid, <hi>feareleſſe.</hi> Maſter <hi>Dearing</hi> hath <q>an excellent Speech, indeed he was an excellent man; Commit your health, your ſickneſſe, your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, <note place="margin">Lett. 13.</note> your Soul, your life, and your death to the protection of Him, That dyed for us, and is riſen againe: A ſick body (let me ſay with reference to the preſent, a perſon, an houſe marked out by the ſpoilers) with ſuch an <hi>aid,</hi> hath a greater treaſure then the Queens Iewell-houſe.</q> It hath indeed, a greater treaſure then hath the Kings Iewell-houſe. That houſe may be emptied of the treaſure there: He may make an hole in all our Ciſterns, and let-out all our comforts. All ſuccours from earth may fail, nay the heart, and that is the ſtrongeſt Fort, may faile, but <hi>God</hi> never failes. <hi>Truſt in the Lord for ever.</hi> Why for ever? There <note place="margin">Eſay 26. 4.</note> is a mighty reaſon or ground for everlaſting Truſt, becauſe in <hi>The</hi> LORD JEHOVAH <hi>is</hi> EVERLASTING STRENGTH. <note place="margin">Pſal. 23. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>I will feare no evill,</hi> ſaith <hi>David.</hi> A very bold and confident ſpeech. <hi>Feare no evill!</hi> He might ſit in darkneſſe, walk in the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of death, the rod might be ſore upon his back, much evill might be towards him, and much might be upon him, and yet <hi>feare no evill?</hi> No, for what-ever befell him, it was The <hi>Lord,</hi> from His hand, His rod, and where-ever he ſate, and whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he walkt, <hi>God</hi> was with him, <hi>Thou art with me, Thy rod and Thy ſtaffe, they comfort me.</hi> WHAT TIME I AM AFRAID, <note place="margin">Pſal. 56. 3.</note>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:111850:31"/> I WILL TRUST IN THEE. Ai, it was a point of great diſcretion, To truſt in The <hi>Lord.</hi> Truly <hi>in vaine is ſalvation ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>er 3. 23.</note> 
                     <hi>for from the hils, and from the multitude of mountaines: Truly in The</hi> LORD <hi>our</hi> GOD <hi>is the ſalvation of Iſrael.</hi> Then truly, ſaith the Godly man, <hi>When I am afraid,</hi> when I ſee all things out of courſe, I will <hi>truſt</hi> IN <hi>The Lord;</hi> He will doe all things well, and all thoſe contrarieties of wills, and workings, ſhall work together for the good of all them that Truſt in Him, (whereof anon.) Therefore I will truſt in The <hi>Lord</hi> for ever: I will commit life and livelihood all to Him, A faithfull Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, and I know Him to be ſo. <hi>When I am afraid, I will truſt in Thee.</hi> So the godly man hath made his concluſion, thereon he reſteth his ſoule, and is confident, as bold as a Lion, for he doth <hi>Truſt</hi> in <hi>The Lord. I will ſay of The</hi> LORD, HE IS MY <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>l <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>1. 2.</note> REFUGE, <hi>and my</hi> FORTRESSE, MY GOD, <hi>in Him will I truſt.</hi> Will he ſo? Is the good man reſolved upon it, That he will truſt in GOD? Yes, that is plaine in the Text. Now mark, <hi>God</hi> will not deceive this Truſt. Indeed an honeſt man will not, he will not deceive me, if I truſt in him; much leſſe will GOD doe it, a faithfull Creator. Now The <hi>Lord</hi> will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver <hi>this man,</hi> how often? as often as he falls into the ſtraits. <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ob. 5. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>In ſixe troubles, yea in ſeven there ſhall no evill come unto him:</hi> (That is) Neither devils, nor men, neither their counſels, nor their ſtrength, neither ſword, nor peſtilence, nor devouring beaſts, ſhall be able to doe this man any hurt. If the devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring peſtilence, if the <hi>oppreſſing</hi> ſword, if famine, if wild beaſts, <note place="margin">Jer. 46. 16.</note> (thoſe foure ſore judgements) come into the Land, (a noble Scholler calls theſe plagues, the <hi>great winding ſheets of the world)</hi> theſe ſhall doe this man no <hi>hurt.</hi> Obſerve what you reade, The <hi>terrors by night</hi> ſhall not affray this man, nor the <hi>arrow</hi> by day, nor the <hi>peſtilence that walketh in darkneſſe,</hi> nor the <hi>deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſal 91.</note> 
                     <hi>that waſteth at noon day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>True, you will ſay, none of all this ſhall hurt this man, for all this is more immediately the <hi>Sword of the Lord</hi> 
                     <note n="(a)" place="margin">1 Chron. 21. 12.</note> the very <hi>Hand</hi> of <hi>God:</hi> 
                     <note n="(b)" place="margin">ver. 13.</note> and The <hi>Lord</hi> will order it ſo, That His <hi>Sword</hi> ſhall not ſlay this man; His <hi>Hand</hi> ſhall not hurt him. But this man muſt looke that the <hi>ſword</hi> of the enemies will overtake him; he muſt looke to fight with men after the manner of Beaſts, they
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:111850:31"/> will hurt him ſure, for they are Adverſaries, and for their might and cruelty called <hi>Lyons,</hi> and <hi>Adders,</hi> and <hi>Dragons,</hi> theſe will hurt this man ſure enough.</p>
                  <p>No, all theſe, with all their might and malice too, ſhall not <hi>hurt</hi> this man: But he ſhall <hi>hurt</hi> them, he ſhall wound them in the <hi>head,</hi> which is the ſeate of life; <hi>He ſhall tread upon the Lion</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l 91. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>and the Adder, the young Lyon and the Dragon ſhalt thou</hi> TRAM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PLE <hi>under foot.</hi> And why ſhall this man be ſo delivered, and be ſo victorious? That is worth the enquiring unto; it is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered; Becauſe this man made <hi>The</hi> LORD <hi>his refuge,</hi> even the moſt HIGH <hi>his habitation: Therefore ſhall no evill befall</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">ver. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>him;</hi> becauſe this man hath <hi>ſet</hi> his LOVE, his <hi>Heart,</hi> his <hi>Delight,</hi> his <hi>Hope,</hi> his <hi>Truſt,</hi> he hath ſet <hi>All</hi> upon GOD, Therefore <hi>God</hi> will deliver him: This man hath <hi>ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ed</hi> GOD above all <hi>gods;</hi> He hath ſet Him <hi>on high,</hi> he hath <hi>knowne His Name,</hi> (that is) hee hath truſted in <hi>Him;</hi> Therefore will The <hi>Lord</hi> ſet this man on <hi>high;</hi> he ſhall ride upon the high places of the earth, over the heads of his Adverſaries, <hi>Becauſe he hath knowne My Name.</hi> O Bleſſed man, and in a bleſſed condition! for he had covered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with the Armes of the Almighty, and under that ſhelter he doth truſt. What then? It follows; <hi>His Truth ſhall be Thy Shield and Buckler.</hi> A weake and fooliſh Queſtion will thruſt in here, I will quickly reſolve it.</p>
                  <p>May we not truſt in the creature? in meanes, they may be faire <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                     </label> and likely; In inſtruments, theſe are honourable and ſpecious; may we not truſt in theſe?</p>
                  <p>No, Be theſe inſtruments or meanes never ſo excellent and <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                     </label> glorious, yet they are but fleſh, we muſt not truſt in them. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> from the beginning of time to this Day, proſper that put his <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>uſt in meanes, in inſtruments. <hi>Some truſt in cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> in horſes.</hi> 
                     <note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſal. 20. 7.</note> And what of them? how ſpeede they? They are <hi>brought downe and faden.</hi> 
                     <note n="(v)" place="margin">ver. 8.</note> nay, there is a curſe upon the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat truſt in man, and make <hi>fleſh</hi> their <hi>Arme.</hi> 
                     <note n="(d)" place="margin">Jer. 17. 5.</note> And this cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e muſt neede<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vertake them, <hi>For their heart de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth from the</hi> LORD: Then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o reſolve the queſtion, we may eſteeme honourably of the inſtruments, but wee muſt ſet GOD above them; We muſt ſet Him on high, as we read before; we muſt praiſe GOD for them; we muſt not <hi>Idolize</hi> them: we
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:111850:32"/> muſt uſe the meanes; we muſt not truſt in them: we muſt give the inſtrument his due praiſe, but all the <hi>glory to</hi> GOD. There is another Queſtion more worthie the reſolving.</p>
                  <p>It is commonly ſaid by every man, I doe <hi>truſt in</hi> GOD. But wilt thou know, O man, whether thou doeſt as thou ſayeſt? Try thy ſelfe by this, and deale truly with thy owne ſoule. Where art thou when the LORD takes away the <hi>ſtay</hi> and the <hi>ſtaffe,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Eſay 3. 1.</note> the whole <hi>ſtay</hi> of <hi>bread,</hi> and <hi>the</hi> whole <hi>ſtay</hi> of <hi>water</hi> (that is) every thing, that thy ſoule tooke delight in, being but <hi>fleſh,</hi> where art thou then? upon the ground, a dejected man, thy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is quite fallen; why then aſſure thy ſelfe, thou didſt make <hi>fleſh</hi> thy foote and thy arme too, thereon thou didſt truſt, and not on GOD: <hi>Fleſh</hi> upheld thee, and not <hi>ſpirit:</hi> hadſt thou truſted in GOD, He had upheld thee now, never more firmely then when the <hi>ſtay</hi> and <hi>ſtaffe</hi> of the creature is taken away: Then The <hi>Arme</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> upholds moſt gloriouſly, when it ſuſtaines alone, made bare of fleſh. I know ſome ſuddain diſaſter, ſome unexpected breach (yet nothing is ſuddain or unexpected to a faithfull man) may make his confidence quaile, and his ſpirit fall: but if he fall flat, and there lye with his face upon the ground, and upon ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conſiderations, cannot raiſe himſelfe and get up his ſpirit, then certain it is, The creature was his ſtay and confidence. I meane thus, If when the ſtay and ſtaffe is taken away, the heart fainteth away and dyes. If the ſpirits be ſunke then, they will not up again, then certain it is, That <hi>ſtay</hi> and <hi>ſtaffe,</hi> be it the <hi>wedge</hi> of gold, <hi>husband, wife,</hi> or <hi>childe,</hi> that was the prop that ſtayed the heart up: but now theſe <hi>bearers,</hi> theſe <hi>ſupporters</hi> are taken away, the perſon is down, his ſpirit flat and ſunke.</p>
                  <p>But thou maiſt ſay, Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u waſt never put to that ſtrait yet; God never yet tooke from thee the <hi>ſtay</hi> and <hi>ſtaffe.</hi> Say, Bleſſed be His Name. And yet doe not <hi>truſt</hi> to this <hi>truſt,</hi> doe not bee confident of this ſtrength. It is not tryed yet as gold in the Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace. That which holds thee up now, may not be ſufficient in the day of Trouble. Thou thinkeſt now, That Thou doeſt truſt in <hi>God,</hi> and He upholds thy Spirit, whereas perhaps the creature is thy ſtay and thy ſtaffe; Examine the truth of this betimes, and take all advantage of experiences from what GOD hath done, and from promiſes what He will doe, and all to make improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:111850:32"/> of this <hi>Truſt in God.</hi> Till our ſtrength be tryed, till we have ſome experience, we cannot tell how great the rebellion of the fleſh will be under <hi>Gods</hi> afflicting hand. It is an eaſie thing to be valiant before the combat, to dreame of a good courage before the heart be tryed,: but indeed To bee unſhaken in the mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt of a tempeſt; and To ſtand upright, when the ground under us doth tremble, This is to know aſſuredly That we are ſtrong in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, That we have boldneſſe and can truſt <hi>perfectly.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Surely never was there more cauſe then at this time, To <hi>ſet</hi> our <hi>hope</hi> in GOD, To make good our confidence, To exerciſe this grace of <hi>ſaith</hi> and <hi>truſt,</hi> To looke back to what <hi>God</hi> hath done, how wonderfull He hath wrought for thoſe that put their truſt in Him: And ſo to gather experience, that is a great meanes to ſupport the heart, and to engage it to truſt in <hi>God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I remember a paſſage, which ſurely is worth the noting, this it is. <hi>David</hi> comes haſtily to <hi>Abimeleck,</hi> and after ſome gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, <note place="margin">2 Sam. 21.</note> and ſome other paſſages betwixt them, demands of the Prieſt, <hi>Whether he could help him to a ſword?</hi> Yes, ſaid the Prieſt, here is in my keeping <hi>The ſword of Goliah the Philiſtine, whom</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">verſe 9.</note> THOU SLEWEST: If thou wilt take that, take it, for here is no other. No other, thought <hi>David,</hi> (for ſo he ſaid) if thou hadſt all the ſwords in the world, yet there is none LIKE THAT, <hi>give it me.</hi> And why ſo? There were other <hi>Giants</hi> in the world, and other <hi>ſwords</hi> as great as that, why <hi>none like that?</hi> The Text reſolves it, That was the ſword where with <hi>David</hi> ſlew <hi>Goliah</hi> the Philiſtine. <hi>None like that</hi> ſword, That revived <hi>Davids</hi> ſpirits (indeed they were fainting) with the ſenſe of experience of GODS faithfulneſſe: He had wrought wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully for <hi>David,</hi> a weakling, and yet He gave him ſtrength to ſlay the Giant with his owne ſword; none <hi>like that;</hi> a double weapon with a double edge, it had ſlaine behind him, it would ſlay before him: <hi>God</hi> had delivered him from <hi>ſuch a death,</hi> and there was the ſword now in his hand, a memoriall of <hi>ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance,</hi> He would put his Truſt in GOD for after-time. This is the Poynt then we are engaged upon, even To put our Truſt in GOD: and, that we may do ſo, To Conſider well what <hi>God</hi> hath done, and then To exerciſe our <hi>faith</hi> upon it, for the better improvement of our <hi>Truſt in Him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:111850:33"/>
                  <p> Surely the very ſet time is now come, That ſo we ſhould doe, improve our <hi>Truſt</hi> in GOD, <hi>live by faith now,</hi> (that is) live upon <hi>God,</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> in <hi>God,</hi> to <hi>God;</hi> to make up a life in Him alone. Therein is aſſurance, and ſtrength, <hi>ſtrong confidence:</hi> 
                     <note n="(a)" place="margin">Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> And <hi>The</hi> LORD <hi>will reject all other confidences,</hi> 
                     <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>2. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> ſo as <hi>man ſhall not be held up by them, nor proſper in them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You will ſay, you muſt have FAITH firſt before you can <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                     </label> exerciſe it and live upon it.</p>
                  <p>True, and before you have it, you ſhall know how you got it. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                     </label> It is an <hi>admirable</hi> grace, and wrought by the <hi>operation, (c)</hi> effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall <note n="(c)" place="margin">Col<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſ 2. 12. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> working of <hi>God,</hi> (the great Worke of <hi>God)</hi> but we muſt worke too, uſe all diligence, and all the meanes <hi>God</hi> hath ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified for the getting of the ſame; uſe the means faithfully, and you ſhall get the Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſure, a Treaſure indeed, ſuch as we heard. A man may live upon it, if he have nothing elſe. <hi>Cry after this grace, life up thy voice for it, as for hid treaſure,</hi> (it is the gift of <hi>God)</hi> but ſo it muſt be ſought for, or it will never be had; it is the principall thing, with all thy getting, get <hi>faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You will ſay, There is need of <hi>Patience</hi> too. Yes, and that it hath a perfect work to calm, quiet, and ſilence the reaſoning of our ſpirits. There is no poſſeſſing of a mans ſoule without <hi>pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> ſpecially now in ſuch a <hi>perilous,</hi> and <hi>exceeding (e) feirce time</hi> as this is, now the Divell is looſe, and rageth amongſt us; <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> Mat. 8. 28.</note> great need of <hi>Patience.</hi> Yet, I ſay, we ſtand in more need of <hi>faith,</hi> for there is no grace like that at this time. <hi>Thou ſhalt forgive Thy Brother ſeven and ſeven times, ſaith the</hi> LORD CHRIST. <note place="margin">Luke 17. 4.</note> We would think this would follow now, LORD ENCREASE OUR LOVE; let that have a perfect work, that we may forgive an offender even ſo often; But the Apoſtles ſaid, <hi>Lord increaſe our faith:</hi> Yes, That is the mother grace, get that, ſtrengthen that, all is done. Shee is a mother in Iſrael, never alone, but honourably accompanied ſtill with her children, <hi>Patience, Meckeneſſe, Love, Hope, Ioy,</hi> all theſe. Would I then reſt quietly in a ſtormy night, when the winds blow, the raine and haile beat upon my houſe; would I be ſecure when terrour is round about; would I ſtand ſtill, unmoveable in an <hi>earth-quake?</hi> Then I muſt ſay when I cloſe mine eyes, and when I awaken, <hi>Lord encreaſe my faith.</hi> You have need of <hi>faith;</hi> It is impoſſible to do or ſuffer any thing
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:111850:33"/> without it, but, by it, All things are done and ſuffered, that we thinke impoſſible and moſt terrible: but nothing is impoſſible to <hi>faith:</hi> Therefore we muſt cry after this grace, and lift up <note place="margin">Prov. 3. 22.</note> our prayer for it; it is life <hi>unto the ſoule, and grace to the neck:</hi> Thereby we walk in our way ſafely, and at the end, we lye downe, and are not afraid: for <hi>faith</hi> makes The LORD our <hi>confidence,</hi> and therefore we will ſay evermore, <hi>Lord encreaſe our faith,</hi> it is the onely neceſſary thing: For, <note place="margin">Job 18. 14.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, it purifieth the heart, it <hi>ſubdues iniquity,</hi> it overcomes the world, nay it gives you victory over the King of terrors: I doe not meane <hi>Death,</hi> though that is a moſt terrible King, but <hi>Sin,</hi> which is the ſtrength and ſting of death, which makes a man ſeek for death as for hid treaſure, that he might be rid of thoſe thoughts of eternity, which is are the poiſon of vipers, and <hi>gall</hi> of Aſps. It ſets an edge upon our feares and our ſorrows. This evill, a pure evill, <hi>Faith</hi> ſubdueth and maſtereth through <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in the <hi>power of His might,</hi> and ſo we are made more <hi>then Conquerours,</hi> by laying hold-faſt on Him, The Rock of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Faith bottomes the heart upon GOD, which was ſaid before, and Faith encourageth the heart to duty (which follows) To live to <hi>God,</hi> To improve all we have and are To His <hi>Glory;</hi> ſo aſſureth the perſon, as He walks before Him here now, ſo he ſhall live in Glory for ever with The <hi>Lord.</hi> Faith then is the principall thing, that excellent, that admiring grace, get that, and we have all things compleatly fitted both to do or to ſuffer as good ſouldiers of Jeſus Chriſt. I will ſhut up this with the words wherewith the righteous have concluded their <note place="margin">Pſal. 33. 21, 22</note> Pſalme, and cloſed up their hearts againſt feare, <hi>Our heart ſhall rejoyce in Him: becauſe we have truſted in His holy Name. Let thy mercy, O</hi> Lord, <hi>be upon us, according as we hope in thee.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:111850:34"/>
                  <head>CHAP. V.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Righteous obey from the heart: True ſound and ſincere obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is never found but in keeping to</hi> Gods <hi>Work, and in His way: They meet with Lions and Bears there, but they have a ſafeguard over them, and are not afraid: They are ſure they are in their way, and upon Duty, which muſt be done, and the work proſper and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe with the increaſe of</hi> God: <hi>And all this in the fitteſt time, when the Adverſary ſhall be moſt confounded, and</hi> God <hi>moſt glorified.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>THe Righteous <hi>obey</hi> from <hi>the</hi> 
                     <note n="(a)" place="margin">Rom. 6. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>heart.</hi> An hearty obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that is obedience indeed, and it is ever found in GODS <hi>way</hi> and Work. Such an obedience then, a walking in GODS <hi>way,</hi> an engaging the heart to GODS <hi>worke,</hi> is a ſoveraigne meanes To quiet and calme the ſpirit, when here is trouble on every ſide. For thus The righteous man reaſoneth; Some Lion, ſome <hi>Eſau,</hi> ſome fierce Adverſary, ſome great trouble or croſſe may meet me in my way: Yes, but I am in GODS way, I am doing my duty, let GOD alone for the reſt; He will work for my comfort. As the valiant Romane ſaid (I allude to it) when it was told him, That the enemie would be upon his back quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>go autem Sacrifico.</note> 
                     <hi>Let him come,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>I will keep to my ſervice, I will do my duty</hi> for all that. I would rather inſtance in <hi>Nehemiah;</hi> he ſaw and heard enough to have daunted any mans ſpirit, that was not <hi>ſuch a man as himſelfe,</hi> That had not <hi>another ſpirit,</hi> and could ſet his <hi>face like a flint:</hi> And yet he was not <hi>carefull,</hi> he was not <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid,</hi> ſhould ſuch a man as he feare, imployed in GODS <hi>worke,</hi> and in His <hi>way?</hi> Should he fly? No not he. Let the adverſary rage, and roare, and ſend, and write, and flatter, and lye, and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and blaſpheme, (the adverſaries did all this, and more) yet he would to his <hi>worke,</hi> and abide by it, for he was upon Temple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work, a ſworne Man to doe his <hi>Lord</hi> ſervice; And this <hi>Lord</hi> hath ſworne to protect that man. Truly it is ſo. Let a Lion, a ſhe-beare, or the devill meet ſuch a perſon, croſſe him in the way, he need not be carefull nor afraid, being groundedly reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:111850:34"/> of this, I am in <hi>Gods</hi> way, upon His worke. O let me be ſtil found <hi>ſo doing.</hi> What? GODS work, and in His way, a mighty comfort this. It is as a Cordiall to the heart, when we ſuffer from the hand there; That there and then we have done our duty, <hi>Gods work</hi> in <hi>Gods way,</hi> ſo <hi>obeying from the heart.</hi> The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels are a ſafeguard about us; They beare us up: what would we have more for our ſecurity? The caſe is evident, it is an excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding comfort, a marvailous eſtabliſhment to a man ſurrounded<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <q>with terrors,</q> That he is in GODS <hi>way,</hi> upon His <hi>worke.</hi> It is a Soveraigne Cordiall now in theſe perilous and exceeding feirce times; It ſtayes and chears the heart, and ſilenceth the reaſoning of the Spirit. What? That I am in <hi>Gods</hi> way, and upon His work; <hi>the heart may meditate terrour now, when the Nations are angry,</hi> &amp; <note place="margin">Eſa. 33. 18.</note> the Kingdom totters like a drunken man. We will conſider with all our hearts the caſe that <hi>Nehemiah</hi> was in, and his courage, for it is very notable; his caſe is the caſe of our Worthies, even of all that are able to ſtand in the gap for the help of the Church: And this time runs parallel with that then, after the very ſame <hi>Line:</hi> Therefore we will heare what <hi>Nehemiah</hi> ſayes, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the caſe about him. What ſayes he? <hi>Should ſuch a man as I flee?</hi> And <hi>Who is there, that being as I am, would goe into the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Neh. 6. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>to ſave his life?</hi> A very bold ſpeech; I pray you, ſince it is not too late, and it may be of much uſe now, let us examine this mans confidence.</p>
                  <p>Why might not ſuch a man as hee flee? what manner of man was he? A faithfull man; one that feared <hi>God above many:</hi> There is the Anſwer for that. A faithfull man cannot be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; a man full of faith cannot be full of feare: BEING AS I AM; In what a caſe was <hi>Nehemiah</hi> in then? In a very ſad and perplexed caſe ſure; All the reaſon he had, if hee had no more then we have, could not tell him, which way to take; for he had heard no leſſe then <hi>ten times,</hi> That from all places the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary would be upon him: <note n="(c)" place="margin">Nehe. 4. 12.</note> And when The Lord brought that counſail to nought, they fell upon another, (The devils mint <note place="margin">* <hi>Fabricator.</hi> Prov. 6. 14.</note> is ſtill going, his ſervants are ſtill hammering there) <hi>The Ad-Adverſary ſent to Nehemiah no leſſe then</hi> FOURE TIMES to procure a brotherly conference about an an <hi>Accommodation</hi> forſooth (but <hi>they thought to doe him</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Chap 6. 2. 3. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>miſchiefe)</hi> And when <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah</hi>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:111850:35"/> returned the Adverſary ſtill the ſame Anſwer, <hi>Foure times together,</hi> I AM DOING A GREAT WORKE WHICH MUST NOT CEASE, <hi>while I come downe to you to Parley</hi> about an <hi>Accommodation,</hi> (which was never in the adverſaries thoughts, for they THOUGHT <hi>to doe him</hi> MISCHIEFE:) Then the Adverſary ſent his ſervant the <hi>fift time,</hi> with an open <note place="margin">ver. 5.</note> letter in his hand, and a loud lye, a Blaſphemie rather, in his mouth, which was as we finde it written: <hi>(a)</hi> And all this to <note place="margin">ver. 6, 7.</note> make the <hi>Builders afraid, and the worke to ceaſe;</hi> which prevailed ſo far with <hi>Shemajah,</hi> (I will mention no more of the falſe bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren;) <note place="margin">ver. 10</note> That he pent himſelfe up (like a wiſe man, who was reſolved to ſave one) in a place, which had gates, <hi>Doores, and Barres</hi> (which the City had not at that time:) and he perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Nehemiah</hi> ſo to doe alſo (by a <hi>Spirit,</hi> as he ſaid, of <hi>Revelation)</hi> To ſlinke aſide from the worke, letting that ceaſe till the brunt of oppoſition were over, and in the meane time provide for his life, <hi>Let us meete together in the houſe of</hi> GOD <hi>within the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and let us ſhut the doores of the Temple, for they will come to</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">ver. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>ſlay thee. And Nehemiah ſaid,</hi> No <hi>man, being as I am, would goe into the Temple to ſave his life, I will not goe in.</hi> No truly, <hi>being as</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">ver. 11</note> 
                     <hi>I am</hi> I will truſt to an open place, that hath neither Walls nor Bulwarks; I am doing my duty; upon my Maſters worke; in His way, I am doing a great worke, which muſt not reſt, It is not neceſſary that I muſt live (though I know <hi>my times</hi> are (my life is) in my GODS hands, not at the diſpoſe of the Adverſary) but the worke muſt be done, that is neceſſary at this time: <hi>Being as I am</hi> upon This worke, and in This <hi>way,</hi> I will not goe into the Temple to ſave my life, not I. <hi>Should ſuch a man as I flee?</hi> and <hi>being as I am?</hi> No, I Will doe my <hi>Worke,</hi> my <hi>Duty,</hi> I will walke in the way boldly (wherein never man miſcarried yet) and for my poore life (well hazarded in ſuch a worke and ſuch a way) and all my concernements about it; all theſe I have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into His hands, Who is as a ſtrong City; <hi>Salvation</hi> will <note place="margin">Eſay 26. 1.</note> GOD appoint for <hi>walls</hi> and <hi>Bulwarke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is an end of that diſpute, That I am in <hi>Gods</hi> way, &amp; upon His work, anſwers all doubts, ſilenceth all gainſayers. A man may be reproached and perſecuted, &amp;c. in this way, but he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be diſtreſſed there, nor forſaken. The experience of all times, &amp;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:111850:35"/> of all the faithfull in all times will give cleare evidence here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
                  <p>The practiſe of <hi>Luther</hi> runs parallel with this of <hi>Nehemiah;</hi> Hell gates opened upon him, when he opened his mouth for <hi>God,</hi> and for His <hi>cauſe,</hi> and to promote His <hi>Glory.</hi> It is notable to reade how <hi>Luther</hi> encouraged <hi>Melanchthon</hi> againſt his <hi>oppreſſing feares,</hi> and himſelfe alſo <hi>in The</hi> LORD: The enemy <hi>lives</hi> ſaid <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanchthon</hi> and is ſtrong: GOD <hi>lives</hi> for ever, anſwered <hi>Luther,</hi> and is <hi>Almighty.</hi> We cannot beare up againſt the tide of ſuch oppoſition, ſaid <hi>Melanchthon,</hi> an excellent man, but his ſpirit was fallen at that time quite: Nor men, nor Devils can hinder now we are in Gods way, and upon His worke, ſaid <hi>Luther;</hi> We carry GOD along with us, His <hi>cauſe</hi> is in our <hi>ſhip,</hi> though the ſtorm riſeth high, yet <hi>God</hi> is above; The floods of ungodlineſſe ſhall not make us afraid: That <hi>God</hi> is with us, (He is with us while we are with Him:) that it is His cauſe we are engaged upon, anſwereth all doubts, ſilenceth the reaſoning of a timerous ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and fortifies it mightily againſt all diſputes and debates from within the ſoule or from without.</p>
                  <p>The great queſtion is now, <hi>will God reſtore Ieruſalem?</hi> ſhall her breaches be made up? ſhall her <hi>wall</hi> be raiſed even now? This is the queſtion, and it is much doubted, and the very beſt have carefull thoughts about it. But ſurely they doe not well to be ſo carefull, neither do they wiſely inquire into the matter. It is true; Jeruſalems <hi>wall</hi> and her breaches there, ſhould take up the <hi>firſt-borne</hi> of our thoughts; but not the <hi>time</hi> when, nor the <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> how theſe breaches ſhall be ſtopped, and the <hi>walls</hi> ſet up. The times and ſeaſons for the accompliſhing hereof, the meanes too, and the manner how, The Father hath <hi>put in</hi> His <hi>own power.</hi> The work goes on a pace; Bleſſed be His Name for all thoſe that have offered themſelves willingly to this worke; I ſay it, goes on with the encreaſe of <hi>God;</hi> and the times are TROUBLOUS, <note n="(d)" place="margin">Dan. 9. 25.</note> which is a good ſigne too. But whether this be the SET time, when GOD will perfect this work, it is not for us to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire; Think we of doing our duty, and upon our COST; It ſhall be done and perfected in GODS <hi>time,</hi> &amp; that is the beſt time: and for the Church, the very <hi>ſeaſon</hi> of Time, and that we may reſolve upon. The LORD is wiſe <hi>in counſell and mighty in worke;</hi> and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:111850:36"/> there the Church reſteth. He may not do all this, this yeer, or the next, or the third year; for This work, Temple-work, the reſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Kingdom of Iſrael, goes on <hi>ſurely,</hi> but <hi>ſlowly;</hi> mighty Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries <hi>ſet</hi> themſelves againſt it, and <hi>decree</hi> againſt it, and will hinder as long as <hi>God</hi> pleaſeth, till His <hi>ſet time</hi> comes. Truly we wonder He hath done ſo much for a people at this time, who have done ſo much againſt Him now and in all times: But Now ſets a mark upon our frowardneſſe, and makes it exceeding ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. And yet His patience is not wearied, though at every dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, and croſſe way, we are at a ſtand. He works gloriouſly every day, and reviveth ſtill his ſervants hopes: And yet He may not make the earth to bring forth <hi>in one day, nor</hi> a Nation to be <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 66. 8.</note> borne <hi>at once;</hi> and what are a few yeares in His account? not ſo much as a few minutes in ours. The earth ſhall bring forth, even to our largeſt expectation, That is certaine; And the manchilde ſhall be borne perfect and compleate, thats out of doubt: per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps not ſo ſoone as we would have it, we are too haſty. It may ſeeme to ſtick even at the birth ſo long, that the Adverſary may lift up his horne with faire hopes, That it will never come forth: But it ſhall come forth in due time (thats <hi>Gods</hi> time, and it is His promiſe) when they that ſee it ſhall the <hi>more rejoyce,</hi> the more their ſorrow and anguiſh was becauſe it ſtuck at the birth ſo long: And <hi>the bones of the Righteous ſhall flouriſh like an Herbe.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">ver. 14.</note> Why like an <hi>Herbe?</hi> Becauſe they were dried like an <hi>hearth</hi> with long expectation: for now <hi>The hand of the Lord ſhalbe known (the more</hi> gloriouſly the longer the ſtop was) <hi>towards his ſervants, and His Indignation towards His enemies;</hi> for <hi>God</hi> hath given His ſervants leave to make this concluſion from His owne words, <q>kind and gratious, He hath brought to the Birth, He will give ſtrength to bring forth (in his appointed time) And there His people ſet up their reſt, doing their Duty, walking in Gods way, and doing His work.</q> And this ſuſtains them in their fainting fitts; quiets and ſettles them in troublous times, They do their duty, They are upon their worke, This I ſay, for it cannot be ſaid too often, is as comfortable to them, and cordiall as this remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance was to the good king, when he heard the ſentence of Death, Behold Lord I have <hi>walked before Thee in Truth and with</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2 Kings. 20. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>a perfect heart, and have done that which is good in Thy ſight.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:111850:36"/>
                  <p> I may not conclude yet, for there is a great difficulty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind; but Let every man, according to his meaſure, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of gifts, and power <hi>God</hi> hath put into his hand, offer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with a willing mind, wholly up to <hi>God</hi> in His way and <hi>work,</hi> ſo doing his Duty, and committing the iſſue and ſucceſſe to <hi>God,</hi> in aſſurance hereof, That The <hi>Lord</hi> does all things well; orders all for the advancing His own <hi>Glory,</hi> and His Churches good: He will, in His own good time, performe His whole work upon <hi>mount Zion,</hi> and on <hi>Ieruſalem, and then He will puniſh the</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Eſai. 10. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>ſtout-hearted, and bring down the Glory of their lookes.</hi> And, in the meane time, for this man, that attends his Duty, minds that wholly; is onely carefull at that point, The <hi>Lord</hi> will guide him with His eye, will uphold him with His hand, ſo as he ſhall not daſh his <hi>foot againſt a ſtone.</hi> Now the difficulty follows, and that will make us daſh and fall too, if we look not to our bottome, and our ſtanding there upon. We ſhall heare now of ſad and grievous things that befell them, which have ſtood to the cauſe of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and done their duty: But bleſſed be <hi>God,</hi> though wee ſhall heare ſuch things, which ſhall make ſome eares tingle, yet we ſhall not heare, That the righteous have forſaken their <hi>way,</hi> or their <hi>duty,</hi> though they have been <hi>ſore broken in the place of dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons,</hi> and <hi>covered with the ſhadow of death:</hi> YET, no not YET ſhall we heare, <hi>That their heart turned back,</hi> nor that <hi>their feet have declined from</hi> THY WAY: No, though all this, which we <note place="margin">
                        <hi>(b)</hi> Pſal. 44. 17. 18. 19.</note> ſhall heare, is or may come upon them, what though? YET they are reſolved, as their Fathers before them, The reſolution of a gracious ſpirit ever, To keep cloſe to GOD, and to <hi>Duty,</hi> To <hi>ſtir <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>p themſelves againſt the hypocrite;</hi> 
                     <note n="(c)" place="margin">Job. 17. 8. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>To hold on their way,</hi> for they have <hi>cleane hands,</hi> and cleane hearts, waſhed white in the bloud of the Lambe. What followes? We need not make it a Queſtion, <hi>They ſhall be ſtronger and ſtronger.</hi> Having now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed this, I come to that, which is ſaid againſt it, to <hi>ſcare</hi> the fearfull-hearted, mentioning onely that firſt, which occaſioneth it; I had ſaid, rather The <hi>Lord</hi> hath ſaid it for me, <hi>He that keeps cloſe with</hi> GOD, <hi>holds on his way, doth his duty, is reſolved at that point, The LORD hath ſworne by His holineſſe, He will uphold this man,</hi> he ſhall not daſh his foot. I will be bold to ſay, This is <hi>good Divinity,</hi> and as comfortable as any you can meet with in
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:111850:37"/> all your readings. Now hearken what is ſaid to <hi>ſcare</hi> the Iſrael of GOD out of it, all His <hi>Antipaſſes</hi> that they may let-in feare, and let goe Duty. The Adverſary ſhall never effect this while hee breathes; with <hi>Gods</hi> help I ſhall be able to beat him with his owne weapons, and fetch comfort, and light, and glory for the righteous, from out of his darkneſſe, and moſt ignominious uſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Gods people, doing their duty, and holding to His way and work.</p>
                  <p>But the fearfull have looked upon all this already, and they object,</p>
                  <p>He that does his duty, keeping to Gods way and worke, may <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                     </label> daſh his foote and fall too, and riſe no more in this world, if he be reſolute upon that way, and to doe his duty therein; as like to daſh upon danger and to be ſwallowed up of it too, in no way more likely then in GODS way, and when we doe our Duty. Take we for example the Patirarchs, Prophets, Apoſtles, that <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.</note> cloude of witneſſes in the little booke of Martyrs, they walked in <hi>Gods</hi> way and did their <hi>Duty,</hi> and did they not daſh upon danger? To come neerer to our own times. Looke upon thoſe TWO WITNESSES, thoſe few <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Vocatur</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipas <hi>non ficto ſed vero nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne: tot pene lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris &amp; ſyllabis Martyres hujus temporis decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat fore</hi> Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>papas. Revel. 2. 13.</note> 
                     <hi>Antipaſſes,</hi> faithful Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates; and faithfull, Miniſters, and faithfull people, oppoſing, in all ages of the world, upward to this day, and ſo will all their Dayes, <hi>Roome</hi> and their abominable Idolatries, and then you will ſay they doe their Duty and are in <hi>Gods way;</hi> But ſee I pray you, and marke well how they are uſed, you would not uſe a Dog ſo; And ſee where they lye, A goodly recompence for doing their <hi>Duty,</hi> and walking in <hi>Gods</hi> way, will the world ſay.</p>
                  <p>No matter what the world ſaies, not a pin matter, nor how they <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> uſe the ſervants of <hi>God:</hi> They are <hi>vile</hi> and <hi>refuſe</hi> with the world, becauſe they doe their Duty, and are the excellent there, not <hi>of the world:</hi> A ſure Teſtimony of perdition to the world of ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men, whoſe <hi>ſuperſtitions</hi> may be out of <hi>ignorance,</hi> but their <hi>cruelty</hi> is out of <hi>malice.</hi> But to the point. It is granted, That if ever the Devil, (that Legion, for I mean with him, all his ſervants) ſtand with open mouth and out-ſtretched arme againſt a man; it is then, when he walks in GODS <hi>way,</hi> and doth his <hi>Duty.</hi> The wicked are carryed with an indignation againſt no <hi>way,</hi> no <hi>work</hi> but that, onely becauſe it is an <hi>holy way,</hi> and a <hi>godly work.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:111850:37"/> a way of <hi>ſuffering</hi> it may be, a way of <hi>periſhing</hi> it cannot be.</p>
                  <p>Not a periſhing way! See yonder, <hi>The Beaſt ſhall make war</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>againſt them, ſhall overcome them and kill them;</hi> Then ſee where <note place="margin">Rev. 11. 7.</note> their bodies lye, and how long, and how merry the Adverſary is over them, very jocund and glad when he hath done ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploit upon thoſe that <hi>tormented them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We have a proverbe, he that <hi>laughs after laughs too,</hi> and more <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                     </label> heartily; he that laughs before, is as he that girdeth-on his harnes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he knows not what may happen to damp his mirth: But he that laughes after ſees all clear before him, and is as he, that putteth his harneſſe off. Certainly, for It was never queſtioned yet, Theſe <hi>witneſſes</hi> ſhall have their time again to laugh, when the Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries ſhall <hi>gnaw</hi> their <hi>tongues for paine.</hi> But to the point. We have ſeene the worſt that can befall the men of GOD in GODS <hi>way</hi> and upon His <hi>worke;</hi> and how ſmall a thing do we ſee? Some <hi>Dead bodies.</hi> I muſt take leave now, To ſpeake according to my underſtanding and to his capacity, alſo who, if he meets with a <hi>Dead body,</hi> takes it to be a <hi>Carkeſſe,</hi> all life is gone: Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe theſe are not <hi>carkeſſes, for</hi> if ſo, They had not layne ſo long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ground, in the <hi>ſtreet of the great Citty:</hi> nor had the Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary any Cauſe to <hi>rejoyce over them</hi> (indeed he hath not, but I ſpeake with reſpect to the offence of a <hi>dead body,</hi> lying uncover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) or hinder their bodies <hi>to be put in the graves.</hi> 
                     <note n="(c)" place="margin">Rev. 11. 9.</note> They were <hi>myſtically</hi> dead ſure, for ſuch alſo is their <hi>reſurrection,</hi> their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>life again:</hi> I think thus it was, and yet I cannot expreſſe it in words what <hi>Antichriſtian Rome,</hi> far more cruel then <hi>heathen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Rome:</hi> (She was a Dragon fell and Cruell, but not ſo Cruell, as a <hi>Lamb</hi> with <hi>hornes,</hi> as Shee is, that looks like a ſheepe, and is ſo in her clothing, but inwardly is a greevous wolfe: O beware of her, and her Religion: ſhe is MYSTERY BABYLON the GREAT, <hi>The mother of Harlots, And abominations of the earth,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 17. 5.</note> and hath no more good in her, then what can be found in the <hi>bottomleſſe pit,</hi> from whence her Power and Authority <hi>aſcendeth.)</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 11. 7.</note> I was ſaying, That <hi>death</hi> there is not properly ſo called; but <hi>my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtically;</hi> thus I thinke it was, Rome with her ſworne ſervants, hath done (and will doe) all the indignities, that are Imaginable againſt theſe <hi>witneſſes, ſuſpending, putting out of office, Defaming, Defacing, Degrading;</hi> Truly I know not what, but what <hi>Rome</hi>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:111850:38"/> (that delights in proud wrath) could doe, ſhee hath done, and will doe againſt theſe witneſſes. And how far doth their malice reach? To the <hi>Body,</hi> no farther: And that was <hi>Dead</hi> in <hi>law</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (the <hi>Body is dead becauſe of ſin)</hi> The <hi>Body,</hi> It is GODS build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we muſt thinke and eſteeme honourably of it, for it ſhall be a <hi>Glorious body:</hi> but as it is here, and in compariſon, the people of GOD put little or no account upon it, and it is according to the Spirits allowance; The Body is not mentioned in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but with this addition, a <hi>Dead, a vile, a corruptible Bodie:</hi> The <hi>Soule</hi> ſtands for All, and indeed it is All, that we might put eſteeme upon it more then upon all the world. We ſee <hi>Bodies</hi> and <hi>dead</hi> bodies there, then the Adverſary can but kill the <hi>Bodie,</hi> their proud wrath can reach no farther: They can but take downe that Tabernacle, which, had it ſtood a little longer, would have fel of its ſelf; God has never given a man His ſecurity, That his Body ſhall be kept from periſhing. The ſtreame of the promiſe runs ſtill to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Soule;</hi> I was in the very mouth of Danger, ſayes <hi>Paul,</hi> almoſt ſwallowed up there: I was delivered at <hi>that time: Nero</hi> (he was the Lyon) had not power over me at that time: And the <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 17.</note> LORD ſhall <hi>deliver me, there</hi> is his ſecurity: from what? from <hi>Nero?</hi> No, hee ſayes not ſo; for at length (when <hi>Paul</hi> had finiſhed his <hi>teſtimony)</hi> he was given up to that devourer: The <hi>Lord ſhall deliver me from every evill worke:</hi> An evil worke, a complying with the workers of iniquity, and with their wicked wayes, that is worſe then the <hi>Devourers</hi> mouth, a thouſand times worſe: ſo nor <hi>Paul</hi> nor the <hi>witneſſes</hi> did doe. Now take all, <hi>will preſerve me to His heavenly Kingdome,</hi> Thats all indeed; and makes amends for all, <hi>will preſerve me to His heavenly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> where the <hi>dead bodies</hi> now, that have all the diſhonours put upon them, that are conceivable, ſhall be glorious Bodies. We have viewed the <hi>Bodies,</hi> now we conſider where they lie.</p>
                  <p>2 Where lye they? In <hi>the ſtreet,</hi> All the diſgrace that can bee imagined ſhall be put upon them, that will doe their Duty, if they come into their Adverſaries hand, and it ſhall be done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them in the <hi>openeſt place,</hi> where the Adverſary may glut his eye in the exerciſe of <hi>proud wrath,</hi> wherewith his heart is filled. To expreſſe it as we read, The Adverſary having made himſelfe drunke with blood, will make theſe <hi>witneſſes</hi> a GA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ZIMG-STOCK,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:111850:38"/> by <hi>reproches and afflictions; a ſpectacle to the world, Angels and men.</hi> 
                     <note n="(d)" place="margin">Heb. 10. 13. 1 Cor. 4. 9.</note> Why then, who is on Gods ſide, who? he that is reſolved to take Gods part muſt expect ſuch uſage, but then he may expect ſuch an exceeding and ſuperlative com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort as will countervail and make amends for all. If all the comforts in the world were diſtilled into one <hi>elixir,</hi> &amp; put into theſe witneſſes hands, it would not be ſo cordiall as this which follows; All this villanous uſage upon theſe <hi>Bodies</hi> ſhall bee done; where? where <hi>alſo our</hi> LORD CHRIST <hi>was Crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> That was without the Gates of Jeruſalem. True; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the territories too, by a <hi>Law</hi> not their own, for the <hi>Iews</hi> could put no man to Death, but from <hi>Caeſar Tiberius,</hi> he was the Emperour in Rome; It is very comfortable: what follows? There alſo our <hi>Lord was Crucified: But rejoyce in as much as ye</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4. 13.</note> 
                     <hi>are partakers of Chriſts ſufferings; that when His glory ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, ye may be glad alſo with exceeding joy.</hi> Who would not rejoyce to be put to <hi>open ſhame</hi> for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> where Chriſt was put to open ſhame for him? A great <hi>Commander</hi> refuſed a Crowne of gold in that place, where the <hi>Lord</hi> Chriſt had put upon him a Crowne of thornes. There is a continuall ſpring of comfort from thence, which abundantly makes amends for all the <hi>proud wrath,</hi> put forth againſt theſe <hi>Bodies,</hi> in the <hi>ſtreet of the great City: There alſo our Lord was crucified.</hi> They ſhall ſuffer no more, but what their <hi>Lord</hi> hath ſuffered before them; and in that He hath <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4. 13.</note> ſuffered that <hi>ſhame,</hi> He ſuffered it for them, that their ſhame now might be their <hi>glory.</hi> Truly there is a comfort contained in theſe words, that is not expreſſible but by the mouthes of theſe <hi>witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> And they felt it then, even a joy unſpeakable. I ſay then, when that <hi>wicked woman,</hi> that abominable ſtrumpet, with her <note place="margin">Rev. 11. 10.</note> lovers, were ſo jocund and joyfull over them, making <hi>merry and ſending gifts one to another:</hi> for this is a concluſion of experience, That GOD leaves not His <hi>Servants (Orphanes) comfortleſſe:</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">John. 14. 18. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> At ſuch a time as this, when they are in the eyes of man, <hi>father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe,</hi> friendleſſe, helpleſſe, in the hands of <hi>proud wrath,</hi> exerciſing all the indignities, that are imaginable upon them, and glutting their eye therewith, then they are <hi>orphans,</hi> (you will ſay) for all have left them, and there they lie as you ſee. But now marke the promiſe, <hi>I will not leave you (Orphans) comfortleſſe: I will come</hi>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:111850:39"/> 
                     <hi>to you:</hi> nay He is come, it is in the preſent tenſe, now He is come in, for all the creature-comforts are gone forth, then <hi>God</hi> comes <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> in, in that ſeaſon and nick of time: And if there be any comfort in His preſence, as ſure there is, for He is The <hi>God</hi> of comforts, and <note place="margin">God ſpeaks to His people moſt comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in a Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe. The ſweeteſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts come forth of the greateſt ſtraits.</note> the Father, not of ſome, but of <hi>all conſolations:</hi> then they are ſure to find it at ſuch a time, when they are, in the eye of the world, <hi>comfortleſſe,</hi> free among the dead, put to open ſhame, and the Adverſary, jocund and merry over them. Then is <hi>Gods</hi> time to come-in, and that is His <hi>Promiſe,</hi> and it is comfort enough for the preſent: For after-time reade on, how theſe faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants have concluded, That, after the rate of their ſorrows and ſufferings, ſhall their comforts and conſolations be: And by the meaſure of their ſhame and reproach for <hi>Chriſt</hi> here, ſhall their robe of Glory be cut-out hereafter, wherewith they ſhall be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in heaven. So they have concluded, and cannot faint in their mindes.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Conſider how long the <hi>Bodies</hi> ſhall lye there; how long ſhall they be ſo diſpitefully uſed? <hi>Three dayes and a halfe.</hi> They are long dayes, as we account length of time, who account GODS Patience a <hi>ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ckneſſe;</hi> But were they three thouſand yeeres, yet that length of time makes no difference in eternity. Their ſoules are ſafe enough; Souls and Bodies ſhall meet againe, The ſpirit of life from GOD <hi>ſhall enter into them:</hi> and then they, that were ſo merry and glad over them, ſhall be ſad enough, <hi>for great feares ſhall fall on them:</hi> And quickly after theſe <hi>turmoiles</hi> they ſhall be for <hi>ever with the Lord,</hi> more glorious then the ſun when he ſhines in his ſtrength; for their bodies were put to open ſhame for Chriſt, and where He <hi>was crucified</hi> (Oh it was a ſweet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration) and ſo long, three <hi>whole long Dayes:</hi> now they ſhall have ſuch a length of Glory, that we have not a thought to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure it. He that hath obſerved this, hath let it ſinke down into his heart, and he will hold to the <hi>way</hi> and <hi>worke</hi> of The LORD, &amp; his countenance wil be no more <hi>ſad:</hi> He may heare ſad things, and obſerve croſſe <hi>wayes,</hi> and croſſe <hi>wills;</hi> hee may ſmart under the execution of <hi>proud wrath:</hi> But he hath reſolved all into this, <hi>The will of The</hi> LORD <hi>be done.</hi> He is moſt content, That GOD ſhould goe that way, which ſhall make moſt for His <hi>Glory,</hi> Who will make, as we ſhall ſee anon, all croſſe <hi>wayes</hi> and <hi>wills</hi> meet at
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:111850:39"/> that higheſt point; and in a ſweet harmony, conſent, good agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and a full anſwerableneſſe to His moſt <hi>Holy will.</hi> In the mean time he doth, and by the grace of <hi>God,</hi> is reſolved to do his duty, and to hold to the <hi>way,</hi> all the faithfull have gone in before him, maintaining his watch over his enemies, himſelf alſo, and his own wayes, ſo finding abundance of Peace. This followes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Now Gods Worke goes on, and His Servants do their duty. The Divell rageth and watcheth to doe miſcheife: Therefore the Righteous maintayne their</hi> watch <hi>and guard alſo; but ſpecially over themſelves, Conſidering the</hi> manner <hi>of their Adverſaries, and of their</hi> Maſters <hi>comming.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>VVAtchfullneſſe over the Enemy, and a mans ſelfe, is the great duty of a Chriſtian, renders him <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> highly honoured of GOD; and <hi>ſecure</hi> againſt his Adverſary;</p>
                  <p>Firſt, <hi>Bleſſed is he that watcheth,</hi> 
                     <note n="(a)" place="margin">Rev. 16. 14.</note> for he will keep his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſo that <hi>the ſhame</hi> of his <hi>nakedneſſe ſhall not appeare:</hi> And <note place="margin">
                        <hi>(b)</hi> Rev. 3. 18.</note> The LORD wil honour thoſe Servants, whom He <hi>finds watching,</hi> with the greateſt honour that can be imagined: <hi>He will gird himſelfe, and come forth and ſerve them.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Luke 12. 37.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, Secure. They who are found watching, are ſecure againſt their Adverſary; he comes like a <hi>roaring</hi> Lion, thinking to doe miſchiefe, (for that is the purpoſe of his heart) but he can doe them no <hi>hurt,</hi> for he finds them waking in their watch-tower.</p>
                  <p>So we come to the <hi>Duty;</hi> we have ſeen the honour of it, the ſecurity in it: now ſee the <hi>nec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſitie,</hi> to be now, as in all times, the ſervants of The LORD have been, WATCHFULL. They are bold and fearleſſe, becauſe they make their <hi>watch</hi> ſtrong: They maintain a wakefull eye over the Adverſary, to prevent his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming againſt them, To hinder <hi>the work.</hi> What needs that? you <note place="margin">Nehe. 4. 1. Jer. 31. 28.</note> will ſay, The <hi>Watchman</hi> of Iſrael keeps His ſervants, <hi>I will watch over them to build and to plant, ſaith the Lord:</hi> And His Angels are a guard about them. True, But all this doth not make them
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:111850:40"/> carnally ſecure; but indeed the more watchfull: <hi>Gods</hi> watching over His ſervants, His giving His Angels charge over them, doth not give them licenſe to ſnore in the daytime, or to ſleep in their harveſt: No, they are in <hi>Gods</hi> way, and upon <hi>Gods</hi> work, then, as The <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> ſaid to His Diſciples, <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 26. 45.</note> 
                     <hi>Sleep on now and take your reſt.</hi> He knew that could not be, No time for ſleeping then: So theſe ſervants of The <hi>Lord</hi> cannot <hi>ſleep</hi> now, now they are in Gods way and work, for they muſt look for all the oppoſition the devill and his Angels can make againſt them, but the fruit of all that old enmity, that is in the Spirit, which rules in and amongſt the children of diſobedience. There is no enemie in all the world, but, if you doe meet him, it will be in GODS <hi>way,</hi> and when you are upon GODS <hi>worke,</hi> Church-work, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple-work, making up the breaches in Jeruſalems walls: there the Adverſaries are, there, &amp;c. then they will appeare in their likeneſſe, the <hi>Lion,</hi> the <hi>Adder,</hi> and the <hi>Dragon, Sanballat</hi> and <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biah,</hi> and the <hi>Arabian</hi> 
                     <note n="(c)" place="margin">Nehe. 6. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>too,</hi> and <hi>the reſt of your enemies,</hi> there they will meet you upon That WALL, and perhaps be upon you before you are aware. If the Adverſary may have his will, ye ſhall neither <hi>know</hi> nor <hi>ſee.</hi> And behold a ſtrange greeting; you <note place="margin">Neh. 4 11.</note> had as good meet with a Beare robbed of her whelps, for you wil find that Adverſary, the very ſame he was, very <note n="(a)" place="margin">Nehe. 4. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>wroth, taking great indignation againſt the work, and the way; perhaps</hi> he will now, as then, mock too, and grin like a dog.</p>
                  <p>So it hath been ever ſince the firſt reſtoring of the Church; When <hi>Moſes</hi> came into Egypt, and made his demands, very peremptory, (for ſuch are the demands of GOD touching His ſervice) he would have all to an hoofe, not leave ſo much as a hoofe in Egypt: Then we reade what followed. How it was after their returne from Babylon, <hi>Ezra</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah</hi> have told us. It was ſo in latter times towards the cloſe of the former <hi>Centurie,</hi> and beginning of this, when <hi>Luther</hi> appeared in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie,</hi> ſpoiling the Pope and his <hi>Merchants</hi> of that great gaine and in-come by <hi>Indulgences, (It</hi> was an ordinary Merchandize with thoſe cunning Merchants, for amongſt their wares they have the precious <hi>ſoules of men.</hi> 
                     <note n="(d)" place="margin">Rev. 18. 13.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>So I ſay, it was when <hi>Luther</hi> appeared in <hi>Germanie,</hi> that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious inſtrument, confounding the Pope and his cunning Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:111850:40"/> reſcuing the cauſe of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and advancing His Glory; Then, and not till then, <hi>Germanie</hi> was full of <hi>ſtirs,</hi> a <hi>tumultuous</hi> Nation; Hell ſeemed to be let looſe, and the devils roaring upon him; But then <hi>Luther</hi> was as bold as a Lion, yet as wiſe as a Serpent; He was upon GODS <hi>worke,</hi> and in His <hi>way,</hi> that made him bold and confident; and ſo he would have <hi>Melanchthon</hi> then to be <hi>ſtrong in The Lord,</hi> (his incouragements are notable;) he did live <hi>amongst Lions,</hi> his <hi>ſoule lay amongst thoſe that were ſet on fire,</hi> that <hi>kept him waking and watchfull;</hi> but thus he did encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage himſelfe in The LORD, he was in <hi>Gods</hi> way, and upon His work. A marvellous comfort, and which commands an holy ſecurity; his heart might <hi>meditate terrour,</hi> but it commands <hi>watchfulneſſe</hi> too, even to doe as the Builders or Reformers did in ancient dayes, <hi>Make your praier unto God,</hi> and <hi>ſet watch againſt them day and night,</hi> becauſe <hi>of them:</hi> For, as the Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries ſaid then, ſo they ſay now; and therefore what the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants did then, ſo they muſt doe now, <hi>Set the people</hi> in their <hi>cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes with</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Nehe. 4 89.</note> 
                     <hi>their ſwords, their ſpeares, and their bowes, and the builders every one gird his ſword by his ſide,</hi> and ſo build. And though they doe put off their clothes, which the builders then did not, (ſaving <hi>that everie one put them off for waſhing)</hi> yet they muſt keep a ſtrong watch, and their ſword under their pillow. <note place="margin">Read <hi>M. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cemens</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon upon <hi>Neh.</hi> 4. 11. wherein, by the good hand of God with him, he hath diſcovered the adverſaries <hi>skirts</hi> upon their face; he hath ſhewn the Nation their nakedneſſe, and the 3. Kingdoms their ſhame; he hath caſt abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable filth upon them, &amp; made them as they are, vile.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is watchful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>neſſe, and as needfull now as then (for now the breaches are ſtopping up) <hi>now the</hi> enemy ſaith, <hi>The builders ſhall not</hi> know <hi>neither ſee till we come in the midſt amongst them and ſlay them.</hi> We are aſſured that all the enemies in the world, are now ſetting themſelves againſt this <hi>way,</hi> and conſulting how they may hinder this <hi>worke:</hi> It is temple-worke, the reſtoring and building Ieruſalems walls. There is need of watchfullneſſe then, mighty cauſe to maintaine a continuall watch over this <hi>Legion</hi> (for he is <hi>many</hi> and full of wrath) as great cauſe to watch as <hi>David</hi> had, when <hi>Saul ſent, and they did watch the houſe to kill him. (* title of the</hi> 59 <hi>Pſal.)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is obſervable, That where the ſervants of The <hi>Lord</hi> have their warrant for their greateſt ſecurity, there they may obſerve cauſe enough why they ſhould be exceeding watchfull. <hi>A vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard of red wine is My Church,</hi> My people, <hi>unto Mee,</hi> moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and moſt Delightfull: <hi>I The</hi> LORD <hi>doe keep it: I will water</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>(d)</hi> Rev. 18. 13.</note>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:111850:41"/> 
                     <hi>it every moment leſt any hurt it, I will keepe it night and day.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">ver. 3.</note> There is ſecurity. Obſerve now what a mighty Adverſary the Church hath (not to ſpeake of the little foxes, and other grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Beaſts, wherewith <hi>Gods</hi> vine-yard is annoyed) <hi>Leviathan,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">ver. 1.</note> the <hi>peircing ſerpent,</hi> even <hi>Leviathan that crooked ſerpent;</hi> The ſpirit meanes, All the divells in hell, and all his ſervants on earth, their force and fraud both: And how prevailing by theſe wayes, This Adverſary is, we may collect by the inſtrument. The LORD brings forth againſt him, <hi>His ſore, and great, and ſtrong ſword;</hi> very comfortable to the Church all this, but it is very ſtirring and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding to keep their watch ſtrong, their garments <hi>white</hi> and cloſe girt unto them. Bee ſober, bee vigilant, becauſe your adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary the divell, as a roaring lion, walketh about ſeeking whom <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5. 8.</note> he may devoure. The concluſion is, The Righteous muſt be full of eyes; They had need to ſet a Thouſand eyes over this Adverſary rather; that is firſt; And then</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Then thouſand eyes over themſelves, even that every man maintaine over himſelfe now, a double watch, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they are the ſouldiers of Jeſus Chriſt, engaged in the warre <hi>with the Lambe,</hi> and going out againſt the <hi>Lambes enemies,</hi> and muſt keep themſelves, according to the charge, <hi>from every wicked thing:</hi> therefore had they need (as the devout Spaniard ſaid) to <note place="margin">Deut. 23. 9.</note> ſet ten thouſand eyes over themſelves: then againe, conſider, A mans enemies are thoſe of his own houſe; enemies alſo, and thoſe the ſtrongeſt within his own breaſt.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Adde to this; That we know not the <hi>day, nor the houre;</hi> but the comming of the <hi>Lord</hi> will be at midnight, in the midnight of the world, when they ſay <hi>all is peace,</hi> and think they may be ſecure, and ſo fall all aſleep, then He comes as a <hi>thiefe.</hi> Put all this together, and it will command watchfulneſſe; wee ſhall double our watch, we ſhall make it ſtrong, That we may be in a readineſſe, with our <hi>loines girt,</hi> our <hi>armour at hand,</hi> for, as we ſaid, we know not at what time danger and trouble may come. We know not the houre, when the generall Judgement, nor when the particular ſhall be; we <hi>know not the houre;</hi> when we lye downe, we know not how we may be awakened, with what cry, nor what noiſe we may heare at midnight. What lyeth in the wombe of a day, is darkneſſe unto us; and what a night may
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:111850:41"/> bring forth, lyeth in the ſame wombe of darkneſſe alſo: Wee cannot ſee into an houre before us. Happy is that man that makes his watch ſtrong, that fortifies himſelfe in The <hi>Lord</hi> his <hi>God,</hi> That keeps himſelf in His feare all the day long, and night alſo; That cloſeth his eyes with GOD, and makes his <hi>Chriſt</hi> the end of his thoughts: ſo ſleeps, as in the lap or arms of The Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty. This man is prepared, and what ever the cry be, with which he is awakened, he is in a readineſſe, his <hi>loines</hi> girt, his <hi>lampe</hi> burning, and oyle for ſupply. So he goes forth to meet, and if he meet with enemies, nay, with devils, he is in a readineſſe, and as bold as a Lion: But if he goe forth to meet his LORD and CHRIST, O how joyfull is he! Him he ſerved all his life long, with Him his laſt thoughts cloſed, when he fell aſleep: therefore in the morning of his awaking, he is bold, and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, joyfull and glad; all his dayes he watched for this time, as the Watch-man for the morning.</p>
                  <p>To draw to a concluſion. Truly this Mother-City, the City of <hi>God,</hi> have done even thus as we heard, and as we all ſhould doe ſo they wait for GOD, ſo they <hi>love</hi> GOD, ſo they <hi>feare Him,</hi> ſo they <hi>Truſt</hi> in HIM, ſo they <hi>obey:</hi> And, to make clear proof that ſo they do, ſo watchfull they are over the Adverſary, And themſelves. And ſo, they thank their GOD, they have profited very much by all the <hi>hatred,</hi> the <hi>hard words,</hi> &amp; <hi>ungodly deeds</hi> from the adverſary: his violent dealing hath made their <hi>love</hi> the hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, their <hi>feare</hi> more refined, and fixed, their <hi>confidence</hi> better bottomed, more ſetled upon the rock, their <hi>obedience</hi> more pure, more ſingle, and more hearty, and their <hi>watch</hi> a thouſand times ſtronger, againſt their enemies, and over themſelves. Thus all things tend to the advantage of His people, and work <hi>together</hi> for their good, which muſt be conſidered on, now in the laſt place.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:111850:42"/>
                  <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>We muſt not judge haſtily of</hi> Gods <hi>works, Theſe are wrought in an excellent Method, though they ſeeme confuſed to us, and doe worke</hi> together <hi>for the good of them, that love</hi> God; <hi>whereunto the preſent time gives cleare evidence.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>GReat are the works of The Lord, <hi>Sought out of them that take pleaſure therein;</hi> SOUGHT OUT with diligent inquiry, not with a curious prying into them, much leſſe with an over-haſty cenſuring and judging of them; here we muſt walk ſoftly, taking leaſure.</p>
                  <p>We muſt not judge of the <hi>acts</hi> of GODS <hi>providence</hi> by pieces, here a part and there a part; as we do not a peice of <hi>Arrace,</hi> not halfe unfolded: ſtay till GOD hath done His <hi>whole worke,</hi> hath accompliſhed it upon <hi>mount Zion,</hi> then unfold the work, and behold a glorious ſymme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>try and uniformity <hi>all together</hi> workeing for the good of thoſe, that <hi>love Him.</hi> If we looke upon GODS works apart and alone, here one piece and there another, they will be as unpleaſing to the eye, as are the members of a body divided, and lying apart from the head: They will ſeeme fearfull and terrible, wondrous croſſe to the marke they tend to.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ioſeph</hi> muſt be a prime and cheife man in <hi>Egypt;</hi> look you how croſſe all things goe! he is ſold for a ſervant, and it was well he ſcaped ſo; when he had gained no little favour, and became a great maſter, then his feet were put in the ſtocks.</p>
                  <p>Things went as croſſe with <hi>David</hi> too. How long? To the very day (I reckon within a few houres) he was to be King, that very day the <hi>people ſpoke of ſtoning of him.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Sam. 30 6.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>GODS providence ſeemed as ſtrange, and as croſſe towards <hi>Mordecai;</hi> and as favourable to <hi>Haman,</hi> That Enemy and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary; <hi>Mordecai</hi> muſt ride in ſtate through the city, and <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> muſt lead the horſe, and lacquie by; and ſo it was. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that day came, <hi>Haman</hi> was very confident, That he ſhould ſee <hi>Mordecai</hi> ſet on high upon a gallows, which he had provided for his purpoſe. Truly the admonition is ſeaſonable; <hi>Iudge no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:111850:42"/> 
                     <hi>before the time, but</hi> remember theſe are GODS workes, and He will work like a GOD, His <hi>providences,</hi> what ever they ſeeme to be now, they wil appeare to be admirable, exceeding glorious; <note place="margin">Little can we by the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of any action, gueſſe at Gods inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the concluſion.</note> Now here is a piece of providence, and it ſeemes terrible; here is another piece and cauſeth diſtractions; A third piece, and that cauſeth a <hi>ſword;</hi> here is a fourth piece, and Oh how croſſe it is to the high marke it tends to! for there be thoughts of <hi>accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation,</hi> of compounding the cauſe of Chriſt, and that is a croſſe way indeed: ſo we judge before the time, ſtay a little while and we ſhall ſee all theſe croſſe wayes meet, and kiſſe each other: ſo as we ſhall ſay, in the cloſe of the work, All was carried on in a curious Method; things ſeeme to be carried very confuſedly in our eye, up and downe, and then a croſſe as upon wheeles: But there is a <hi>wheele within the wheeles and</hi> eyes, (providences) <note place="margin">Ezech. 1.</note> round about. If we could ſee we would ſay; All things are carried in an excellent Method. The lines of Gods providence drawn in the circumference of the world, ſeeme no leſſe confuſed then the moaths in the ſun.</p>
                  <p>But we ſhall ſee one day, That not one line could be ſpared; And that all tend Directly to the great <hi>center, The Glory of the Workman</hi> and <hi>The reſt of His people.</hi> We think we ſee crooked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, an unevenneſſe in the lines and wayes of Gods Providence; But we are deceived; mans wayes are unequall, Gods wayes are equall: ſtay a little, we ſhall ſay ſo too. I ſaid well, ſtay a while, as thoſe that <hi>live by faith,</hi> and do not <hi>make haſte,</hi> untill GOD hath wrought His whole worke, till we can put <hi>all together;</hi> Then we ſhall diſcerne plainly, That <hi>all together</hi> worked gloriouſly for the promoting the great, ſupreame and ſoveraigne ends, GODS <hi>Glory</hi> and HIS <hi>Churches peace,</hi> in the exalting His people, pluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down and confounding the Adverſary.</p>
                  <p>Nay GOD hath not wearied out His people, with expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Though He hath not yet accompliſhed His <hi>whole worke,</hi> yet He gives His people leave to behold ſome pieces thereof; And ſee how wonderfull and admirable they are, what ſtrange pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences, croſſe wayes, as was ſaid, hath he made to meet; contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry natures, and wills have wrought effectually towards the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Truth and Peace, that theſe might meete in a ſweet agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Take a view of it at once, and behold the poyſon of Aſpes,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:111850:43"/> viperous tongues, embalming; wounds, healing; weakneſſe, ſtrengthening; temptations, fortifying; ſtraits, enlarging; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe counſels, enſnaring (the perverſe counſellours:) fears, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting; diſtractions, uniting; troubles, quieting; ſtops &amp; preſſures to beare down the ſpirits of men, heightening the ſame. Thus the LORD hath done in this ſhort time. What then may the people of GOD expect to ſee in after time, when the work is done, and they can put <hi>all together,</hi> who have ſeen ſuch ſtrange providences, and glorious workings thereof already? He that hath wrought ſo gloriouſly, and hath given His people ſuch a diſcerning, will worke much more, and will be admired in the cloſe of His whole work when His people can put all together.</p>
                  <p>Now we are to conſider with more enlagement what The LORD hath done, making croſſe wayes meete in a good agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and croſſe ſpirits to ſtand in a poſture for the ſafeguarding His Kingdome; And what a good GOD do His people ſerve! who would not feare Him? who would not ſerve ſuch a <hi>God?</hi> who would not truſt Him now? Hee makes all work for good; All that we call evil; and to ſenſe it is ſo, is good to them; never any thing in the world fell out to The people of GOD whereof they could not ſay, <hi>this is good now,</hi> for it works thereunto; and which is yet more comfort, they can ſay confidently, <hi>it will be better anon,</hi> within an hower, a minute, a little minute. GODS Hand is with them, and through Him they improove all, good and evill, all is good to them; they find it ſo or they make it ſo: or, rather againſt the nature thereof, it is made ſo to them: things diſagreeing are made to agree very well, and impoſſible things to be poſſible, for ſo we read, if we read the Hiſtory of theſe laſt months. Can a man imagine, (who walkes by ſenſe) but that the noiſe of ſwords, and ſtaves would ſilence the lawes, and daunt the ſpirits of men utterly? yet it was not ſo, This noiſe wakened the lawes, and raiſed the ſpirits the higher: would we not think that the ſword would make diviſions? It was taken up for that end, and ſo it works moſt naturally. But ſo it ſhall not do, It ſhall worke contrary effects: it ſhall cement and ſodder men to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: It ſhall make many to be as one man, of one mind in a houſe, and ſo to ſeek the peace of Iſrael.</p>
                  <p>Yea but the ſword drawes blood, makes havock in the Land, It robbs, and ſpoiles, &amp;c.</p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:111850:43"/>
                  <p> Very true: but it had made more havock, had it come upon us, and found us ſleeping: then it had cut all our throats. It had raged all the Land over with a rage <hi>reaching unto heaven,</hi> as now in <hi>Ireland.</hi> Bleſſed be <hi>God,</hi> we know our friends now, we ſee our enemies, the Papiſts and Atheiſts all the World over. It is not a Kingdome divided againſt it ſelfe, but one Kingdome divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt another: The <hi>Kingdome</hi> of CHRIST againſt the Kingdome of Antichriſt. And this Antichriſtian kingdom will rage as they can, <hi>to their power to ſhed blood,</hi> But The LORD hath them in His chaine, and hath cauſed His people to ſet a <hi>watch</hi> over them: and hath ſent forth His Hoſt againſt them: There is this good in it now, and it is a great good, The enemies of the Church are in part manifeſt now: they ſhall be more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt anon. So are her friends, ſhee knowes now and can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve her ſelfe in the queſtion, <hi>Who will riſe up for mee againſt the evill doers?</hi> or who <hi>will ſtand up for me againſt the workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity?</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 94. 16.</note> The Church cannot forſake her confidence now in her GOD; He that hath wrought HITHERTO will worke: He that hath diſcovered the Adverſary: He that hath made their madneſſe ſo manifeſt, will goe on to doe yet more: what will He do? The Church can anſwer, That which ſhall be beſt for her ſons and daughters both for the <hi>time, manner</hi> and <hi>meanes</hi> of doing it, though all this they leave in their LORDS hand, let Him work as He pleaſeth, if in the dark, and His foot-ſteps are upon the waters, and no print of them, yet, as Maſter <hi>Bradford</hi> ſaid, ſo ſaith the Church, <hi>She will follow her</hi> LORD <hi>in the dark.</hi> Though he ſeeme to goe by compaſſe, by the bow, as we call it, yet Hee goes the ſtraighteſt, and neereſt courſe to His GLORY, carrying all levell thereunto. The Church is marvailouſly contented with this, (That all works for her <hi>Lords</hi> Glory) her ſpirit ſhall work after Him, even the ſtrength of her ſpirit, in that way He goes, though clouded and over-ſhadowed with da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kneſſe: for ſhe is confident, This very way wherein ſhe ſees not the prints of all his foot-ſteps, (ſhe ſees very much) tends moſt directly to her full comfort here, and her glory hereafter.</p>
                  <p>The Church hath ſeene ſo much of <hi>God,</hi> ſuch ſweet experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſo many providences, ſo ſtrange, ſo wonderfull, ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings-in of <hi>God</hi> unto her, when in her Egypt, in her wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:111850:44"/> that ſhe cannot diſtruſt him now. <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 22. 4.</note>
                     <hi>Our fathers truſted in thee:</hi> What follows? Thou <hi>didſt deliver them: They cryed unto thee,</hi> and they <hi>were delivered.</hi> Though we are full of chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, yet <hi>God</hi> is the ſame to His Church for ever: And to diſtruſt now after all this, were a provocation as was theirs (by <hi>unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe)</hi> at <hi>the</hi> SLA, <hi>even at the</hi> RED <hi>Sea.</hi> The Church cannot queſtion <hi>Gods</hi> love to her, nor dare ſhe queſtion His <hi>Power;</hi> Hee is GOD, The <hi>King</hi> of His Church, He reigneth in the midſt of His enemies, and then like Himſelf, moſt gloriouſly. He brought along Captivity upon His people for THEIR GOOD. He hath <note place="margin">Jer. 24 5.</note> ordered our diſtractions ſo, that they have beene for <hi>our good.</hi> How ſo? GOD will have it ſo, and we need not ask a queſtion, when we ſee it to be ſo, diſtractions for GOOD. They have ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to union, and joyning together, the good with the good ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver faſter, the bad with the bad never cloſer, like the ſcales of the <hi>Leviathan,</hi> they ſtick together that they cannot be ſundred. Croſſe ſpirits, who will be oppoſite, and ſpurne againſt the pricks for <hi>their hurt,</hi> theſe ſhall be ſuffered and countenanced for the <hi>good of His people,</hi> To make them more in <hi>love</hi> with <hi>Truth,</hi> to <hi>contend</hi> for it more earneſtly, in a more orderly and unanimous way, now that they ſee <hi>all the wicked,</hi> all the Malignants of the world are bent and doe contend againſt them: Then we muſt conclude, All tends to advance GODS glory and His peoples good; Their <hi>fears</hi> have wrought for GOOD; it hath made them <hi>wait patiently for God;</hi> it hath made their <hi>love</hi> more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, their <hi>feare</hi> more refined, their <hi>dependance</hi> more glorious, their <hi>obedience</hi> more ſincere and hearty, their <hi>watch</hi> ten thouſand times ſtronger againſt their adverſaries, and over themſelves. Bleſſed be GOD who hath done all this, made their <hi>fears</hi> and diſquietings to pull downe and ſpoile their owne ſtrong-holds, <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Sin,</hi> and to build up and fortifie their impregnable Forts, <hi>Love</hi> to <hi>God, Feare</hi> of <hi>God, Confidence</hi> in <hi>God, Obedience</hi> unto <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Watchfulneſſe in all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To ſhut up all. The Righteous <hi>wait</hi> patiently for <hi>God;</hi> they <hi>love</hi> Him, they <hi>feare</hi> Him, they ſtay themſelves upon Him, they <hi>obey</hi> from <hi>the heart,</hi> (if their Obedience were not hearty, their Truſt were preſumption) they make their watch ſtrong over themſelves, and againſt their adverſaries: Goe thou thy way
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:111850:44"/> now, thou art in Gods way, and doe likewiſe, and be no longer <hi>ſad:</hi> if thou ſtandeſt alone now, and there be none that will take thee by <hi>the hand,</hi> unleſſe to thruſt thee downe, yet <hi>fear not:</hi> Though an Hoſt encamp about thee, thou art in <hi>Gods</hi> way, and upon His work, fear not: He will hold thee by His hand, He wil be thy <hi>Arm every morning, thy ſalvation alſo in the time of trouble.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Onely keep to your ſtrong hold, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> hold faſt your confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. Let <hi>ſinners in Zion</hi> be afraid, fearfulneſſe muſt ſurpriſe the Idolatrous Nation, they have no <hi>God</hi> to look unto, no <hi>chambers</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Eſay 26. 20.</note> to enter into, while the indignation paſſeth over: They are now like a tottering wall, and a broken fence; they are falling and daſhing to pieces like a potters veſſell. The Lord <hi>ſees their</hi> day <hi>is comming,</hi> for they are very proud, their rage riſeth high, and ſo many ſteps and degrees to their utter ruine, and everlaſting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion. As the righteous work out their ſalvation with feare and trembling, ſo doe the wicked work out their deſtruction with joy and gladneſſe over the ruines they have made in the world: you can wait upon <hi>God,</hi> you <hi>love</hi> Him, you <hi>feare</hi> Him, you <hi>truſt</hi> in Him. We have concluded. <hi>Our fathers truſted in Thee: they</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 22. 4, 5.</note> 
                     <hi>truſted, and Thou didſt deliver them. They cryed unto Thee and were delivered. For the armes of the wicked ſhall be broken, but</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 37. 17.</note> 
                     <hi>The Lord upholdeth the righteous.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
